Computers: Universe: About Universe

UniVerse is one of a family of Database Management Systems descended from a product called PICK.

In the late sixties, the improbably named Dick Pick, founder of Pick Systems Inc., was developing systems for the American armed forces. He designed the remarkably intuitive and practical system which he gave his name. Sadly, Dick died recently.

His achievement became one of the IT industries best kept secrets: widely used by a remarkably loyal user community, but unheard of outside its own customer base. This was despite a number of companies seizing upon PICK's basic design as being suitable for their own databsae products. McDonnel Douglas, the aviation giant with a strong IT arm, produce a version known as 'Reality'. The French IN2 company cleverly called theirs 'IN2'. Prime Computer Inc., now a subsidiary of Computervision, released first 'Prime INFORMATION' and then 'PI/OPEN'. Cosmos developed an excellent DOS based product for PC's called 'Revelation' (and latterly 'Advanced Revelation' for Windows), and of course VMark brought the first Unix implementation to market in the form of UniVerse.

PICK was originally a complete operating system, running the machine it was installed on: and some of its derivatives took the same form. However, this tended to limit the customers in the use of their hardware, and it must be admitted that whatever PICK's strengths as a DBMS, it was a clunky operating system. When Prime released their product, they implemented it under their existing operating system, but as this was the remarkable but still proprietary 'PRIMOS' it was not a huge step forward in open systems. Cosmos and later VMark capitalised on this weakness by providing PICK-like products for the world's two most popular platforms: DOS/Windows based PC's and Unix based servers and mini-computers.

VMark adopted an agressive marketing position, selling UniVerse not only as a candidate for the development of new corporate systems, but also as an escape route to users of other PICK systems previously wedded to particular hardware manufacturers. By allowing them to port their systems, and the investment those systems contained, to a ubiquituous Unix platform, they hoped to win business from the enormous base of existing PICK clients. In this, they achieved considerable success. It is for this reason that when creating UniVerse 'accounts' (see UniVerse and UNIX below), you are offered different 'flavours' of the product, compatible with what is sometimes called 'generic' PICK, Prime INFORMATION, Reality, IN2, and PI/OPEN, as well as VMark's own synthesis of the best elements of each (in their view) which they christened 'IDEAL'.

Computers: Universe: The UniVerse Paradigm

'Typelessness'

Perhaps the first point to understand, particularly for developers used to other development languages and environments, is that UniVerse is 'typeless'. It does not distinguish the way other languages do between numbers, dates and text: let alone between bytes, words, short integers and long integers. All of its data, without exception, is stored on disk, and manipulated in memory, as strings of ASCII characters.

For instance, if you were to examine some UniVerse data using a low level disk editor, you would find that the value of an invoice for R12.23 was stored as a character 49: the ASCII '1', followed by a character 50, the ASCII '2', and so on.

The treatment of these values in memory is just the same. If a variable in a UniVerse Basic Program, for instance, has a value of '111', you can add '2' to it to make it '113', or concatenate '1' to make it '1112'.

The UniVerse Hierarchy:
Accounts, Files, Records, Fields, Values, and Subvalues

As was explained above (seeUniVerse and UNIX) UniVerse accounts are UNIX directories which contain a basic UniVerse 'file set'. To invoke UniVerse, you must first cd to such a directory under Unix before using the uv command to start UniVerse. If the files UniVerse requires to run do not exist in your current directory, it will inform you that the directory 'is not a valid UniVerse account' and offer to make it one, by copying the necessary files from UniVerses home directory.

These files define UniVerse's behaviour within the account they inhabit. Unlike UNIX, which can search across an entire system for program names corresponding to the commands you enter, or files corresponding to the names you enter, UniVerse interprets commands and filename strictly locally. While you can make a file in one UniVerse account visible to another, you must do this on a file by file basis. Each UniVerse account is essentially a closed environment.

UniVerse files are not quite the same thing as UNIX files. A UniVerse file is more like an Oracle table or a DBase file: it is a collection of records. Naturally, as UniVerse runs over UNIX, each UniVerse file is unlimately implemented as one or more UNIX files, but the way in which this is done is hidden from the UniVerse user. The UNIX implementation of these files will be explained later, but for now it is sufficient to see UniVerse files as the second stage of the UniVerse hierarchy: UniVerse accounts are collections of UniVerse files.

The files contain collections of records, and each record represents a single entity. For instance, if you were running an accounting system, it is likely you would have a CUSTOMERS file: each record in such a file would represent one of your customers. Each would also have a 'key': a unique string associated with the record, allowing it to be accessed directly without searching through the whole file. So far, this is elementary, and most Database Management Systems take this same approach. The difference lies in the consistency with which UniVerse applies this approach. Everything within UniVerse must fit into the Accounts/Files/Records hierarchy, and so each program your write becomes a record in a programs file, and each command in the TCL Universe command language is a record in a special file called the VOC file.

Records are further divided into fields. In a data file (such as the mythical CUSTOMERS file already mentioned) each field in a record has a defined purpose: the first field of each record might store the customers company name, the second their phone number, and so on. However, in some records, the fields do not all represent different 'kinds' of information. For instance, each program in a UniVerse system is a record in a file, and each line of each program is, strictly speaking, a field of that record. Naturally, while the lines of the program must be in a defined order for the program to work, this does not mean that the third field of one program record has the same meaning as the third field of another. UniVerse programmers rarely think of the lines of their programs as fields, but nevertheless this is how they are stored, and in this way they remain within the rules of the UniVerse hierarchy.

Values and subvalues are subdivisions of fields, enabling a single field to store many pieces of information. For instance, if you decide to store the names of your customers children on the CUSTOMERS file, you can define a single field called CHILDREN and record each child's name as a value within that field. If you decided to store all the given names of each child ('John Micheal Steven Smith') you could even divide the values into subvalues: 'multi-valued' fields are very common in UniVerse systems, 'sub-valued' ones, thankfully, less so.

A common and useful technique is the 'association' of multi-valued fields. For instance, if you wished to store the nameand date of birthof each child, you could do so by defining two multivalued fields, CHILD.NAMES and CHILD.DOBS, where the first value in CHILD.NAMES corresponded to the first date in CHILD.DOBS, and so on. This is again a commonly found technique.

Thus the UniVerse structure can be thought of a 6-dimensional. Thus, to find a single piece of data, you must know:

1. Which account the file is in
2. Which file the record is in
3. Which record the field is in
4. Which field the value is in
5. Which value the sub-value is in
6. Which sub-value the data is in.

Unlike UNIX, though, the UniVerse data structure is not recursive. UNIX directories can contain other directories. UniVerse accounts can only contain files, not other accouts; files can only contain records, not other files, and so on.

It was mentioned earlier that all the data in this structure is stored as strings of ASCII characters. Each record, in fact, is a single string. The ASCII character 254 divides each field from the next and is known as a field mark, the ASCII character 253 divides values within fields, and is known as the value mark, and the ASCII character 252 divides each subvalue from the next, and is thus (you guessed it) known as the subvalue mark. In theory, files could be implemented as a single string broken into records, and accounts as a single string broken into files, but the concept is not taken so far. As an interesting note, though, the character 255 is still known as a 'record mark' or 'item mark' (the original PICK term for records being 'items'), but it is very rarely used.

The 'Post-relational' Database Management System

You will sometimes hear UniVerse referred to as a 'post-relational' system, and may have wondered what this meant.

In fact, it is a piece of marketing nonsense which implies two things: (a) Universe is NOT relational, and (b) that's a good thing, not a bad one.

Strictly speaking, a relational database is one which conforms to the 12 relational 'laws' devised by Codd and Date, the originators of 'relational calculus' which underpins the 'relational model', and it is debatable as to whether any commercial database is truly relational: even those which claim to be like Oracle and Ingres. However, UniVerse breaks so many of them that it cannot even pretend to be relational, hence (a).

(b) is more debateable. For instance, one of the reasons UniVerse cannot be considered relational is that it allows 'repeating' or multivalued fields. Of course, you don'thaveto use them in your designs, so is this a problem? The relational laws, though, are designed to make it as difficult as possible to implement non-relational systems. You may, of course, form your own view once you've completed this course.

Personally I think this flexibility is one of UniVerse's strengths. UniVerse allows quick and intuitive development and modelling: it is designed in a simple and pragmatic way, rather than in close adherence to any underlying theory. This does, though, give one a lot of rope. It's still up to us, though, whether we hang ourselves.

Computers: Universe: UniVerse and UNIX

Accounts

A UniVerse account is a UNIX directory containing what might be termed the basic UniVerse 'file set'.

The easiest way to create a UniVerse account is to create an empty UNIX directory, cd to it, and enter the 'uv' command to invoke UniVerse. The UniVerse bin directory contains its executable: if it is not on your path, you will have to enter the full path to the command: something like /universe/bin/uv.

UniVerse will display:

This is not a valid UniVerse account.
Would you like to make it one?

Enter a Y in reply, and you will be offered a choice of Universe 'flavours' (see above: About UniVerse). My own background is in Prime INFORMATION, and that is the flavour used by the EDS team at the Cape of Good Hope bank who form the immediate audience for this guide, so I shall assume you choose the Prime INFORMATION flavour: the differences, though, are generally minor.

A few indecipherable messages will scroll past your screen as UniVerse copies its basic 'file set' into its account, and you will be left at the UniVerse > prompt you will soon grow to love.

At this point, it might be instructive to have a peek at the UNIX directory underlying this UniVerse account. You will discover at this point that none of the UNIX commands you have spent years coming to terms with work from the UniVerse prompt (with one or two minor exceptions) as UniVerse has its own command language. The first command in this language you will now learn: SH opens a UNIX command shell from 'inside' UniVerse. Enter this command know, and at the Unix prompt enter the 'ls' command to take a look.

You will notice six five files and a directory. The files are VOC, D_VOC, VOCLIB, D_VOCLIB, and D_&SAVEDLISTS&: the directory &SAVEDLISTS&. By now you will have noticed several unsettling things:

1. UniVerse commands and filenames are almost entirely in UPPER CASE. Later you will also discover that the keywords and variable names in its programming language Universe Basic are also in upper case. This is a surprise and sometimes a problem for UNIX people, whose 'caps lock' key has usually rusted over from lack of use. Get used to it.

The & character appears appears in two of these names: in fact, it is a favourite of PICK people and appears in the names of many system files, So much so that the UK's leading Prime INFORMATION software house was called &Ampersand Systems Ltd. Be careful when typing these names under UNIX to prefix the & symbols with a backslash, thus: \&SAVEDLISTS\&. You will kick off a lot of phantom processes (which is what & is used for under UNIX) until you get used to this.

3. You had to go to UNIX to get a view of the physical structure of the underlying directory. This is because UniVerse takes a completely different view of what is going on: instead of five UNIX files and one UNIX directory, it can see three UniVerse files complete with 'dictionaries'. What this means you will discover soon, but for now the distinction is worth bearing in mind. UNIX and UniVerse 'files' are related, but are not one to one and not even always under the same names. For this reason, tinkering with the contents of a UniVerse account from UNIX usually causes problems, as UNIX doesn't understand UniVerse and tends to trample across its carefully laid structures: take care until you know how the two systems relate.

Don't forget to enter the UNIX exit command to close the UNIX shell and return to UniVerse...

Computers: Universe: Introduction

Universe is a commercial unix-based pick-derived post-relational multiuser database management system.

Let's take it a bit at a time:

database management system: It's a program which allows users to store, update, and report on large quantities of data.

multiuser: It usually runs on a biggish central computer to which a number of users connect using their PC's or terminals and access data simultaneously.

post-relational: It has a different way of organising data to the ubiquitous 'relational databases' such as, say, Oracle.

pick-derived: It is one of a family of databases based on the original 'Pick' database, designed by the legendary Dick Pick.

unix-based: It was the first and, at time of writing, still the only pick-derived database to run under Unix.

commercial: It's copyrighted by a company called VMark and sold for money.

My first job in IT was as a programmer working with another pick-derived database called Prime INFORMATION, which ran on Prime's own minicomputers. I gradually learnt that Pick was extremely popular with its surprisingly large user base, but little known elsewhere: and consequently Pick programming was something of an esoteric skill to have acquired. At a number of sites I found myself providing consultancy and training to developers familiar with more mainstream technologies where they had taken on responsibility for supporting Pick products.

Life, the Universe, and Everything is a set of notes on Universe I wrote in 1999 while training developers from Electronic Data Systems working at the Cape of Good Hope Bank in Cape Town. They were written rather quickly, and while have reformatted them to suit www.mannyneira.com, I have not otherwise checked or edited them: and indeed no longer have access to either Universe documentation, or a Universe system to play on. They are therefore offered to anyone who might find them either of practical use, or historical interest, but without any promise of accuracy or responsibility for the consequences of inaccuracies. If you find any mistakes, be kind and let me know at mailbox@mannyneira.com

Republishing these notes reminds me that I foolishly allowed myself to lose touch with the old Cape of Good Hope Bank team. If any of them come across this, and feel like getting in touch, I'd love to hear from them too.

Manny Neira, 3rd February 2006

Original 1999 introduction

This guide provides an introduction to VMark's UniVerse Database Management System.

It does not aim to provide a detailed reference guide, as the Universe documentation (which is available on-line in 'Acrobat Reader' format) does this extremely well. Rather, it aims to build a conceptual model, a framework of ideas, which should allow you to approach the mass of detail in VMark's manual with greater confidence and understanding.

The guide has been written for developers already experienced in other languages or development environments, and thus assumes a thorough understanding of IT. It also assumes a very basic competence in Unix, sufficient to log in, create a directory, move from one directory to another, and so on: but this is not a strenuous requirement as it would not be difficult to exceed the Unix expertise of the author. It does not assume any knowledge of UniVerse, so should suit both beginners and those who have already spent sufficient time with the product to become confused.

The guide was originally written for my colleagues in the EDS Africa team at the Cape of Good Hope Bank in Cape Town, South Africa: but contains nothing which is relevant only to them. We use UniVerse release 9 on IBM AIX servers, but again, most of the ground covered will be relevant to UniVerse users irrespective of version and platform. What the guide may contain, however, is a certain amount of nonsense: having been prepared quickly and with too much reliance on my memory of working with UniVerse and systems like it. For this, I can only ask tolerance and kindly correction.

Manny Neira, 23rd June 1999

Computers: Universe: UniVerse Basic

BASIC stands for Beginner's All-purpose Symbolic Instruction Code. It's first implementation was designed by Dartsmouth University and is now known as Dartsmouth Basic.

It was originally designed as a teaching tool, but its adoption by the early home computers (such as the little black plastic Sinclair ZX81, for a long time the world's selling computer) established it as the best known of all computer languages. The machine which finally outsold Sinclair, the IBM PC, used to run GW-BASIC (GW standing for 'Gee Whiz' would you believe) from ROM if there was no MS-DOS floppy in the drive. Microsoft's heavy promotion of Visual Basic, and it's integration into the Office suite, completes the cycle of what is arguably the world's most successful programming language.

Successful, but much maligned. Many technologists still regard Basic as a lightweight development language: or as unstructured and encouraging poor programming practice.

The pity is that these are criticisms based largely on an understanding of the original Dartsmouth Basic and the various 'home computer' implementations it inspired. Even applied to these languages, this view is misplaced. These early versions of Basic aimed to be, above all, to be usable by the novice. They used interpreters rather than compilers, largely because of the ease this brought to development and debugging (even now, most debuggers are essentially interpreters applied to compiled languages, allowing you to execute code a line at a time and inspect variable values: which you could do with interpreted Basic without a debugger). A user completely new to computers would typically be wrting simple programs within hours of getting his computer home from the store. Early Basics were designed for beginners, and was extremely well suited to its task.

The disdain of Basic becomes even more unreasonable, though, when applied to its modern forms. Good Basic compilers have allowed Basic programs to attain the speed necessary for serious applications. Structured programming techniques have long since become an integral part of the language. It is true that Basic still supports that bete noire of coding style gurus, the GOTO unconditional jump, but then so do C and Pascal: the latter being the language designed specifically designed to teach structured programming. There is no obligation to use GOTO in any of these languages, however.

In short, I am asking you to put aside any preconceptions you may have about languages with the word Basic in their names. UniVerse Basic is a particularly strong and well structured implementation of the language, and retains an astounding ease of use and transparency: the true heritage of Dartsmouth Basic.

Computers: Universe: Basic Arrays

Static vs Dynamic arrays

UniVerse Basic supports two kinds of array: dimensioned arrays (also called static arrays), and dynamic arrays. They have in common merely the fact that they are arrays: that is, they can hold more than one value. They are otherwise entirely different in their use and function.

(The difference between static and dynamic arrays has nothing to do with the differences between static and dynamic hashed files. The similarity in terminology is entirely coincidental.)

Dimensioned arrays

A dimensioned array is very similar to the array structures found in other languages.

A dimensioned array (uniquely amongst UniVerse Basic variables) must be declared before it can be used, using the DIM statement:

DIM DEMO.ARRAY(10)

This statement dimensions the array DEMO.ARRAY to store 10 values. The values can be individually addressed using a subscript in round brackets. The elements are numbered from 1 to 10 (C and Pascal programmers please note: not 0 to 9). Each individually addressed element can be treated much as any variable can.

DEMO.ARRAY(1) = 'This is a value for element 1'
DEMO.ARRAY(1) := ' with a bit appended'
PRINT DEMO.ARRAY(1)

To assign the same value to all elements of a dimensioned array in one go, use the MAT statement:

MAT DEMO.ARRAY = ''

You can create one or two dimensional arrays using DIM. To create a two dimensional array and address its elements, use code like the following:

DIM TWO.DIM.ARRAY(10,10) ; * TWO.DIM.ARRAY contains 100 elements
TWO.DIM.ARRAY(1,1) = 'This is a value for element 1,1'
TWO.DIM.ARRAY(1,1) := ' with a bit appended'

(For some reason, the special term vector is sometimes applied to a one dimensional array, and matrix to a two dimensional one.)

You can change the number of elements in a dimensioned array while your program is running, simply by reusing DIM with the same array name. An example follows:

DIM MATRIX(3,3)
MAT MATRIX = 99
DIM MATRIX(4,2)

The state of the MATRIX array is now as follows:

MATRIX

|

1

|

2

|

(3)

1

|

99

|

99

|

(lost)

2

|

99

|

99

|

(lost)

3

|

99

|

99

|

(lost)

4

|

(unassigned)

|

(unassigned)

|

Counting squares in the table above reveals:

Six elements have subscripts valid in both the old and new versions of MATRIX. They are 1,1, 1,2, 2,1, 2,2, 3,1 and 3,2. They all retain their value of 99..

Three elements in the original MATRIX had subscripts outside the range of the new matrix: 1,3, 2,3 and 3,3. The values these elements contained are simply lost, and the memory used to store them is simply returned to the operating system.

Two elements in the new MATRIX are themselves new: 4,1 and 4,2. These elements are 'unassigned'. Reading their values will cause a run time error until some value has been assigned to them.

Dynamic arrays

A dynamic array is simply a long string divided into sections by the occurence of certain delimiter characters.

There are three levels of delimiter, known as the field mark (ASCII character 254), the value mark (ASCII character 253) and the subvalue mark (ASCII character 252). If these names and values seem familiar, it is because they exactly correspond to the markers used to separate fields, values and subvalues in a record in a UniVerse file (see The UniVerse Paradigm).

There is no equivalent to the DIM statement which applies to dynamic arrays. As a dynamic array is merely a string, you can begin just by assigning a value to it. You can use the UniVerse Basic system variables @FM, @VM and @SM to evaluate to field, value, and subvalue markers.

DYNARRAY = '[F1]' : @FM : '[F2V1]' : @VM : '[F2V2S1]' : @SM : '[F2V2S2]'

As a dynamic array is merely a string, you can also use it wherever you would use a string. For instance, you could:

PRINT DYNARRAY ; * Prints [F1]þ[F2V1]ý[F2V2S1]ü[F2V2S2]

(As characters 252, 253 and 254 lie outside the range of ASCII 'printable characters' (32, space, to 126, ~), the way they are displayed will depend on the terminal or printer you are using. The odd characters shown above are dependent on the font used to display this page: they may be different on your own equipment should you run these examples. If you are particularly unlucky, they may even set printer or display modes, and cause the equipment to behave oddly: the truth is that these markers are not generally meant to be displayed.)

You can access the fields in a dynamic array using a subscript in 'vector' or 'pointy' brackets (as I've heard them called) like this:

PRINT DYNARRAY<1> ; * Prints [F1]
PRINT DYNARRAY<2> ; * Prints [F2V1]ý[F2V2S1]ü[F2V2S2]

To access the values in the second field individually, use two subscripts within the pointy brackets:

PRINT DYNARRAY<2,1> ; * Prints [F2V1]
PRINT DYNARRAY<2,2> * Prints [F2V2S1]ü[F2V2S2]

Finally, and predictably, three subscripts allow you to access individual subvalues:

PRINT DYNARRAY<2,2,1> ; * Prints [F2V2S1]
PRINT DYNARRAY<2,2,2> * Prints [F2V2S2]

As you can see, a dynamic array can be used to store up to three 'dimensions' of information. Note also that using 'out of range' subscripts causes no run time error when accessing fields, values, or subvalues: the dynamic array simply yields an empty string if the subscript you are looking for 'doesn't exist'. The code below illustrates this point:

PRINT DYNARRAY<1,2> ; * Prints an empty string, ie. nothing
PRINT DYNARRAY<1000> * * Prints an empty string, ie. nothing
PRINT DYNARRAY<99,472,293> * * Prints an empty string, ie. nothing

The subscript notation can also be used to assign values to a dynamic array, either overwriting existing values, or creating new ones.

DYNARRAY<1> = '[F1V1]' ; * Overwrites field 1 of DYNARRAY
PRINT DYNARRAY<1> ; * Prints [F1V1]
DYNARRAY<1,2> = '[F1V2]' ; * Adds second value to field 1, creating a value mark in the process
PRINT DYNARRAY<1> ; * Prints [F1V1]ý[F1V2]
DYNARRAY<10> = '[F10]' ;* Adds a string of field marks to position [F10] in field 10
PRINT DYNARRAY ; * Prints [F1V1]ý[F1V2]þ[F2V1]ý[F2V2S1]ü[F2V2S2]þþþþþþþþ[F10]

You can insert values into a dynamic using the INS statement:

INS '[NEWFIELD]' BEFORE DYNARRAY<10;>
PRINT DYNARRAY ; * [F1V1]ý[F1V2]þ[F2V1]ý[F2V2S1]ü[F2V2S2]þþþþþþþþ[NEWFIELD]þ[F10]

Note the difference here between using INS to load field 10 and using ...<10>=.... A simple assignment would have overwritten the value in field 10. INS actually inserts a new field at that position, pushing the value [F10] out into field 11.

You can also delete values using DEL:

DEL DYNARRAY<10;>
PRINT DYNARRAY ; * [F1V1]ý[F1V2]þ[F2V1]ý[F2V2S1]ü[F2V2S2]þþþþþþþþ[F10]

The string F10 is now back in field 10.

If you wish to find a string within your dynamic array, you can do so using the LOCATE statement:

* Finds [F10] at field number 10 and prints '10'
LOCATE '[F10]' IN DYNARRAY<1> SETTING POSITION THEN
PRINT POSITION
ELSE
PRINT 'Not found'
END

Note the <1> after the DYNARRAY array name in this code. This indicates that the search should begin with field 1, but more importantly it indicates that the string being searched for is a complete field. Compare the following:

* Fails to find [F1V2] because it is not a complete field, and prints 'Not found'
LOCATE '[F1V2]' IN DYNARRAY<1> SETTING POSITION THEN
PRINT POSITION
ELSE
PRINT 'Not found'
END

To find [F1V2], you would have to search at value level:

* Finds [F1V2] as the second value in field 1 and prints 2
LOCATE '[F1V2]' IN DYNARRAY<1,1> SETTING POSITION THEN
PRINT POSITION
ELSE
PRINT 'Not found'
END

The &lt1,1> not only defines the starting position for the search, it indicates that the search must find a value within field 1. The general principle remains that you can only search 'one level down': you can search an entire dynamic array for a complete field, a field for a value, or a value for a subvalue. As the result is returned as a single number and not a set of coordinates, it could not be otherwise. How would LOCATE report finding [F1V2] in field 1, value 2, by returning a single number?

LOCATE really comes into its own, however, when dealing with a field only list (containing no values or subvalues): particularly if the fields are in sorted order. Consider the following:

NEWARRAY = 1 : @FM : 2 : @FM : 4 : @FM : 5
LOCATE 5 IN NEWARRAY<1> BY 'AR' SETTING POSITION ELSE PRINT '5 absent' ; * Prints nothing
PRINT POSITION ; * Prints 4
LOCATE 3 IN NEWARRAY <1> BY 'AR' SETTING POSITION ELSE PRINT '3 absent' ; * Prints '3 absent'
PRINT POSITION ; * Prints 3

First, to explain the BY 'AR' clause. This optional clause informs LOCATE that it is dealing with a sorted list: the AR denotes the sort order: ascending right-justified. AL stands for ascending left justified, DR for descending right justified, and DL for descending left justified.

One advantage of the BY clause is that it can speed up your search. If your list is sorted AR, and you are looking for the value 3, UniVerse knows that it can give up the search as soon as it reaches the first string higher than 3: which it does when it gets to 4. It therefore doesn't have to search the entire dynamic array for a value that is not there unless the value it is looking for happens to be bigger than all the fields already in the array.

More importantly, though, it adds an interesting twist to the action of the SETTING clause in the case where the string searched for cannot be found: as the variable following SETTING is set to the position the string would have been in if it had been found. By using INS to insert the string in this position, the dynamic array can be maintained in a sorted order without the need for a sorting algorithm.

This is a very neat and widely used trick. The code runs as follows:

LOCATE STRING IN SORTEDARRAY<1> BY SORTORDER SETTING POSITION ELSE
INS STRING BEFORE SORTEDARRAY<POSITION>
END

This code will maintain a sorted list of STRING values automatically.

Comparison of dimensioned and dynamic arrays

From all this, it will seem that dynamic arrays are vastly more flexible than dimensioned arrays: and they are. They are supported by a LOCATE statement, for which dimensioned arrays have no equivalent, and allow strings to be inserted into the middle of an array by shuffling other strings to the right, which dimensioned arrays cannot do. They do not require each element to be initialised, do not cause run time errors if accessed 'out of range', and do not require resizing to accomodate more or fewer strings: all of which dimensioned arrays do. They even offer three dimensions in place of the maximum of two dimensions supported by dimensioned arrays.

Why, then, should one ever use dimensioned arrays? While there are several reasons, one stands head and shoulders above the others: because they are faster. UniVerse can address a single element in a dimensioned array almost as quickly as a single variable. The fields, values, and subvalues of a dynamic array require clever searches along long strings counting field, value, and subvalue markers to address. While they are cleverly implemented, this will never be as fast as a dimensioned array.

In general, I would make the following recommendations:

1. Where each element you are going to store has a specific and unique meaning, and is wedded to its numeric position, use dimensioned arrays. This is precisely the situation you are in when you read a record from a UniVerse data file. Field 1 of the record may be the customer name, field to the product code, and so on. The values of these fields do not require sorting, and it would be meaningless to 'insert' elements into such an array. The number of elements you will require to hold the record is not going to change during the life time of the program. All these factors suggest dimensioned arrays as the natural home for records read into memory. UniVerse Basic offers two statements to read a record into memory: READ which will read one into a dynamic array, and MATREAD which will read it into a dimensioned array. For most data files, MATREAD is appropriate.

2. Don't store values and subvalues in dynamic arrays: store fields only. By keeping your dynamic array structure flat, or 'one-dimensional', you allow the dynamic array to be searched for values, you simplify the business of inserting and deleting values, and you make your code easier to understand and maintain. Rather than creating an array called INVOICES which stores fields, each of which has an invoice number in value 1 and invoice value in value 2, create two dynamic arrays, called INVOICE.NUMBERS and INVOICE.VALUES. Whenever you insert a field into one, insert a corresponding field into the other. Whenever you delete a field from one, delete the same field from the other. This has the added advantage that as each dynamic array is half the size, it is far quicker to process.

3. In short, use dimensioned arrays for structures built from elements of data with different meanings, and dynamic arrays for lists of a single entity. If you must process lists of structures, combine the two: create a dimensioned array called INVOICES, element one of which is a dynamic array full of invoice numbers (stored as fields), element two of which is a dynamic array full of the corresponding invoice values, and so on.

Computers: Universe: The Build Cycle

What is a build cycle?

If you have only used interpreted languages, you may be unfamiliar with the idea of a build cycle. It is simply the series of steps you must take from writing your program to running it.

On the other hand, if your background is in a programming language like C you may be used to a very complex build cycle which involves editing, compiling, linking, make files, and so forth. The UniVerse Basic build cycle is, thankfully, far simpler than this.

Essentially there are three stages:

1. Editing your program.
2. Compiling your program.
3. Running your program.

These three stages are described below, and are followed by a few tricks to take the drudgery out of this routine.

If you are writing a 'shared' subroutine, to be called by other programs, there is a fourth stage known as 'cataloging' your program. This is described in the section on Basic External Routines below.

Creating a file to store programs

Each program you write will take the form of a record in a file: and it follows that you need to create a file to store your programs. Bear the following in mind:

1. Your program file must be a directory file (see Directory Files): UniVerse will refuse to compile records in any hashed file. A directory file is so called because it is implemented as a directory under Unix: and each record in it becomes a simple Unix text file. Type 19 files uses the record keys as Unix file names. Type 1 files build impromptu subdirectory structures designed to ensure that a filename is never over a certain length. Unless you have a good reason to use a type 1 file, therefore, I recommended the simplicity of a type 19 file. There are advantages to a simple Unix implementation, especially if you are using a Unix based source control system such as RCS.

2. If you are planning a large suite of programs, you may want to consider creating more than one program file and dividing your programs by function. There is no limit to the number of program files you can put in an account, though you need to strike a balance between functional separation and simplicity.

3. There is a well established convention amongst UniVerse developers that program files are either called BP or suffixed .BP. It's not a convention I'm crazy about, as I believe unnecessary abbreviations detract from readability, but on the other hand there's no doubting that most UniVerse programmers will instantly recognise the initials BP as standing for Basic Programs, so it is perhaps as well to do the same.

During this section, we will be creating onlya few programs, so a single file will suffice. Create your program file with the command:

>CREATE.FILE BP 19
??FB??

Writing your program

You have, by now, created dozens of records using the UniVerse editor, so you may be glad to hear that program records are created using the same tool. Incidentally, refer back to The Editor - ED if you are not throroughly familiar with the editor, as it will be used extensively in this section. If you have been using vi you will be unable to implement the useful macros at the end of this section, or to use the vital editor command FORMAT, which idents your code to show its structure. Yes, you could indent your code yourself, but (a) it takes time and (b) it would only reflect the structure you thought your code had, not the structure it really had if you had, say, forgotten to close your ELSE BLOCK with an END: more of this later.

For now, I shall follow the time honoured convention of making your first UniVerse program display the words Hello world! on the screen. The PRINT statement does the work, the END marks the end of the program. All UniVerse Basic programs end in END:

>ED BP HELLO.WORLD
New record.

----: I
0001= PRINT 'Hello world!'
0002= END
0003= (Press ENTER)
Bottom at line 2.
----: FORMAT
??FB??
----: P
??FB??
----: FI
Record "HELLO.WORLD" filed in file "BP".
>

The P command above is not strictly necessary: but I wanted to show you what FORMAT had done to your code. The 'standard' indent was applied to your first line, and the final END was pulled in to the left. This pattern will become more and more meaningful to you as you gain experience writing and formatting programs.

Compiling your program

Having written your program, you must compile it. Before discussing the command you must enter, it is perhaps worth explaining what happens when you compile a program.

If you were running a interpreted language, such as Dartmouth Basic, each line of your program would be read in turn, and converted into a series of numeric instruction codes which would be fed to your computer's CPU for execution.

A true compiled language, like C, is converted into numeric instruction codes before a single line of code is run. Once this has been done, the original C source code could, in theory, be thrown away: the computer merely executes the numbers. It is kept only because it is likely that the program may need to be changed in the future.

The UniVerse Basic approach lies somewhere between these two. The problem with compiling down to numbers suitable for a particular CPU is that CPUs, and the numbers they understand, vary from computer to computer, so code compiled on one machine cannot be run on another, and so a compiler capable of translating directly from source code to 'binary' code must be created for each machine.

In addition, whereas an interpreter contains many complex routines internally (and thus can employ them whenever they are required by the current instruction), a compiled language must include all the code for common activities in the binary code of any program which uses them.

To get round this, the original PICK was built on a 'virtual machine'. Dick Pick asked himself what functions the 'ideal' CPU would have for implementating his database. He then built a program which behaved like this 'ideal' CPU by translating instructions into the instructions undestood by the machine he was working on. In principle, this 'virtual machine' is the only part of an PICK system written in code specific to the CPU being used: the rest of PICK is written in PICK Basic, which is compiled into the numeric instructions required not by the underlying CPU, but by the 'virtual machine'. (I say in principle because some implementations cheat in certain places for efficiency reasons).

Thus, when PICK (or its later descendants) moved from computer to computer, only the virtual machine had to be rewritten for the new host. The rest of PICK continued using the same virtual machine, and thus the same numeric instruction set.

Pascal programmers may find this approach familiar as Pascal originally implemented a similar idea, with Pascal being compiled down to 'P code', which was then interpreted by a virtual CPU. Later Pascals, again for efficiency reasons, have largely abandoned the approach in favour of true compilation, but UniVerse retains the idea.

The numeric instructions used by the UniVerse virtual machine are known as 'op-codes', and the series of op-codes generated when you compile a UniVerse Basic program as 'beta code' or (in common with true compilers) 'object code'.

How much sense all this made to you will depend largely on your technical background. If it seems complicated, don't worry, because you can use UniVerse Basic without having to understand any of it: it is provided to satisfy the voracious technical appetite of C programmers to know what is going on 'under the bonnet'.

To compile your program, use the command:

>BASIC BP HELLO.WORLD
??FB??
>

Notice that BASIC created a file called BP.O. The O stands for 'object code', and the object code for your program is stored in this file. This is because object code is one of the very few things in UniVerse which is not stored in ASCII, and programs like ED get very confused when asked to load object code records. To reduce the possibility of this, a separate file is created to store it. You will see messages reporting the creation of a .O file whenever your compile the first program in a new program file.

Running your program

All that remains now is to run your new program. True to UniVerse's philosophy, the command to do this is what you'd expect it to be:

>RUN BP HELLO.WORLD
??FB??
>

Developing from the editor

This program is so simple that it is unlikely you would have to repeat the ED/BASIC/RUN loop more than once to get it working correctly, but in real world examples you may find yourself doing it frequently.

If the cycle is perfectly even, you may find yourself typing .X3 again and again to reuse the appropriate commands from the stack (see The Command Stack): but you will eventually trip yourself up when your program doesn't compile, you therefore omit to run the program, and suddenly .X3 is no longer the right command. Even if your programs always compile without error (which planet are you from?) this approach still requires you to reinvoke ED and find the line you were last working on each time round.

There is a useful alternative.

1. Use SAVE to write your program to the file without leaving the editor (best to do this periodically anyway, so that next time a 'Machine being shut down in 5 minutes' message is delayed by 6 minutes by a busy network you don't lose too much work).
2. Still from the editor, use the command XEQ BASIC BP HELLO.WORLD command to compile your program.
3. If your program compiled correctly, use the command XEQ RUN BP HELLO.WORLD to test run it.

The beauty is that you need never leave the editor or lose your position in the record.

This can be made even easier by creating an editor macro:

ED &ED& BASIC.RUN
New record.

----: I
0001= E
0002= SAVE
0003= XEQ BASIC @FILE @ID
0004= XEQ RUN @FILE @ID
0005= (Press ENTER)
Bottom at line 5.
----: FILE

If this macro seems familiar, it is because it first appeared in the section Editor Macros. If you followed the examples in that section, you may find this record already in your &ED& file. You can now reduce your build cycle to an occassional .X BASIC.RUN issued from the editor. Even if your program is not suitable for running from the editor (because, for instance, it is a subroutine not designed to be run independently), you can still save and compile it in this way: create an alternative macro called just BASIC which omits the RUN command.

Note once again the use of @FILE and @ID to replace BP and HELLO.WORLD: these tokens automatically take the appropriate values for the record your are editing, and allow you to use the same macro while editing any program. Again, all this is explained in the section Editor Macros.

Creating a command to run your program

You may wish to create a VOC record to run your program: allowing you, and your client users, to run your program by entering a single command at the UniVerse prompt. The simplest way is by creating a paragraph:

>ED VOC RUN.HELLO.WORLD
New record.

----: I
0001= PA Say hello to the world
0002= RUN BP HELLO.WORLD
0003= (Press RETURN)
Bottom at line 2.
----: FI
"RUN.HELLO.WORLD" filed in file "VOC".
>

This will work perfectly well. However, it is probably better to create a verb rather than a paragraph, like this:

>ED VOC HELLO.WORLD
New record.

----: I
0001= V Say hello to the world
0002= HELLO.WORLD
0003= B
0004= BP.O
0005= (Press RETURN)
Bottom at line 4.
----: FI
"HELLO.WORLD" filed in file "VOC".
>

The B on the third line indicates the HELLO.WORLD is a Basic program, and the BP.O on the fourth provides the name of the file which stores the programs object code.

Both paragraphs and verbs were covered in greater depth earlier in this course. See Paragraphs and Verbs for more information.

So why prefer the verb to the paragraph? Chiefly because it is specfically designed for this job. A paragraph is a device for handling command scripts of all kinds: a verb is purpose build for running programs, and so a more precise fit to the purpose.

Also, there is a system variable called @SENTENCE which you can use in a UniVerse Basic to capture the string that the user typed in to run your program, and which is usually used to support command line parameters. The @SENTENCE value generated by the paragraph includes the words RUN BP, which are just noise and make the command string harder to parse.

Computers: Universe: Basic Conditions

Condition handling: IF

To execute a statement only on a particular condition, use an IF statement like this:

IF VALUE = 0 THEN PRINT 'Value is 0'

To execute a different statement if the condition is not true, add an ELSE clause:

IF VALUE = 0 THEN PRINT 'Value is 0' ELSE PRINT "Value isn't 0"

More than 1 line can be made conditional by beginning a new line immediately after then THEN, and closing the clause with an END:

IF VALUE = 0 THEN
   PRINT 'The value is 0.'
   PRINT 'No invoice will be printed.'
END

If you wish to add an else clause, use END ELSE to terminate the THEN clause, and END to close then ELSE clause.

IF VALUE = 0 THEN
   PRINT 'The value is 0.'
   PRINT 'No invoice will be printed.'
END ELSE
   PRINT 'This invoice has a value of ' : VALUE
   PRINT 'Invoice to be prnted...'
END

Finally, IF statements may be nested:

IF VALUE = 0 THEN
   IF QUANTITY = 0 THEN
      PRINT 'The invoice has no quantity'
          PRINT 'and no value.'
   END ELSE
      PRINT 'There has been a mistake.'
          PRINT 'The quantity is ' : QUANTITY
          PRINT 'The value should not be zero.'
   END
END ELSE
   PRINT 'This invoice has a value of ' : VALUE
   PRINT 'Invoice to be prnted...'
END

Note the identation of the lines above. This is done automatically by the editor's FORMAT command, and is extremely useful. If an END statement does not line up with the IF statement which set the condition, then somewhere along the way you have omitted an END, or a THEN, or in some other way made a mistake in your code: so this forms a useful check.

Multiple condition handing: CASE

A commonly asked question is 'does UniVerse Basic support ELSEIF?'. The answer is no, but it does provide the same facility in the form of the CASE block.

A case block begins with BEGIN CASE and ends with END CASE. Between these lie one or more CASE statements, each followed by a particular condition. When UniVerse reaches BEGIN CASE, it then examines each CASE condition in the block until it finds one which is true. It then starts executing the statements under that CASE statement until it encounters either the next CASE or the block's END CASE. Finally, it transfers control to the statement following the END CASE.

As ever, a written description can make something sound more complicated than it is. Consider instead the following example:

BEGIN CASE
   CASE TYPE = 'I'
      PRINT 'Processing INVOICE document...'
      * Process INVOICES here.
   CASE TYPE = 'C'
      PRINT 'Processing CREDIT NOTE document...'
      * Process CREDIT NOTES here.
   CASE 1
      PRINT 'Invalid document type: not processed.'
END CASE

Each time the code above is run, only one of the three messages will be printed: as soon as UniVerse Basic has found a true CASE, the others are ignored. Note the CASE 1: this is a common and useful trick. As the value 1 is logically true (see Basic Types), the statements between the CASE 1 and the END CASE will always be executed if none of the other CASEs are true: a handy safety net. Of course, CASE 1

will always be the last CASE in the list: any cases below it would never be reached, as CASE 1 is always true.

Such constructs are more efficient if the cases more likely to be true are put at the top (providing, of course, that the arrangement doesn't alter the logic away from that desired, as moving CASE 1 above would). To explain this, imagine that the code above is used to process 9000 invoices, 900 credit notes, and 100 invalid types. To discover an invoice takes only one comparison: TYPE = 'I' must be true. To find a credit note takes two: TYPE = 'I' must be false, and TYPE = 'C' true. Invalid types take three. Thus, the total number of comparisons made is 9000 * 1 + 900 * 2 + 100 * 3 or 11,100. However, reverse the order of the first two tests, and suddenly invoices will require two tests, and credit notes only one. The number of comparisons made would become 900 * 1 + 9000 * 2 + 100 * 3 or 19,200: getting on for twice as many.

Computers: Universe: Basic File I/O

Opening a file: OPEN

Before you can read from or write to a UniVerse file, you must open it using the OPEN statement. This stores a kind of 'file handle' in a file variable, and you may then use the file variable in your READ and WRITE statements. An example of an OPEN statement runs:

OPEN 'VOC' TO VOC.FILE ELSE STOP "Sorry, can't open VOC."

Note the ELSE clause. Your OPEN statement must have an ELSE clause to tell it what to do if it can't open the file: for instance, if the file name you have provided does not exist. In this case, I've decided to simply stop the program if it cannot be found, but you must decide the best approach in each case.

Reading and writing records using dynamic arrays: READ and WRITE

To read a record from a file, you need a file variable for the file, and a key for the record. You can then store the contents of the record in a variable. An example follows:

READ VOC.RECORD FROM VOC.FILE, 'RELLEVEL' ELSE VOC.RECORD = ''
PRINT VOC.RECORD ; * Prints something like Xþ9.4.1.1þINFORMATION...

The contents of the RELLEVEL record from the VOC file are loaded into VOC.RECORD as a dynamic array: the PRINT statement lets you take a look at what you've got. (You may remember that RELLEVEL is a standard VOC record which contains UniVerse release level information: see Other VOC Records).

Note again the ELSE clause: this is executed if the record you are looking for does not exist. Again, I've chosen to simply use an empty string as the record value in this case, but it might be more appropriate for you to display an error message, assign some non-empty default value, or even offer to create the missing record: it depends, of course, on your application. Setting records to empty strings in ELSE clauses has become something of a knee-jerk coding reaction, and probably contributes to many obscure bugs in UniVerse applications, which would have been highlighted earlier if an ELSE clause somewhere actually reported a problem.

To write your record, use WRITE:

WRITE VOC.RECORD TO VOC.FILE, 'TEST.WRITE'

Here, I have written the record back under a different key, effectively creating a new record. Note that WRITE will create new records if the key is not already on the file, or overwrite an existing record if it is, without a murmur. If either condition would constitute an error in your program, you must check for it using READ before writing.

Reading and writing records using dimensioned arrays: ,MATREAD and MATWRITE

MATREAD and MATWRITE correspond exactly to READ and WRITE, except that instead of using a dynamic array as a record memory buffer, they use a dimensioned array. You must therefore declare a dimensioned array to act as a buffer:

DIM VOC.RECORD(10)
MATREAD VOC.RECORD FROM VOC.FILE, 'RELLEVEL' ELSE MAT VOC.RECORD = ''
FOR FIELD.NUMBER = 1 TO 10
   PRINT VOC.RECORD(FIELD.NUMBER)
NEXT FIELD.NUMBER

The VOC file is awkward to handle in this way because it's records contain different numbers of fields. The RELLEVEL record is only four lines long, but a paragraph could easily contain 50 lines.

MATREAD handles such variables as best it can. If the record contains fewer fields than there are elements in the array, the unused elements are assigned empty string values. If there are more fields than elements, the additional fields are put into the special element 0 as a dynamic array. This element can be accessed using the syntax VOC.RECORD(0) but its perhaps best not to rely on this kind of overflowing handling within your logic. Increase the size of your dimensioned array, or use a dynamic array, rather than habitually searching element 0. (Note that I am assuming here that you are using Prime INFORMATION or IDEAL flavoured UniVerse: the others store excess fields in the last element, but the same principles apply.)

You can write the dimensioned array back to the file using MATWRITE:

MATWRITE VOC.RECORD TO VOC.FILE, 'TEST.WRITE'

MATWRITE is as happy to overwrite existing records or create new ones as WRITE, so again, add whatever tests you need to to prevent behaviour which shouldn't be happening.

Reading a single field from a file: READV

Though it is far less commonly done, you can read and write individual fields rather than entire records. It generally isn't any faster than reading and writing entire records, but may be a neater implementation of your design. Fields are read using READV:

READV TYPE.DESC FROM VOC.FILE, 'RELLEVEL', 1 ELSE TYPE.DESC = ''

Note here the 1 after the key 'RELLEVEL'. This tells READV which field number you wish to read. As usual, READV takes an ELSE clause: but note that it will only be executed if the record you are looking for does not exist, not merely if the field number you have requested is greater than the number of fields in the record: in that case it simply reads an empty string.

Predictably, to write a single field to a record you use WRITEV:

WRITEV TYPE.DESC TO VOC.FILE, 'TEST.WRITE', 1

If the record you are writing to exists, only the field number you have specified will be overwritten: the others will retain their values. If it doesn't, it will be created, with sufficient field marks (and thus empty fields) to put the field you have written in at the appropriate position.

Deleting records: DELETE

To delete a record, use the DELETE statement:

DELETE VOC.FILE, 'RELLEVEL'

Locking records for update: READU, MATREADU and READVU

UniVerse, like most of its predecessors, is primarily designed for the creation of multiuser systems: and you should bear this in mind in coding your file handling. If you use READ to read a record, modify it's contents in memory, and then WRITE it back, what is to say that some other user hasn't READ the same record just before you and written it back just after you? If they had, all the changes you made would be wiped out by the other users WRITE.

To prevent this kind of problem, UniVerse provides alternatives to READ, MATREAD and READV called READU, MATREADU and READVU respectively. The 'U' stands for 'update': and if you are planning to update a record, you should read it with a ...U read.

The only difference this makes is that UniVerse will lock a record when you READU it, preventing any other user from using READU to read it. If you try to READU a locked record, what will happen will depend on your code. Consider the following READU.

READU VOC.RECORD FROM VOC.FILE, 'RELLEVEL' ELSE VOC.RECORD = ''

If RELLEVEL is already locked, this READU will simply wait until the lock is removed: effectively hanging your program. It will not take the ELSE clause just because the record is locked: only if the record doesn't exist..

Although simply waiting for the lock to become available may be a suitable strategy on occassion, sometimes you will need to take specific action on encountering a lock. To do this, add a LOCKED clause.

READU VOC.RECORD FROM VOC.FILE, 'RELLEVEL' LOCKED
   STOP 'Sorry, the record is locked by another user. Try again later.'
END ELSE
   VOC.RECORD = '' ; * RELLEVEL doesn't exist
END

The message in the LOCKED clause above is not strictly accurate, as the RELLEVEL record may not even exist: if you READU a key which doesn't exist, you still create a lock on that key, effectively reserving it for yourself. Anyone else trying to READU the same key will find it locked.

A locked record (or a locked new key) will remain locked until one of four things happen:

1. You write it: WRITE VOC.RECORD TO VOC.FILE, 'RELLEVEL'
2. You release it: RELEASE VOC.FILE, 'RELLEVEL'
3. You program finishes running.

Don't rely on the third route: some programs can keep records locked for long periods, causing serious disruption to other processes, and a program which loops (like a data entry screen looping through updates or a batch processing routine) can lock huge numbers of records. Also, what you write today as a 10 second utility to update 100 records may be extended by future programmers to update thousands of programs: a problem if it doesn't release it's record locks.

The RELEASE statement can also be used to release all the locks held by a user on a particular file (RELEASE VOC.FILE, with no record key) or all the locks held by a user on any file (just RELEASE), but if you find yourself using either, it may be a sign that your program is holding locks unecessarily long. At some point, your program must decide whether or not to WRITE the record. It is at that point that you should RELEASE the individual record if you have decided not to WRITE it.

Locking records for reading: READL, MATREADL and READVL

It might be that you do not intend to update a record you have read, but wish nevertheless to ensure that noone else updates it while you are using it. To do this, use READL, MATREADL or READVL. These apply 'shared locks': UniVerse will prevent a user placing an update lock with READU on a record which has one or more shared locks applied by READL, and will prevent a READL placing a shared lock on a record which already has a READU update lock, but will allow many users to simultaneously apply READL shared locks.

A Locking Strategy

Bear in mind that neither READL nor READU will prevent a READ. The UniVerse locking system is cooperative rather than preemptive: which means that it relies on processes using the locking system to control their own behaviour rather than forcing a locking regime on them which they cannot avoid. This system works well if applied consistently, but will obviously fail wherever a programmer decides to WRITE a record for which he has never obtained READU lock.

A comparison might be made with C memory handling. C provides all the functions which are needed to manage memory safely: provided that programmers are careful never to address memory that they haven't reserved or 'allocated', and provided that they release it one they've done with it. It doesn't, however, enforce good practice, and both through guile and error far too many C programs still write to memory they don't own.

To safely manage multiuser access to your UniVerse System:

1. Do not create, modify, or delete a record without first obtaining an update lock using READU (or equivalent).

2. Do not assume that a record has remain unchanged since you read it unless you originally obtained a READU or READL lock on it which you have not yet released.

Processing select lists

Select lists, and some of their uses, were covered in an earlier section of this course (see Select Lists). These notes now discuss how such lists can be created and used within a UniVerse Basic program.

One method involves introducing a new UniVerse Basic statement which has applications beyond the creation of select lists: EXECUTE. You may remember a similarly editor command called XEQ (see The Editor - ED) which allowed you to execute TCL commands without leaving the editor. The UniVerse Basic statement XEQ serves a similar purpose, allowing you to execute TCL commands from a program. The syntax is simple, as is shown in the example below:

PRINT 'Press RETURN to see a listing of the VOC file...':
INPUT PAUSE
EXECUTE 'LIST VOC'

Combining this command with a TCL SELECT command allows you to create your select list from your UniVerse Basic program, using any of SELECT's usual parameters.

EXECUTE 'SELECT VOC WITH TYPE = "M"'

The second way to create a select list from your program is to use the UniVerse Basic SELECT statement. This simply takes a file variable, created with OPEN, as a parameter. An example follows:

SELECT VOC.FILE

Please note the differences between these approaches:

1. The TCL SELECT command can be used from the UniVerse command prompt. It can use WITH and BY clauses to modify the scope and sorting of its list. It accepts a filename as a parameter. It can only be used from a UniVerse Basic program via the EXECUTE statement.
2. The UniVerse Basic SELECT statement can only be used in a UniVerse Basic program. It cannot apply conditions or sorting to the lists it creates. It accepts a file variable as a parameter.

From this description, it will seem that using EXECUTE 'SELECT...' is far more flexible than using SELECT: and so it is. But the list of differences is not complete: the most important follows:

3. Using the UniVerse Basic SELECT command is much, much faster than using EXECUTE 'SELECT...'.

So, as always, it's up to you. If you cannot live without a sorted or scoped select list, you'll have to use EXECUTE 'SELECT filename parameters'. If you can, you'll be able to use the much faster SELECT filevariable.

Having created your select list, you must access the keys it contains from your program. To do this, UniVerse provides the READNEXT statement. By its nature, it is almost always written into a LOOP/REPEAT structure.

OPEN 'VOC' TO VOC.FILE ELSE STOP "Sorry, can't open VOC."
EOF = 0
SELECT VOC.FILE
LOOP
   READNEXT VOC.KEY ELSE EOF = 1
UNTIL EOF
   PRINT VOC.KEY
REPEAT

The READNEXT statement simply reads one key from the select list each time it is executed, until it runs out of keys and executes its ELSE clause. The logic above is fairly cautious: it's not uncommon to see the ELSE clause setting the key to an empty string in its ELSE clause, and then exiting as soon as it encounters an empty string. The problem is, though it is not easy, it is possible to get keys with empty string keys into UniVerse files: I once spent a long time debugging a program until I realise that READNEXT was returning an empty string as a key before it ran out of keys, thus terminating the loop early and leaving half the file unprocessed. Setting the key to an exotic value (like '*** END OF FILE ***') is also sometimes used, but there is always the possibility, however weird your special value, that a record in the file will have it: most probably because during a test run your loop didn't terminate properly and you ended up writing your special value to the file. Using an entirely separate flag is the only completely safe method.

Why is the UniVerse Basic SELECT statement so much faster than the equivalent TCL command? The reason is that the UniVerse Basic SELECT doesn't actually create a select list at all. It creates a kind of internal pointer to the first record in the the first group, and each time you READNEXT it merely reads the key pointed at and moves it along to the next key. Effectively, if you use EXECUTE 'SELECT...' you end up traversing the file twice: once to select the keys, and again to process them. Using the UniVerse Basic SELECT with READNEXT means that you only traverse it once, during processing. It also explains, however, why you cannot sort or apply selection criteria to your list.

Computers: Universe: Basic Flow Control

Flow control

Usually, each statement in your program is executed in turn until the final END statement is reached. Any divergence from this 'flow' must be deliberately engineered, and you have already seen two ways in which this can be done: by making statements conditional (see Basic Conditions) and by looping (see Loops). UniVerse Basic provides two further statements which you can use to control the order in which your statements run:

The unconditional jump: GOTO

To use GOTO, you must add two lines to your program. The first is a 'label', which serves as a kind of place marker. It can be just a number at the beginning of a line, but usually some kind of descriptive name is chosen. A name must be followed by a colon, like this SKIP.MESSAGE:. The second is the GOTO itself, which must be followed by the label to which control should be transferred:

PRINT 'Invoice entry complete.'
IF VALUE # 0 THEN GOTO SKIP.MESSAGE
PRINT 'Error! Value is 0!'
SKIP.MESSAGE:
* Continue with program...

This will work, but it's poor code. It's difficult to think of uses of GOTO which aren't: almost any use of GOTO can be better written using loops and conditions. For example, the code above could have been written:

PRINT 'Invoice entry complete.'
IF VALUE = 0 THEN PRINT 'Error! Value is 0!'
* Continue with program...

I would not advise someone never to use a GOTO, because all such arbitrary prohibitions eventually fall foul of some very particular circumstance where the the thing prohibited is found to be the most efficient, readable, and natural way to solve a problem, but I would suggest that GOTO will be so favoured very rarely, and you should try applying a loop or condition before employing it. If these prove complicated to implement, it may even be a sign that the overall structure of your program could be confused and could benefit from a clearer structure.

Internal subroutines: GOSUB

GOSUB is similar to GOTO in that it transfers control to a label somewhere in your code. The difference is that UniVerse Basic makes a note in memory of the point at which the GOSUB appeared, and as soon as it encounters a RETURN statement, it transfers control back to the line following the GOSUB. The net effect is to allow you to create 'subroutines' which allow complex tasks to appear in your 'main logic' as a single GOSUB statement, while their detailed implementation is tucked away lower in the program. For instance, consider the following:

GOSUB SELECT.INVOICES
LOOP
   GOSUB GET.INVOICE.NUMBER
UNTIL NO.MORE.INVOICES
   GOSUB PROCESS.INVOICE
REPEAT
STOP 'Invoice processing complete'

* Select the invoices.

SELECT.INVOICES:
   * Code to select invoices
   RETURN

* etc.

The beauty of this code is that its overall structure is almost impossible to miss from the 'main' loop at the head of the program. Future maintenance programmers may therefore turn their attention to discrete routines which handle the individual tasks: which may themselves (if they are complex) be broken down into further routines.

Breaking an alogorithm into logically distinct functions is recommended by almost all coding gurus, and so I need not bang on about its advantages to long. In UniVerse Basic, this practise can take two forms: the use of 'internal' subroutines via GOSUB, or the use of 'external' or 'shared' subroutines accessed via CALL (see
Basic External Subroutines later). As a general rule, I would suggest using GOSUB when the subroutines are genuinely specific to the current program, and using external subroutines only when they might genuinely be of use to other programs too. It is true that internal subroutines are not as discrete as many structured programming advocates would like - they have, for instance, access to all the variables in the same source file - but it is as well not to clutter your shared routine libraries with lots of routines other programmers will find useless. If you're keen on using an external subroutine, think carefully about how the task you have in mind might be 'generalised' to make it genuinely useful outside your current program, write and share the generalised version, and then call this from your program. For instance, perhaps GOSUB SELECT.INVOICES could be replaced with CALL SELECT.FILE('INVOICES', CRITERIA).

Computers: Universe: Basic Loops

UniVerse Basic supports two forms of loop.

Fixed iteration loop: FOR/NEXT

The first made its first appearance in traditional Dartmouth Basic: the FOR/NEXT loop:

FOR COUNTER = 10 TO 1 STEP -1
   PRINT COUNTER
NEXT COUNTER
PRINT "Lift off!"

FOR begins by setting the counter variable, imaginatively called COUNTER, to the starting value of 10. The value is checked against the terminating TO value of 1, and (as the STEP to be added each time is negative) decides that the loop is not complete. Execution then passes to the next statement, which prints that value on the screen. The NEXT statement simply returns execution to the head of the loop.

FOR now adds the STEP value to COUNTER. In this case, the STEP is -1, and so COUNTER becomes 9. Again, it is compared to the TO value, and again the loop continues.

This process repeats until COUNTER reaches 1. FOR compares the counter to the terminating value, and because it has not yet passed this value, the loop continues, and 1 is printed. NEXT then returns execution to the FOR statement. COUNTER is incremented and reaches 0: this passes the terminating value, and so FOR transfers control to the statement following the NEXT, which in this case prints Lift off!.

Loop terminated by condition: LOOP/REPEAT

If you do not know how many times your loop will repeat, or it would require extra processing effort to find out the number of loops required in advance, you may be better off using a LOOP/REPEAT loop. A perpetual loop can be set up as follows:

LOOP
   PRINT 'Still looping...'
REPEAT

This loop is perfectly legal, but will run for ever, which is not usually helpful. Usually you will want to specify some condition which will eventually terminate the loop. You can do this by using the UNTIL statement:

COUNTER = 10
LOOP
   PRINT COUNTER
UNTIL COUNTER = 1
   COUNTER -= 1
REPEAT

Note that the UNTIL can appear anywhere: not necessarily at the top or the bottom of the loop. This makes LOOP/REPEAT far more flexible than the choice of top-terminating or bottom-terminating loops offered by most other languages: though by making UNTIL the first or last statement inside the loop you can emulate either.

You can use a WHILE clause in place of an UNTIL clause if you wish: WHILE will continue the loop as long as the condition following it is true, whereas UNTIL will continue as long as it is false. If follows that UNTIL condition is logically identical to WHILE NOT(condition), and vice versa.

Choose the one which makes your condition read the most naturally. For instance, the the examples below, EOF is an 'end of file' variable, while MORE.RECORDS is a flag which indicates whether there are still records to process:

LOOP
   * Read from the file
UNTIL EOF
   * Process the information read
REPEAT

LOOP
   * Read from the file
WHILE MORE.RECORDS
   * Process the information read
REPEAT

Computers: Universe: Basic Operators

Most of these operators have appeared already in this course, often used to support example code. For completeness, however, here is a complete list:

Precedence: ()

Brackets are used to override the usual 'precedence' rules, the order in which operators are applied. For instance, 1 + 2 * 3 would normally evaluate to 7, but (1 + 2) * 3 evaluates to 9.

Addition: +

If a + is put before a single operand, it simply means 'positive', so +4 is the same as 4.

If it appears between two values, it adds them. 4 + 2 evaluates to 6

Subtraction

If a - is put before a single operand, it simply means 'negative', so -4 is simply 'minus 4'.

If it appears between two values, it substracts the second from the first. 4 - 2 evaluates to 2

Multiplication: *

4 * 2 evaluates to 8.

Division: /

4 / 2 evaluates to 2.

Exponentiation: ^ or **

4 ^ 2 and 4 ** 2 both evaluate to 16.

Concatenation: or CAT

'Hello ' : 'World!' and 'Hello ' CAT 'World!' both evaluate to Hello World!.

Substring extraction: []

To extract n characters from the end of a string, append [n]. 'UniVerse'[2] evaluates to se.

To extract n characters starting from position p, append [p,n]. 'UniVerse'[3,2] evaluates to iV.

To break your string into sections delimited by character c, and take n sections beginning from section s, append [c,s,n]. 'UniVerse Basic Programming Language'[' ',2,1] evaluates to Basic.

Equality: EQ or =

1 = 2 evaluates to 0 (falsity).

Inequality: NE or #

1 # 2 evaluates to 1 (truth).

'Less than' test: LT or <

1 < 2 evaluates to 1 (truth).

'Greater than' test: GT or >

1 > 2 evaluates to 0 (falsity).

'Less than or equal to' test: LE, <=, =<, or #<

1 <= 2 evaluates to 1 (truth).

'Greater than or equal to' test: GE, >=, =>, or #>

1 >= 2 evaluates to 0 (falsity).

Pattern matching: MATCH or MATCHES

Use this operator to check a string against a 'pattern template'. These templates are made up of a number of elements strung together. Each element takes the form nt, where n is a number between 0 and 9, representing 'number of characters' (0 meaning 'any number of characters) and t is a 'type of characters': A for alpha, N for numeric, and X for 'any'. Thus the pattern template 2A means 'two alpha characters, 0N means 'any number of numeric characters', and 2X1A means 'any two characters followed by an alpha character'. A few examples may clarify. All of the following evaluate to 1 (truth):

'ABC123' MATCHES '3A3N'
'Route 66' MATCHES '0X2N'
'Cloud 9' MATCHES '5A1X1N'

You can also include literals in your pattern template, putting them in quotes if they might otherwise be mistaken for pattern elements. My own advice is to use quotes to highlight literals whether or not they are required. All these are true too:

'ABC123' MATCHES '"ABC"3N'
'Route 66' MATCHES '"Route "2N'
'Cloud 9' MATCHES '0X"9"'

Fin her expression could be used. C programmers may recognise this as a form of their beloved condition ? truevalue : falsevalue operator.

Logical operators: AND, OR and NOT

AND combines two conditions, and evaluates to 1 (truth) if they are both true, or 0 (falsity) if either or both are not. 1 = 2 AND 3 # 4 evaluates to 0 (false).

OR combines two conditions, and evaluates to 1 (truth) if either or both are true, or 0 (falsity) if they are both false. 1 = 2 AND 3 # 4 evaluates to 1 (truth).

NOT is actually a function, but is so closely related to AND and OR that it is always documented with them. NOT takes a single parameter, returning 1 (truth) if it is false, or 0 (falsity) if it is true. NOT(1 = 2) evaluates to 1 (truth).

Assignment operators: =, +=, -= and :=

The assignment of variables is straightforward, taking the form VARIABLE = VALUE.

To increase the numeric value stored by a variable, use VARIABLE += INCREMENT. This is logically the same as VARIABLE = VARIABLE + INCREMENT, but is more efficient and clearer.

Similarly, you can decrease the numeric value stored by a variable using VARIABLE -= DECREMENT.

To concatenate a string to the end of an existing string, use VARIABLE := EXTRA.BIT.

The following example code uses all four assignment operators.

VALUE = 100
VALUE += 1 ; * Value now 101
VALUE -= 2 ; * Value now 99
VALUE := '!' ; * Value now 99!

Computers: Universe: Basic Good Practice

Efficiency

'Go faster' operators

Always use VAR1 += VAR2 in place of VAR1 = VAR1 + VAR2: it is appreciably faster. Favour -= and := similarly.

For next loops

Don't use expressions as terminating values in FOR/NEXT loops: use only constants or variables. For instance, rewrite:

FOR RECORD.NUMBER = 1 TO DCOUNT(RECORD.LIST, @FM)
   * Do something
NEXT RECORD.NUMBER

...as...

NUMBER.OF.RECORDS = DCOUNT(RECORD.LIST, @FM)
FOR RECORD.NUMBER = 1 TO NUMBER.OF.RECORDS
   * Do something
NEXT RECORD.NUMBER

This prevents UniVerse recalculating the terminating value every time round the loop. If you cannot restructure your FOR/NEXT loop because you are relying on the recalculation, replace the FOR/NEXT loop with a LOOP/REPEAT loop. It may be faster, but it will definitely be more readable.

CASE constructs

If your CASE conditions are mutually exclusive, their order will make no difference to the behaviour of your code, but may make a difference to its performance. Even where the conditions are not mutually exclusive, they can sometimes be rearranged without affecting the logic of the program, to increase its speed.

This is because UniVerse evaluates each condition in turn until it encounters one which is true: the more often it finds that the first CASE is true, the fewer comparisons it need make in total. (See Basic Conditions for a detailed example).

Testing for existence

The quickest way to test a record for existence (assuming you don't need to read any of the information it contains) is to use READV to read field 0 thus:

READV DUMMY FROM VOC.FILE, 'RECORD.BEING.TESTED', 0 ELSE PRINT "It's missing!"

Looping through dynamic arrays

Never loop through a dynamic array using a subscript to address each field. Addressing individual fields by subscript within a dynamic array takes time: the higher the subscript, the more time. Use LOOP/REPEAT around a REMOVE statement instead. REMOVE is specifically designed to remove consecutive dynamic array fields without searching from the beginning of an array to resolve a subscript each time.

Creating select lists

Use the UniVerse Basic SELECT statement instead of EXECUTE 'SELECT...' wherever possible. If the reason you did not use it originally is because you wanted a sorted list, ask yourself if your program really needs to sort the list: quite often batch programs which need not sort are given sorted lists merely because it makes the display of keys 'currently being processed' neater: this is an expensive luxury.

If you already have a dynamic array, and you wish to turn it into a select list, you need NOT write it to &SAVEDLISTS& and then issue an EXECUTE 'GET.LIST...'. You may sometimes find this approach taken in early UniVerse Basic (or PICK or INFO Basic) because it was at one time the only available method. You may now, though, simply say SELECT DYNAMIC.ARRAY: the select statement, when followed by a dynamic array, will turn the array into a select list, and save a great deal of time.

Arrays

Use dimensioned rather than dynamic arrays unless there is a good reason not to: the elements of a dimensioned array are far quicker to address than the fields of a dynamic array.

If you need a dynamic array, keep it one-dimensional by using only field marks: not value or subvalue marks. Most of the things which dynamic arrays are good at (being searched, sorted, grown, shrunk and traversed) are made difficult or possible once it contains mixed markers. Think of dynamic arrays as a 'list' type.

Growing dynamic arrays

For some reason...

DYNAMIC.ARRAY := @FM : 'NEWFIELD'

...is generally considerably faster than...

DYNAMIC.ARRAY<-1> = 'NEWFIELD'

...despite the fact that they are nearly identical. Both add a field to a dynamic array. The <-1> syntax is slightly neater, as if DYNAMIC.ARRAY is empty above, the := @FM syntax will add an empty field before the new field. However, this can easily be dealt with by writing...

DYNAMIC.ARRAY = DYNAMIC.ARRAY[2, LEN(DYNAMIC.ARRAY) - 1]

The time this takes to execute is usually far less than the time gained by using := @FM, paricularly when building a long dynamic array in a loop. You need only trim the first character once.

Removing empty fields

The CONVERT statement changes all the occurences of a character in a string to another character. If the 'from' and 'to' strings contain more than one character, the first character of the first string is converted to the first character of the second, and so on. The TRIM function not only trims leading and trailing spaces from a string, but replaces all multiply occurring spaces within the string with single spaces. You can use CONVERT and TRIM together to remove empty fields from a dynamic array as follows:

CONVERT @FM TO ' ' IN DYNAMIC.ARRAY
DYNAMIC.ARRAY = TRIM(DYNAMIC.ARRAY)
CONVERT ' ' TO @FM IN DYNAMIC.ARRAY

This relies on the fact that an empty field is represented by two field marks next to each other. When they are converted to spaces and trimmed, they are replaced with a single space.

Note that this code assumes that your fields do not already contain spaces. If they do, you must find at least one character which your string could not contain (which we'll represent by the variable SAFE.CHARACTER) and safe gaurd the 'real' spaces as follows:

CONVERT ' ' : @FM TO SAFE.CHARACTER : ' ' IN DYNAMIC.ARRAY
DYNAMIC.ARRAY = TRIM(DYNAMIC.ARRAY)
CONVERT SAFE.CHARACTER : ' ' TO ' ' : @FM IN DYNAMIC.ARRAY

Cleaning strings

To 'clean' a string of any characters which do not want, first define a variable which contains all the characters which you do want. For instance, if the surnames in your system must be purely alphabetic, try the following:

LEGAL.CHARACTERS = 'ABCDEFGHIJKLMNOPQRSTUVWXYZ'
JUNK.CHARACTERS = SURNAME
CONVERT LEGAL.CHARACTERS TO '' IN JUNK.CHARACTERS ; * So anything left is junk...
CONVERT JUNK.CHARACTERS TO '' IN SURNAME ; * ...which can be got rid of.

Quality

FOR/NEXT counter variables

Never rely on the value of a counter variable outside a FOR/NEXT loop. It is undefined. Even if you find that it reliably takes a particular and useful value, that could change with the next release of the UniVerse Basic compiler.

Subroutine parameters

Don't use subroutine parameters as 'working variables' within your subroutine. Assign them new values only if it is clearly the purpose of the subroutine to do so.

When calling a subroutine, put brackets around naked variables if you do not wish them to be changed by the subroutine you are calling: this converts them to 'expressions' and is sufficient to prevent them being changed even if the subroutine you are calling attempts to change them.

Record locking

1. Never create, update, or delete a record without first obtaining an update lock with READU, MATREADU or READVU.

2. Never assume that a record has remained unchanged since you read it unless you obtained an update lock (READU) or shared lock (READL) which you still hold.

3. Never keep records locked longer than you have to.

Computers: Universe: Basic External Subroutines

Within any system, there are some tasks which are common to many different routines. Some of them are highly abstract, like the task of sorting a list or calculating a factorial number: some are specific to the real world purpose of the system, like running a credit check against a customer code, but either way they may be a necessary part of many different UniVerse Basic programs.

It would, of course, be a waste of time to write the same 'customer credit check' code in every UniVerse Basic program which required it. It would multiply the chance of error, as each implementation of the task would require separate testing, and if any changes were made to the real world credit checking procedure, they would have to be reflected by code changes in many different programs.

It would be better if you could write a single CHECK.CUSTOMER.CREDIT subroutine which could be accessed by any other program as required. And, of course, you can.

To call an external subroutine, you use the CALL statement, followed by the name of the subroutine, and a list of 'parameter' values in round brackets and separated by commas. For example:

CUSTOMER.CODE = ORDER.RECORD(4)
ORDER.VALUE = ORDER.RECORD(7)
CREDIT.OK = 0
CALL CHECK.CREDIT(CREDIT.OK, CUSTOMER.CODE, ORDER.VALUE)
IF CREDIT.OK THEN
   GOSUB FULFILL.ORDER
END ELSE
   GOSUB REJECT.ORDER
END

In this routine, the external subroutine CHECK.CREDIT is called. It is 'passed' three parameters. CUSTOMER.NUMBER and ORDER.VALUE are supplied as the information the external subroutine requires to make its decision, and CREDIT.OK is the variable that the calling routine is expecting the subroutine to assign. The calling routine then bases its choice between fulfilling and rejecting the order on the new value of CREDIT.OK value.

The subroutine might look something like this:

   SUBROUTINE CHECK.CREDIT(RESULT.FLAG, CUSTOMER.ID, CREDIT.REQUESTED)
   RESULT.FLAG = 1
   BEGIN CASE
      CASE CUSTOMER.ID = 'ACME' ;* No more credit for ACME!!
         RESULT.FLAG = 0
      CASE CUSTOMER.ID = 'GSL'  AND CREDIT.REQUESTED > 500 ; * Limited credit to GSL
         RESULT.FLAG = 0
      CASE CREDIT.REQUESTED > 1000 ; * Noone gets more than 1000
         RESULT.FLAG = 0
   END CASE
   RETURN
END

This isn't a very realistic example: very few companies would hard code volatile commercial data into a subroutine, but it serves to illustrate the principle. As you can see, the CHECK.CREDIT routine is like any other UniVerse Basic program, except for two things: it begins with a SUBROUTINE statement, and it ends with a RETURN,

The SUBROUTINE statement quotes the name of the subroutine, and lists the parameters which any calling routines have to supply. If you compare the CALL statement in the calling routine with the SUBROUTINE statement above, you will see that while the parameter variables have different names, they correspond in number and purpose. In fact, the parameters are passed by position: as long as the RESULT.FLAG is passed as the first parameter by the calling program, it doesn't matter what variable name is used to pass it. The same goes for the other variables.

The RETURN statement returns control to the statement following the CALL statement in the calling routine.

Note that the value of RESULT.FLAG is changed in the subroutine, and that the change is reflected in the value of CREDIT.OK in the calling routine. The technical term for this is 'passing by reference'. What it means is that the calling routine is actually passing not merely a value '0' as the current value of CREDIT.OK, it is passing the variable CREDIT.OK itself. Thus, when any changes are made to RESULT.FLAG, they are made to CREDIT.OK in the main program automatically.

The alternative is called 'passing by value', in which only the value is passed, and changes in the subroutine do not affect the main routine. In most programming languages, you are given an explicit choice when you write your calls to subroutines which parameters you will pass by reference and which by value. UniVerse Basic does not do so quite so directly. If you use a single variable name in a parameter position, it will pass it by reference, meaning that the subroutine will have the power to change the value of the variable in the calling routine. If you use a constant or an expression, it will pass by value, preventing any changes in the corresponding variable in the subroutine affecting the calling routine.

However, you can use this knowledge to prevent variables which you don't want changed being passed by reference. Simply turn them into expressions. The simplest expression which evaluates to the value of variable X is (X). By putting brackets round variables in your CALL, you prevent the subroutine you call changing them.

For this reason, it might have been better to write the CALL statement in the original example like this:

CALL CALL CHECK.CREDIT(CREDIT.OK, (CUSTOMER.CODE), (ORDER.VALUE))

This is, in fact, what I'd recommend. Not only is it safer, but it adds documentation. Anyone looking at this CALL can see that you don't plan to have CUSTOMER.CODE and ORDER.VALUE changed. However, whether you do this depends on how confident you are that your subroutines never change parameters they shouldn't.

In order to all CHECK.CREDIT to be called, it must be compiled (like any program) and then 'cataloged': or added to a register of subroutines kept by UniVerse. The most common catalog command looks like this: CATALOG filename programname, so in this case would have run:

CATALOG BP CHECK.CREDIT

However, only puts the subroutine on a register of subroutines available from the current account. If you are writing a subroutine you wish to make available to programs in any account, you must use a 'glabal' catalog. The syntax is slightly different, as you put an asterisk in front of the subroutine name when cataloging:

CATALOG BP *CHECK.CREDIT

The CALL statement required to call a globally catalogued subroutine is also slighted different, also taking an asterisk before the subroutine name:

CALL *CALL CHECK.CREDIT(CREDIT.OK, (CUSTOMER.CODE), (ORDER.VALUE))

If you make changes to a catalogued subroutine - whether it is cataloged within the account or globally cataloged - the changes will not become visible to calling routines until the subroutine has been recompiled and recataloged. When you recatalog a globally cataloged routine you will see the following warning:

>CATALOG BP *CHECK.CREDIT
"*CHECK,CREDIT" already exists globally.
Overwriting this file may affect other users.
Do you want to overwrite the existing version?  (Y/N) =

Enter a Y to force the catalog. To prevent the warning appearing, add the word FORCE to the CATALOG command:

>CATALOG BP *CHECK.CREDIT FORCE
"*CHECK.CREDIT" cataloged.

Computers: Universe: Basic Syntax

About Basic Syntax

What follows is not a mathematically rigorous description of UniVerse Basic syntax, which I was interested to discover cannot be found even in the VMark's documentation. Such descriptions are useful and even necessary in the punctuation-ridden world of C and Pascal, but would be overkill here. This more informal list of rules, though, should get you through most programs.

Programs

Your program must end with an END statement. END is also used to close blocks of code (more of this later), so if the compiler message Final END statment missing appears, while it is possible that you have forgotten this, it is much more likely that you've failed to close a block of code within the program, and so the final END statement is being pressed into service closing a block which should have been closed earlier in the code.

Example: END

Statements

UniVerse Basic statements must be written in upper case.

Example:
STOP

The three statements REM (short for 'remark'), * and !, are all comment statements, and anything following them on the same line is ignored by the compiler.

Example:
* This is a comment

Sadly, Basic statements may not span more than one line: not even comments. You can, though, put more than one statement on a line by separating them with semi-colons: though I would only recommend this for 'end of line' comments.

Example:
STOP ; * Stop here

A semi colon appearing after a comment statment is considered part of that comment, not a statement separator.

Example:
* This line doesn't print anything ; PRINT 'Hello'

Variables

While variable names may be written in either case, and are not case sensitive, I strongly recommend you follow the almost universal (no pun intended) practice of writing them in upper case, and separating the words they contain with dots. Lower case variable names may even be mistaken for a comment or literal string, these being the only places lower case normally appears in UniVerse Basic.

Example:
PRINT INVOICE.VALUE

Constants

You must enclose string constants between a pair of single quotes, double quotes, or (unusually but sometimes usefully) backslashes. My own policy is to use single quotes by default, double quotes where the string to enclose contains single quotes, and backslashes where it contains single and double quotes.

Examples:
PRINT 'The Gazette'
PRINT "The Angler's Gazette"
PRINT \The "Angler's Gazette" magazine\

Numbers may be written without quotes. Positive numbers may have or omit a leading + (I would recommend you omit it lest someone thinks you omitted an operand in what was meant to be an addition, so odd does it look), but negative numbers must naturally carry a leading -. Decimal points may be used as usual.

Examples:
PRINT 123.45
PRINT +123.45 ; * (looks odd, huh?)
PRINT -123.45

Very big and very small numbers may be easier to represent in scientific notiation. Write a number greater than or equal to 1 and less than 10, and follow it by an E followed by the number places to shift the decimal point (negative numbers shift it to the left, making the number smaller than 1).

Examples:
PRINT 2E5 ; * Prints 200000
PRINT 2E-3 ; * Prints 0.003

Computers: Universe: Basic Types

Typelessness

All values in a UniVerse Basic program, whether they represent words, numbers, 'true/false' flags, or dates in the real world, are stored as strings of characters. This is what was meant by the assertion in the introduction to this course that UniVerse is 'typeless' (see The UniVerse Paradigm).

Whether a value is deemed to represent a piece of text, a number, a flag or a date depends entirely on the logic of your program and on the UniVerse Basic functions and operators you use. The following examples demonstrates a single value being treated first as if it represented a string, then a number, then a flag, and finally a date:

VALUE = 3479
* Concatenation assumes the value to represent a string
PRINT (VALUE : '2') ; * Prints 34792
* Addition assumes the value to represent a number
PRINT (VALUE + 2) ; * Prints 3481
* The IF statement assumes the value to represent a 'true' or 'false' flag
IF VALUE THEN PRINT 'TRUE' ELSE PRINT 'FALSE' ; * Prints TRUE
* This function assumes the value represents a date
PRINT (OCONV(VALUE, 'D')) ; * Prints 10 JUL 1977

Some operators and functions, like : (concatenation operator), obviously assume that your values represent strings. Others, like + (addition operator), obviously assume that they represent numbers. When using such operators it's not usually difficult to work out what UniVerse Basic will do. However, some are less obvious. Consider the following example. If the values are deemed to represent strings, they are clearly different. On the other hand, if they are deemed to represent numbers, they are the same. Which does UniVerse Basic do?

VALUE1 = 3479
VALUE2 = '03479'
IF VALUE1 = VALUE2 THEN PRINT 'SAME' ELSE PRINT 'DIFFERENT'

In fact, it prints SAME: thus demonstrating that, for the purposes of the comparison, the program assumed that both values represented numbers, and so concentrated on the value of the numbers they represented.

Stricty speaking, it would be more consistent for UniVerse Basic to support two operators, one doing a string comparison (say. =, and the other doing a numeric comparison (say, ==). After all, this is how it gets round the problem of addition: to add strings you use :, to add numbers +. However, this would seem odd, and UniVerse in general takes a very pragmatic view of such issues, preferring intuitiveness to mathematical consistency. It would also lead to errors. It would be annoying if your program reported a discrepancy between the total as printed on your invoice (say, 1000.00) and the sum of your net amount and your sales tax (say, 900+100 yielding 1000), just because you forgot to use == instead of =. It therefore decides for itself which you are likely to mean.

If you are ever in doubt about how an expression will be evaluated, you can test it without having to write, compile and run a test program. Use a RetrieVe enquiry like:

>LIST VOC SAMPLE 1 ID.SUP EVAL "IF 123='0123' THEN 'SAME' ELSE 'DIFFERENT'"

LIST VOC SAMPLE 1 ID.SUP EVAL "IF 123="0123" THEN "SAME" ELSE "DIFFERENT"" 12:08
:39  08-23-99  PAGE 1
IF 123='0123' THEN '
SAME' ELSE 'DIFFEREN
T'..................

SAME

Sample of 1 records listed.
>

This uses the EVAL keyword to test your expression: Handily, the expression itself appears as the column heading, and the value underneath it. (For information about EVAL, see Overriding Dictionaries).

Strings

If a value is deemed to represent a string, all its characters are significant. For instance:

VALUE1 = 'ABC'
VALUE2 = 'abc'
VALUE3 = ' ABC'
IF VALUE1 = VALUE2 THEN PRINT 'SAME' ELSE PRINT 'DIFFERENT' ; * Prints 'DIFFERENT'
IF VALUE1 = VALUE3 THEN PRINT 'SAME' ELSE PRINT 'DIFFERENT' ; * Prints 'DIFFERENT'
IF VALUE2 = VALUE3 THEN PRINT 'SAME' ELSE PRINT 'DIFFERENT' ; * Prints 'DIFFERENT'

Numbers

If a value represents a number, the form of the number is immaterial as long as UniVerse recognises it as being number. For instance:

VALUE1 = '12.3'
VALUE2 = '012.30'
VALUE3 = ' 1.23E1'
IF VALUE1 = VALUE2 THEN PRINT 'SAME' ELSE PRINT 'DIFFERENT' ; * Prints 'SAME'
IF VALUE1 = VALUE3 THEN PRINT 'SAME' ELSE PRINT 'DIFFERENT' ; * Prints 'SAME'
IF VALUE2 = VALUE3 THEN PRINT 'SAME' ELSE PRINT 'DIFFERENT' ; * Prints 'SAME'

Dates

A value can represent a date if it can also represent an integer, because it is then taken to be the number of days since the 31st of December 1967. For instance, the value 4, if deemed to represent a date, represents the 4th of January 1967. The date on which these notes were written (the 23rd of August, 1999) would be represented by the value 11558.

The rules for comparing dates are therefore the same as the rules for comparing numbers. If two values represent the same integer, they also represent the same date.

Clearly, it is no use printing the value 11558 on a screen or a report and expecting the user to understand it. A function called OCONV is therefore provided to 'convert for output'. The first parameter is the value to convert, and the second value the 'conversion specification'. The conversion specification for dates is D.

PRINT OCONV(11558, 'D') ; * Prints 23 AUG 1999

If you wish, you can be more specific in your 'conversion specification'.

PRINT OCONV(11558, 'D-DMY[2,2,2]') ; * Prints 23-08-99
PRINT OCONV(11558, 'D/MDY[2,2,4]') ; * Prints 08/23/1999
PRINT OCONV(11558, 'D DMY[2,A,4]') ; * Prints 23 AUGUST 1999

The conversion specification for dates runs as follows:
D for date
the character to separate the elements of the date (-, / and a space are used above)
the letters DMY arranged as you would like the day, month and year arranged
in square brackets, the number of digits in the date month and year: note the use of A for the alpha month.

The function ICONV() (convert from input) does the reverse:

PRINT ICONV('23 AUGUST 1999', 'D') ; * Prints 11558

Storing dates in this way makes date arithemetic extremely simple.

BASE.DATE = ICONV('23 AUG 1999', 'D')
WEEK.LATER = BASE.DATE + 7
PRINT OCONV(WEEK.LATER, 'D') ; * Prints 30 AUG 1999
WEEK.EARLIER = BASE.DATE - 7
PRINT OCONV(WEEK.EARLIER, 'D') ; * Prints 16 AUG 1999
DATE.OF.MILLENIUM = ICONV('01 JAN 2000', 'D')
PRINT DATE.OF.MILLENIUM - BASE.DATE : ' days till millenium' ; * Prints 131 days till millenium

Most applications store dates in fields in this way, using the third 'conversion' field of the corresponding dictionary record to ensure that a 'human readable' date is displayed in any column including the date. (See Data fields.)

True and false: 'boolean' flags

Any value can be deemed to represent truth or falsity. If it is numerically equal to zero or is an empty string, it represents false: if anything else, it represents truth.

IF '' THEN PRINT 'TRUE' ELSE PRINT 'FALSE' ; * Prints FALSE
IF ' ' THEN PRINT 'TRUE' ELSE PRINT 'FALSE' ; * Prints TRUE
IF 0 THEN PRINT 'TRUE' ELSE PRINT 'FALSE' ; * Prints FALSE
IF 1 THEN PRINT 'TRUE' ELSE PRINT 'FALSE' ; * Prints TRUE
IF 0.5 THEN PRINT 'TRUE' ELSE PRINT 'FALSE' ; * Prints TRUE
IF 0.0 THEN PRINT 'TRUE' ELSE PRINT 'FALSE' ; * Prints FALSE

The IF statements above may look a little odd, as you will more commonly see comparisons provided as conditions, such as:

IF 1 > 2 THEN PRINT '1 is bigger than 2' ELSE PRINT '1 is not bigger than 2'

But comparison operators like =, >, < work by evaluating to a '1' if the condition they represent is true, or a '0' if it is false. In the example above, the expression 1 > 2 is false, and so evaluates to 0, and therefore has the same effect as the statement IF 0 THEN... in the earlier example.

Computers: Universe: Dictionaries

Dictionaries have been mentioned in passing several times in earlier sections without a full explanation of their use: we will now examine them in detail.

To begin with, whenever you create a UniVerse file, you are actually creating two files: a data file, and a dictionary file. The terminology here is somewhat confusing at first until you get used to it. Let's say you create a file called CUSTOMER.INVOICES. The term file is used to refer both to the thing you've created (ie. the CUSTOMER.INVOICES file, complete with data and dictionary portions), and to the data file and dictionary file individually. You get used to it.

Let's try this as an example:

>CREATE.FILE CUSTOMER.INVOICES DYNAMIC
WARNING: An operating system file will be created with a truncated name.
Creating file "CUSTOMER.001" as Type 30.
Creating file "D_CUSTOMER.001" as Type 3, Modulo 1, Separation 2.
Added "@ID", the default record for RetrieVe, to "D_CUSTOMER.001".
>

As you can see, there are two 'Creating...' messages. The first refers to the creation of the data file (which has a UNIX filename of CUSTOMER.001), and the second to the creation of the dictionary file (which has a UNIX filename of D_CUSTOMER.001). This makes it clear that the files are physically entirely separate. They are associated by the F (file) type VOC record CUSTOMER.INVOICES, the second field of which points to the data file CUSTOMER.001, and the third line of which points to the dictionary file D_CUSTOMER.001 (see File Pointers). When you use the word CUSTOMER.INVOICES in a UniVerse command, UniVerse consults the VOC file and therefore knows where to find both the data and dictionary files.

In the data file, each record represents an invoice, and be 'keyed' by the invoice number. The fields of each record would each carry some piece of information about an invoice. While a real invoicing file might have hundreds of such fields, a simple layout for the purposes of illustration might run:

Key

|

Invoice number

Field 1

|

Customer name

Field 2

|

Product description

Field 3

|

Unit price

Field 4

|

Quantity invoiced

You could start entering these records simply by using the editor. Try the examples below (for the sake of argument, we'll assume the pricing is in €uros):

>ED CUSTOMER.INVOICES 0001
New record.
----: I
0001= ACME Widgets Limited
0002= Castellated Grommets
0003= 10.38
0004= 2000
0005= (Press RETURN)
Bottom at line 5.
----: FI
"0001" filed in file "CUSTOMER.INVOICES".
>ED CUSTOMER.INVOICES 0002
New record.
----: I
0001= Universal Thingies Inc.
0002= Revolving Stud Pins
0003= 427
0004= 7
0005= (Press RETURN)
Bottom at line 5.
----: FI
"0002" filed in file "CUSTOMER.INVOICES".
>ED CUSTOMER.INVOICES 0003
New record.
----: I
0001= Imperial Exporters plc
0002= Galvanised Retention Sprockets
0003= 38
0004= 104
0005= (Press RETURN)
Bottom at line 5.
----: FI
"0003" filed in file "CUSTOMER.INVOICES".

As you can see, you were able to create the file and enter records without a dictionary. So why do you need a dictionary?

Their primary use is to explain the structure of their records to the Retrieve enquiry language. This language is explained in detail later (turn to The Retrieve Query Language), but a few simple examples will be used here to illustrate the use of dictionaries.

Let's say you wanted to enquire on the records you had just entered. The simplest way to do this would be to use the LIST command. Try this:

>LIST CUSTOMER.INVOICES

LIST CUSTOMER.INVOICES 11:51:31 08-06-99 PAGE 1
CUSTOMER.INVOICES

0001
0002
0003

3 records listed.
>

This is fine as far as it goes: you have a complete listing of the keys of the records you entered on your screen. But to show the contents of those records, you must define dictionary records. The following sections describe the different types of dictionary record, how to create them, and how they are used.

Computers: Universe: Data Fields

Each record in the dictionary file represents a field in the corresponding data file. For instance, the first field of the CUSTOMER.INVOICES file contains customer names. A record called CUSTOMER.NAME should therefore be created on the dictionary to represent it.

The easiest way to enter dictionary records is with the editor. All dictionary records have the same format:

>ED DICT CUSTOMER.INVOICES CUSTOMER.NAME
New record.

----: I
0001= D The customer's trading name
0002= 1
0003= (Enter a space and press RETURN)
0004= Customer Name
0005= 15T
0006= S
0007= (Press RETURN)
Bottom at line 7.
----: FI
"CUSTOMER.NAME" filed in file "CUSTOMER.INVOICES".

Note that the keyword DICT was used before the file name CUSTOMER.INVOICES to refer to the dictionary of the file. In general, where a command takes the form command filename ... you can use command DICT filename... to apply the command to the dictionary of a file.

The first field of the dictionary record is much like the first field of a VOC record, being made up of a one or two letter type, followed by an optional description. In this case, the type is D, meaning 'data' (you will encounter other types in the following sections), and the description is The customer's trading name. This last is there solely as internal documentation, to provide information to anyone who might edit the dictionary record in the future.

The second field (of a D type - other types use their second fields differently) of the dictionary record carries the field number of each data record which carries the CUSTOMER.NAME. In this case, as field 1 of every CUSTOMER.INVOICES record carries the customer's name, the value here is 1.

The third field contains a 'conversion specification'. This is because the form in which some information is typically stored by UniVerse differs from the form in which it is displayed. For instance, dates are stored as the number of days passed since 1967. The way in which a field should be converted before display can be coded. For dates, for instance, the conversion code of D DMY[2,A3,4] would store 1 and display 01 JAN 1968. Text strings like customer names, though, are generally displayed exactly as stored, and so the conversion specification can be left blank. The space entered above is ignored.

The fourth field is the title which will appear at the head of the column of customer names in an enquiry.

The fifth field combines the width of the column displayed in the enquiry with the 'justification' of the column. For instance, to display a right-justified column 10 characters wide, you would enter a format of 10R. To allow 30 characters, left justified but breaking on complete words where possible, you would enter 30T (T standing for 'text' justification). Please bear in mind that this does not set a limit on the capacity of the field. Even if a dictionary record defines a field as having a format of 10R, it may contain 11 characters (or 111). They will simply 'wrap around' the column in an enquiry.

Finally, the sixth field contains either an S or an M. As was explained during our discussion of the UniVerse's data structures (see The UniVerse Paradigm above), fields can be further divided into values, and values into subvalues. If a field is designed to hold more than one piece of information in this way, it is multi-valued and must carry an M in this field of its dictionary record. Otherwise, it is single-valued and carries an S.

In the same way, set up the following records in DICT CUSTOMER.INVOICES

| |

PRODUCT

|

UNIT.PRICE

|

QUANTITY

1

|

Type/Description

|

D Product sold

|

D Unit Price

|

D Quantity sold

2

|

Field Number

|

2

|

3

|

4

3

|

Conversion

|

(blank)

|

MD20P

|

(blank)

4

|

Column Header

|

Product

|

Unit Price

|

Quantity

5

|

Format

|

20T

|

10R

|

10R

6

|

S or M

|

S

|

S

|

S

Now try the command:

>LIST CUSTOMER.INVOICES CUSTOMER.NAME PRODUCT UNIT.PRICE QUANTITY

LIST CUSTOMER.INVOICES CUSTOMER.NAME PRODUCT UNIT.PRICE QUANTITY 16:41:00  08-06
-99  PAGE 1
CUSTOMER.INVOICES  Customer Name..  Product.............  Unit Price  Quantity..

0001               ACME Widgets     Castellated Grommets       10.38        2000
                   Limited
0002               Universal        Revolving Stud Pins       427.00           7
                   Thingies Inc.
0003               Imperial         Galvanised Retention       38.00         104
                   Exporters plc    Sprockets
>

The LIST command consulted the dictionary of CUSTOMER.INVOICES to determine the meaning of the words CUSTOMER.NAME, PRODUCT, UNIT.PRICE and QUANTITY, and was therefore able to extract the appropriate data from each record and format it appropriately. Note, for instance, that the customer and product names are being wrapped on word boundaries as a result of their ...T formats, and that the unit price is showing two decimal places even where decimal places were not included as part of the data, thanks to its MD20P conversion. (This conversion code, and others, will be explained in the section on UniVerse Basic).

Note that LIST displays the record keys automatically, using the file name as the column header, and extending the width of the column to accomodate this name. While it's useful to show the keys, this is not the best format to choose.

It is determined by the dictionary record @ID. This dictionary record is created automatically when you create a file, as whatever other fields you may decide on, UniVerse knows that you must have a key to each record. You should never delete the @ID dictionary record, because UniVerse can become confused if it does not find it: but you can edit it to control the way in which the key is shown in enquiries. The table below shows both the 'default' @ID record as it was created by UniVerse, and a modified version which would show the keys more suitably. Use the editor to modify the @ID appropriately.

| |

Default @ID

|

Improved @ID

1

|

Type/Description

|

D Default record ID for RetrieVe

|

D Invoice number

2

|

Field Number

|

0

|

0

3

|

Conversion

|

(blank)

|

(blank)

4

|

Column Header

|

CUSTOMER.INVOICES

|

InvNum

5

|

Format

|

10L

|

6R

6

|

S or M

|

S

|

S

Rerunning the command we tried earlier now gives the following results:

LIST CUSTOMER.INVOICES CUSTOMER.NAME PRODUCT UNIT.PRICE QUANTITY 17:41:33  08-06
-99  PAGE 1
InvNum    Customer Name..    Product.............    Unit Price    Quantity..

  0001    ACME Widgets       Castellated Grommets         10.38          2000
          Limited
  0002    Universal          Revolving Stud Pins         427.00             7
          Thingies Inc.
  0003    Imperial           Galvanised Retention         38.00           104
          Exporters plc      Sprockets

3 records listed.
>

As you can see, the invoice number now has a more meaningful column header, and a column width more appropriate to its length.

You may have noticed a similarity between the use of dictionaries and the use of the VOC file. VOC records also begin with a line stating their type and providing a description. They are also used to interpret the meaning of words supplied on a command line. In fact, in some versions of PICK, the VOC file is called the Master Dictionary. The similarity applies to another feature. As you know, you can define a synonym for any word by copying its VOC record under a different key. Similarly, you can set up a synonym for any field name by copying its dictionary record. Making a copy of the CUSTOMER.NAME record called CLIENT.NAME allows you to use these words synonymously in RetrieVe enquiries.

However, this can be more than just a convenient way of making synonyms. As you can see above, the customer name is rather cramped. It has a narrow column width designed to allow all four columns to be shown across the screen at once. But what if you wanted to omit the other columns and show the customer's name in a wider column? You could of course edit the CUSTOMER.NAME dictionary record: but that would mean changing it before each enquiry, which would become cumbersome. A better approach is to create a synonym called, say WIDE.CUSTOMER.NAME, and change its format to 50T. Try this, and then enter the command:

>LIST CUSTOMER.INVOICES WIDE.CUSTOMER.NAME

LIST CUSTOMER.INVOICES WIDE.CUSTOMER.NAME 17:53:56  08-06-99  PAGE 1
InvNum    Customer Name.....................................

  0001    ACME Widgets Limited
  0002    Universal Thingies Inc.
  0003    Imperial Exporters plc

3 records listed.
>

As you can see, each customer name fits comfortably within the new column size, and the original CUSTOMER.NAME field definition is still available.

In fact, though, this is not the method I would recommend to achieve this effect. The problem is that it creates two field names for a single field, and this can be a development and maintenance headache. In much the same way that it is good practice to have a single F type pointer to each file (see File Pointers), it is good practice to have a single D type pointer for each data field. You can still set up synonyms similar to the ones described here, though, using I types, which are discussed in the next section.

Computers: Universe: The Dictionary Dictionary

I have already mentioned that you can apply most commands to dictionary files as easily as to data files. LIST itself is no exception. Try this:

>LIST DICT CUSTOMER.INVOICES

DICT CUSTOMER.INVOICES    17:51:53  08-13-99  Page 1

               Type &
Field......... Field. Field........ Conversion.. Column......... Output Depth &
Name.......... Number Definition... Code........ Heading........ Format Assoc..

@ID            D    0                            InvNum          6R     S
CUSTOMER.NAME  D    1                            Customer Name   15T    S
WIDE.CUSTOMER. D    1                            Customer Name   50T    S
NAME
PRODUCT        D    2                            Product         20T    S
UNIT.PRICE     D    3               MD20P        Unit Price      10R    S
QUANTITY       D    4                            Quantity        10R    S
VALUE          I      UNIT.PRICE *  MD20P        Value           10R    S
                      QUANTITY

7 records listed.

Here you can see, in a single enquiry, all the dictionary records you have defined. An interesting point, though, is that in order to format an enquiry like this, LIST requires a dictionary. After all, how does it know that the title of the first column is 'Field Name'? And indeed, how did it know which columns to display, given that you specified no field names after your LIST command?

The answer to both questions is that every dictionary has a dictionary. But does this mean that that dictionary in turn must have a dictionary, and so on in an infinite series of dictionaries? No. The thing is, while the format of each data file is unique, and so must have a unique dictionary, the dictionary files themselves are all structured exactly the same way: and you've learnt this structure in the last few sections. This means that they can all share the same dictionary. It is called DICT.DICT. Take a look:

>LIST DICT.DICT

DICT.DICT    18:00:34  08-13-99  Page 1

               Type &
Field......... Field. Field........ Conversion.. Column......... Output Depth &
Name.......... Number Definition... Code........ Heading........ Format Assoc..

@ID            D    0                            Field           14L    S
                                                 Name
FIELD          D    0                            Field           14L    S
                                                 Name
ID             D    0                                            15L    S
ITEM.ID        D    0                                            10T    S
KEYR           D    0                                            15R    S
KEY            D    0                                            15L    S
CODE           D    1                                            4L     S
F1             D    1                                            35L    S
EXP            D    2                            FIELD # or EXPR 30T    S
                                                 ESSION
A2             D    2                                            3R     S
DATA.FILE      D    2                            DATA.FILE.NAME  30T    S
LOC.           D    2                            LOC.            3T     S
LOC.L          D    2                            LOCATION        40T    S
LOC            D    2                            LOCATION        15T    S
Press any key to continue...

This listing goes on for a number of pages, and is not as friendly as it might be, largely because UniVerse themselves do not follow the rule I recommended whereby each field is given a single D type entry to define it. Don't ask me why: I've told them often enough, but they've stopped answering my mail.

But doesn't DICT.DICT also require a dictionary? Well, because it is a dictionary, it follows the same structure that any dictionary follows. And the dictionary of a dictionary is... DICT.DICT. In other words, DICT.DICT is its own dictionary. You can prove this curious fact to yourself by sneaking a look at its VOC record:

>ED VOC DICT.DICT
3 lines long.

----: P
0001: F
0002: /work/universe/DICT.DICT
0003: /work/universe/DICT.DICT
Bottom at line 3.
----: Q
>

And there it is: field 2 (which points to the data file) and field 3 (which points to the dictionary file) both point to the same file (see File Pointers for information about file pointers). This neat device precludes the need for an infinite series of dictionaries.

To find out how LIST decides which fields to show when you enter a LIST DICT filename command without specifying field names (as you did above), check out the @ record in DICT.DICT (for information about how the @ phrase determines the default enquiry, see Phrases):

>ED DICT CUSTOMER.INVOICES @
The file "DICT.DICT" is read-only and cannot be updated.
3 lines long.

----: P
0001: PH
0002: BY FIELD.NO BY TYPE ID.SUP FIELD FIELD.TYPE FIELD.DEF FIELD.CONV FIELD.HE AD FIELD.FMT FIELD.ASSOC_
0003: HEADING "'F' 'T' Page 'PL'"
Bottom at line 3.
----: Q
>

Several things to notice here.

1. The field names, and the BY clauses, determine what you see when you type LIST DICT filename....

2. A trick I haven't mentioned before: the use of a _ character at the end of line 2 to allow the phrase to continue on line 3: which you can use in any phrase which gets rather long.

3. The HEADING clause, which puts a custom written heading at the top of your enquiry. I'll explain this, along with other clever things the query language can do, in the section on RetrieVe.

4. The ...read-only... message: as you can see from the paths on fields 2 and 3, DICT.DICT points to the central UniVerse directory. If you changed it, you'd change the way every dictionary is displayed, not just in this account, but in every account on your system. UniVerse only gives toys like this to the Unix system administrator root. If you don't fully understand what DICT.DICT does, you shouldn't edit it. If you do, you wont anyway.

Computers: Universe: Imaginary Fields

One obvious omission from our CUSTOMER.INVOICES file layout is a field to hold the value of each invoice. It will be apparent, though, that the file holds enough information to calculate the value of the invoice without such a field: so it could be argued that to actually store it is redundant, wasting disk storage when the value, when required, could be derived by taking the product of the UNIT.PRICE and QUANTITY fields at any time.

This approach is fine in UniVerse Basic programs, but what if you wanted (as you surely would) to show the value of each invoice in an enquiry? Without a dictionary record, the word VALUE could not be used in an enquiry.

UniVerse provides a type of dictionary record which allows you to reference a field like VALUE which is not physically stored in a record, but can be derived by applying a formula to other fields which are. It is called an imaginary dictionary record, I-type dictionary record, or simply an I-descriptor.

Create a VALUE I-descriptor like this:

>ED DICT CUSTOMER.INVOICES VALUE
New record.

----: I
0001= I Value of invoice
0002= UNIT.PRICE * QUANTITY
0003= (Enter a space and press ENTER)
0004= Value
0005= 10R
0006= S
0007= (Press ENTER)
----: FI
"VALUE" saved in file "DICT CUSTOMER.INVOICES".
>

You may find this record familiar, as it is very similar to the dictionary records we created for PRODUCT, UNIT.PRICE and QUANITY in the last section (see Data fields). In fact, only the second line of an I-descriptor is significantly different. The first, as do all first lines of dictionary records, consists of the type (an I) followed optionally by a description. The third, fourth, fifth and sixth lines are all as described before.

In a D type dictionary record, however, the second line contains the number of the field being referenced. For instance, the dictionary record UNIT.PRICE contains a 3 on its second line, as it can be found on the third field of every CUSTOMER.INVOICES record. As the VALUE of an invoices does not appear in a CUSTOMER.INVOICES record, such a number cannot be used in an I-descriptor.

In it's place is a UniVerse Basic expression which evaluates to the desired value. In this case, as the invoice value can be calculated by multiplying the unit price of the product by the quantity bought, it is UNIT.PRICE * QUANTITY (* being the UniVerse Basic multiplication operator).

To gain full advantage from I-descriptors, it is therefore necessary to understand UniVerse Basic, which is covered at length near the end of this course. However, must I-descriptors are relatively simple, and the most common types are explained below:

Constant I-descriptors

You can create an I-descriptor which always returns the same value, regardless of the record it is evaluated with. For instance, perhaps the simplest I-descriptor formula of all, 1, can be usefully totalled within UniVerse enquiries to provide record counts: as it returns one for each record listed by the enquiry.

Synonym I-descriptors

I argued in the previous section (see Data fields above) that is was good practise to maintain only one D type dictionary record for each field in the data file, thus giving each field a unique and consistent name. If you wish to set up a synonym of the CUSTOMER.NAME field, giving the customer name a wider column to live in, create an I-descriptor called WIDE.CUSTOMER.NAME with a formula of CUSTOMER.NAME. One advantage of this tidy approach is quickly apparent: should the file ever be redesigned, pushing the customer's name onto the second field, editing the CUSTOMER.NAME field is sufficient to accomodate the cange. If CUSTOMER.NAME and WIDE.CUSTOMER.NAME were both D types, they would both have to be modified.

Arithmetic I-descriptors

I-descriptors often apply arithmetic operators to other fields in order to derive new values. VALUE is one such. The UniVerse Basic arithmetic operators are:

*

|

Multiplication

/

|

Division

+

|

Addition

-

|

Subtraction

^

|

Exponentiation

String manipulating I-descriptors

Many I-descriptors operate by adding strings together, taking subsections of strings, or otherwise operating on them. UniVerse Basic is extremely strong at string manipulation, as is appropriate to a database management system that stores all data as strings. You will learn more about its features later, but for now the most commonly used string manipulations in I-descriptors are:

Operation

|

Example formula

|

Result when applied to CUSTOMER.NAME of ACME Widgets Limited and PRODUCT of Castellated Grommets

Slicing relative to the beginning of a string

|

CUSTOMER.NAME[1, 3]

|

ACM

Slicing relative to the end of a string

|

CUSTOMER.NAME[3]

|

ted

Concatenating strings

|

CUSTOMER.NAME : ' buy ' : PRODICT

|

ACME Widgets Limited buy Castellated Gromets

Delimiting a string by a chosen character, and extracting a section

|

FIELD(CUSTOMER.NAME, ' ', 1, bits_menu, computers_menu, universe_menu)

|

Widgets

Converting strings to upper case

|

UPCASE(CUSTOMER.NAME)

|

ACME WIDGETS LIMITED

Converting strings to lower case

|

DOWNCASE(CUSTOMER.NAME)

|

acme widgets limited

Translation I-descriptors

A common requirement is to create a value which reports a value from another UniVerse file. For instance, you might decide to run discount schemes for favoured clients: scheme 'A' for the most lucrative, 'B' for the fairly lucrative, and 'C' for anyone else. You could then add a DISCOUNT.CODE field to your CUSTOMER.INVOICES file, showing which discount you have decided to apply to each invoice. This code would be a key to another file, called DISCOUNT.SCHEMES, which in turn would have a field called PERCENTAGE.DISCOUNT.

To show the DISCOUNT.CODE for each invoice is simple: you can just enter the command LIST CUSTOMER.INVOICES DISCOUNT.CODE. But what if you wanted to show the actual percentage discount? You can't say LIST CUSTOMER.INVOICES PERCENTAGE.DISCOUNT because the dictionary record PERCENTAGE.DISCOUNT is on the dictionary of DISCOUNT.SCHEMES, not the dictionary of CUSTOMER.INVOICES. But you can create an I-descriptor which 'translates' the percentage discount from the DISCOUNT.SCHEMES file.

To do this, you use a UniVerse Basic function called TRANS(). This function is an ordinary part of UniVerse Basic, but is so useful for I-descriptors that you'll rarely find it anywhere else. In the example above, you could create an I-descriptor called DS.PERCENTAGE.DISCOUNT on the dictionary of CUSTOMER.INVOICES. The DS. at the beginning of the name is a reminder to anyone using the field that the data associated with it is actually being obtained from DISCOUNT.SCHEMES. Such prefixes for translation I-descriptors are entirely optional, but useful and very common.

The formula on line 2 of the DS.PERCENTAGE.DISCOUNT I-descriptor would look like this:

TRANS('DISCOUNT.SCHEMES', DISCOUNT.CODE, 'PERCENTAGE.DISCOUNT', 'X')

Taking the four parameters in turn:

1. 'DISCOUNT.SCHEMES' is the name of the file which contains the information you want to translate.

2. DISCOUNT.CODE yields the key to DISCOUNT.SCHEMES. Note that it is not in quotes: this is because it is not the string 'DISCOUNT.CODE' itself which is the key, but the 'A', 'B', or 'C' contained in the field. Remember that field names in the formulas of I-descriptors are replaced with their values: a little like variables in a program.

3. 'PERCENTAGE.DISCOUNT' is the name of the DISCOUNT.SCHEMES field which contains the value you want to retrieve.

4. 'X' is a special code which means 'if the record can't be found, return an empty string'. The three other possible codes are 'V', which does the same as 'X' but displays an error message to highlight the failure, 'C' which returns the key to the record which couldn't be found, and 'N' which returns the key to the record if the value found is an empty string.

Conditional I-descriptors

A common requirement is to take a simple coded field, such as a GENDER field on a PERSONNEL file, and provide a friendlier description of the code for a report: so instead of showing M for male and F for female, you can show the full words Male and Female in your enquiry. The UniVerse Basic expression to achieve this is quite intuitive:

IF GENDER = 'F' THEN 'Female' ELSE 'Male'

(C programmers may notice the similarity to their beloved condition ? trueresult : falseresult syntax).

In fact, this formula is a bit dodgy. What if the GENDER field was empty, or someone updated it incorrectly, entering a W for 'woman' instead of an F for 'female'? In both these cases the formula would yield Male. Fortunately, you can nest IFs:

IF GENDER = 'F' THEN 'Female' ELSE IF GENDER = 'M' THEN 'Male' ELSE 'Unknown'

You now need only to decide if a woman is more likely to be offended by being called 'Male' than by being classified as 'gender unknown'.

Subroutine I-descriptors

It's possible that your I-descriptor may be very complicated. For instance, you might wish to put I-descriptors on the dictionary of your CUSTOMER.INVOICES file showing the value of the invoice in different currencies. You may recall the original figures were in €uros, so you might call your I-descriptors DOLLAR.VALUE, YEN.VALUE, STERLING.VALUE and RAND.VALUE. The calculations might be quite complicated: they would have to access some kind of CURRENCY.RATES file to find today's exchange rate, apply charges for currency conversions, and so on. It is unlikely that such a computation could be expressed neatly, if indeed at all, in a single UniVerse Basic expression.

In such situations, you can use an extremely hand function called SUBR(). Like TRANS() (see above), this is a standard UniVerse Basic function, but is not terribly useful outside I-descriptor formulae: within them, however, it is wonderful.

SUBR() call a UniVerse Basic subroutine of your choice. Subroutines can take a number of 'parameters', similar to parameters in most programming languages (C, Pascal, PL/SQL and so on) and used both to pass values values into the subroutine, and to get values back. All the information you need to create subroutines will be provided later, in the section on UniVerse Basic, but for now it is useful to now that the first line of each subroutine states the subroutine name and the parameters it takes. For instance, a subroutine to convert a Euro value to another currency might look like this:

SUBROUTINE GET.CURRENCY.VALUE(CURRENCY.VALUE, EURO.VALUE, CURRENCY.CODE)

Returning to the formula of your I-descriptor, the SUBR() function takes the same number of parameters as the subroutine you wish to call. The first parameter is the name of the subroutine, and the others provide values to pass into the 2nd parameter in the subroutine onwards. The subroutine must return its result through its first parameter. This is one of those things that is difficult to describe, but simple once you've grasped it. The following implementations of the foreign currency I-desciptors mentioned above may help.

I-descriptor

|

Formula

DOLLAR.VALUE

|

SUBR('GET.CURRENCY.VALUE', VALUE, 'USDOLLAR')

YEN.VALUE

|

SUBR('GET.CURRENCY.VALUE', VALUE, 'JAPYEN')

STERLING.VALUE

|

SUBR('GET.CURRENCY.VALUE', VALUE, 'UKPOUND')

RAND.VALUE

|

SUBR('GET.CURRENCY.VALUE', VALUE, 'SARAND')

As you can see, the formula is the same in each case, with only the currency codes varying. The same subroutine is being called in each case, receiving the €uro value and currency codes in the second and third parameters respectively, and returning the result via the first.

A final note: you may have noticed that the I-descriptor VALUE appears in the formula for the I-descriptor DOLLAR.VALUE. In fact, I-descriptors can refer to I-descriptors just as easily as D type data fields.

Computers: Universe: Indexing Fields

So far in this course, the enquiries you have been running have been extremely simple. They haven't applied any criteria to reduce the number of records displayed: you have been displaying all the records in each file you've enquired on.

Later, you will discover how to list only records which match certain criteria: such as (for example) all the CUSTOMER.INVOICES made out to a particular client, or for over a certain amount. If you apply such a condition to your enquiry, UniVerse simply reads all the records on the file, and includes only those which are appropriate. But what if your file contained 20,000 records and you were only expecting 3 or 4 to be displayed? You'd be waiting a long time for a very short enquiry: long enough for UniVerse to read 20,000 records, and decide that 19,997 of them aren't needed.

This is a problem common to all databases, of course. To get round it, most databases allow you to create indexes (or, as some people have it, 'indices'), Roughly speaking, an index is a file turned upside down: you use the value of a chosen data field as the key, and then read the keys corresponding to that value as data. For instance, an index on the CUSTOMER.NAME would allow you to use the name 'United Boxgirders' as the key, and read all the CUSTOMER.INVOICE keys which carry this company name.

UniVerse supports a rather nice indexing system: reasonably efficient, and (compared to some) very simple to use.

First, we need a file to play with. We'll create a copy of the VOC file to experiment with:

>CREATE.FILE COPY.OF.VOC
Creating file "COPY.OF.VOC" as Type 30.
Creating file "D_COPY.OF.VOC" as Type 3, Modulo 1, Separation 2.
Added "@ID", the default record for RetrieVe, to "D_COPY.OF.VOC".
>

Then we need to load it with records. We can make copies of all the records in the VOC file using the COPY command. Though we wont be covering this in detail until later, its format is fairly transparent:

>COPY FROM VOC TO COPY.OF.VOC ALL

825 records copied.

(The number of records in your VOC file may be different, of course).

As all the records in the COPY.OF.VOC file are the same as those in the VOC file, they must have the same overall structure. If they have the structure, they can use the same dictionary. You can therefore copy all the records from the VOC dictionary to the COPY.OF.VOC dictionary to. You must add the keyword OVERWRITING though, because there is already an @ID record on the dictionary of COPY.OF.VOC which was added automatically during the CREATE.FILE (see above), and you want this overwritten, not preserved.

>COPY FROM DICT VOC TO DICT COPY.OF.VOC ALL OVERWRITING

19 records copied.

You now have a COPY.OF.VOC file that is almost identical to the original VOC the only differences being between their names (of course), and their file types: as the VOC is static, while COPY.OF.VOC is dynamic.

Imagined that you wished to list only the menu pointers, or 'M' type records, in your COPY.OF.VOC file (see Other VOC Records). You can do this by adding a WITH clause to your LIST command. (WITH hasn't been explained yet, but it is not difficult to see the basic idea here: it is described in more detail later in the course).

>LIST COPY.OF.VOC WITH TYPE = 'M'
LIST COPY.OF.VOC WITH TYPE = "M" 15:47:52 08-18-99 PAGE 1
NAME.......... TYPE DESC..........................

CONV.ACCT.MENU M Menu - UniVerse Account
Importation
PRINT.ADMIN.ME M Menu - UniVerse Spooler
NU Administration
BASIC.CONT M Menu
SP.JOB M Menu
CONSYS.MENU M M
SP.MOD M Menu
ACCT.CONV M Menu
SP.STATUS M Menu
MENUS M MENU selector - Invoke the
MENU maintenance menu

9 records listed.
>

In order to display these results, LIST had to read every record in the VOC file: all 800 or so of them, simply to reject 791 as irrelevant. On most systems, the delay while this happened would have been imperceptible, but if you are running on modest hardware you may have noticed a pause before the enquiry finished. But no matter how powerful your computer, by the time this file reached 80,000 or even 800,000 records in size, you'd have noticed the delay. If the number of M type COPY.OF.VOC records remained in ration, you'd now be reading 800,000 records and rejecting 791,000 of them.

To avoid this, you can create an index. The command to do so is extremely simple:

>CREATE.INDEX COPY.OF.VOC TYPE
>

The command is extremely quiet: you are simply returned to the > prompt once it has done its thing. You have created the index, but it is initially empty. To bring the index up to date:

>BUILD.INDEX COPY.OF.VOC TYPE

Locking 'COPY.OF.VOC' file for exclusive use.
Starting SSELECT for file 'COPY.OF.VOC index TYPE'.
Compiling "@Ak.0".
IF F1 [ 1 , 1 ] = P THEN F1 [ 1 , 2 ] ELSE F1 [ 1 , 1 ]
Compiling "@INDEX.TYPE".
IF F1 [ 1 , 1 ] = P THEN F1 [ 1 , 2 ] ELSE F1 [ 1 , 1 ] ; @1 : ( char ( 251 ) ) : @Ak.ID

825 record(s) selected to SELECT list #0.

Clearing Index File INDEX.000

Starting DATA processing for index 'TYPE'!
*********************************
825 total processed.

Updating INDEX.MAP flags...

Index build of TYPE complete.

File 'COPY.OF.VOC' Unlocked.

>

As you can see, by contrast BUILD.INDEX is rather noisy. Thankfully, though, you can ignore it's rather cryptic output. The index has now been brought up to date.

But the best has yet to come. From now on, this index will be updated automatically whenever a record in COPY.OF.VOC is added, changed, or deleted. You need make no changes to your application: even UniVerse Basic programs which update COPY.OF.VOC written before the index was created will automatically update the index whenever they write to COPY.OF.VOC. In fact, these indexes require so little effort that its easy to forget that they are there, which is sometimes a problem, as old, little used, or obsolecent indexes are not always removed, but (like all indexes) still require disk space to store and CPU and I/O time to keep up to date.

It's a good idea to periodically check the indexes on a file: particularly if you are about to add a new index to it. You can do so using LIST.INDEX:

>LIST.INDEX COPY.OF.VOC ALL
Alternate Key Index Summary for file COPY.OF.VOC
File........... COPY.OF.VOC
Indices........ 1 (0 A-type, 0 C-type, 0 D-type, 1 I-type, 0 SQL, 0 S-type)
Index Updates.. Enabled, No updates pending

Index name Type Build Nulls In DICT S/M Just Unique Field num/I-type
TYPE I Not Reqd Yes Yes S L N IF F1[1,1]='P' T
HEN F1[1,2] ELSE
F1[1,1]

>

Finally, if you do need to remove an index, the syntax runs:

>DELETE.INDEX COPY.OF.VOC TYPE
Removing index file TYPE.
>

So how do you take advantage of your index? In most cases, you need do nothing. An enquiry like the one you used above, LIST COPY.OF.VOC WITH TYPE = 'M', will automatically consult the TYPE index if there is one. This also means that any existing application code does not usually have to be modified to take advantage of the new indexes: it will use them if it finds them and gain the performance improvements automatically.

I say 'usually' because there are a few UniVerse Basic statements which are designed to consult indexes directly, and will only work if they are there: you will learn about these later. But these are purely optional: any existing query, whether executed from UniVerse Basic or from the command line, will automatically use indexes if they will help.

Given that they are so easy to create and maintain, why not just index everything and have consistently speedy enquiries? Indexes do carry two costs:

1. Updating an index takes a certain amount of CPU and I/O time. Each index you add increases the amount of work your system has to do when it writes a record.

2. Indices occupy disk space: a file with many indices may grow to several times its original size, and similarly multiply all its costs of storage, maintenance and backup.

Computers: Universe: *: Other dictionary record types

A and S types

You may sometimes come across dictionary records with types of A or S. They play roles similar to D and I type dictionary records, but are supported largely for compatability reasons: some forms of PICK (see About UniVerse above) used these instead of D and I. If you come across them, you'll find their layout described in the UniVerse documentation: but they are both less friendly and less efficient than the types I have already described, and have no extra functionality. My advice would be that if you find yourself having to change one, do so by replacing it with a D or I.

X types

Like X type records in the VOC file, X type dictionary records are not designed to be used as words in commands. They are there to store data. For instance, many files have records keyed by sequential numbers. In order to add a new record to such a file, you must find the lowest unused number you can use as a key. You could do so by enquiring on the file itself, but this would add enormous overhead. Instead, most programmers add a record to the dictionary of the file, called (by convention) &NEXT.AVAILABLE&, which is a type X and carries the lowest unused number on its second field. This is locked, read, updated, and unlocked by every process which adds a record to the main file.

One or two X types are harmless, but as with X type records in your VOC file, bear in mind that each one increases the size of a file crucial to the performance of your system, as well as 'taking up' a word which might otherwise be available as part of your command language. It is therefore advisable to use them sparingly. If you find yourself setting up ten X types on a dictionary, consider setting up a separate UniVerse file for the values, as it seems likely you will be dealing with a new form of 'entity' altogether, rather than merely a chance administrative detail of your main data file.

Computers: Universe: Phrases

Unless you don't get out often enough, once you've typed...

LIST CUSTOMER.INVOICES CUSTOMER.NAME PRODUCT UNIT.PRICE QUANTITY VALUE

...a few times (and most probably mistyped it a few more) it has lost its charm as a form of entertainment. If you find yourself displaying the same group of fields in the same order over and over again, it would be useful if you could define a single word which would automatically collect them all together for you.

Well... you can't, so tough luck.

Only kidding. In fact, its simple. You can create a phrase dictionary record which will do exactly this. To create one for CUSTOMER.INVOICES, enter the command:

>ED DICT CUSTOMER.INVOICES MAIN.FIELDS
New record.

----: I
0001= PH Phrase including all the main fields
0002= CUSTOMER.NAME PRODUCT UNIT.PRICE QUANTITY VALUE
0003= (Press RETURN)
Bottom at line 2.
----: FI
"MAIN.FIELDS" filed in file "DICT CUSTOMER.INVOICES".
>

You may now enter the command:

LIST CUSTOMER.INVOICES MAIN.FIELDS

This will have exactly the same effect as the earlier command, and save your fingers.

Phrases have other advantages. Let us say that your application produces the original enquiry in several places. If you add a new field you would like to include in each of these places, you need to modify each in turn. If, on the other hand, each time the enquiry is used it uses the phrase MAIN.FIELDS, simply changing the phrase is sufficient.

If you create a phrase called @ - that is, just using the 'at' symbol as its key - you need not even name the phrase with your enquiry. Simply typing the command:

LIST CUSTOMER.INVOICES

...has the same effect as typing...

LIST CUSTOMER.INVOICES @

It's good practice to define an @ dictionary record for every file you create. In this way, someone can look at the most important fields in your file (which you decide in advance via your @ dictionary record) simply by entering the command LIST filename, without first having to consult the dictionary.

Similar to @ is @LPTR, which is the 'default phrase' used when you enter the command LIST filename LPTR: which sends the output to a 'line printer'.

The @ and @LPTR phrases are ignored if you enter any field names on your command line: UniVerse assumes you are then listing explicitly the fields you want, and does not alter this selection. If you want to list only record keys (which is what LIST displays in the absense of explicit field names if there is no @ phrase), you can use the command LIST filename ID.ONLY.

You can put other keywords in phrases besides field names. The subject of sorting your enquiry will be covered in more detail during the discussion of the RetrieVe query language, but for now note that you can sort your enquiry results by appending BY fieldname to your LIST command. If you put a BY clause in your phrase, even in your @ phrase, it will apply the sort whenever the phrase is used. In short, you can put any valid Retrieve clause into a phrase.

Computers: Universe: The REVISE Command

Creating and modifying UniVerse records

So far, we have been creating records using the editor: and you will find throughout your UniVerse career that this is often the simplest and quickest way of entering and modifying information. It is particularly useful when you are very familiar with the format of a file, and therefore know with confidence what information should go onto each numbered field. This is particularly true, of course, of VOC and dictionary records, which have a format common to all UniVerse accounts, applications, and systems.

However, such an approach is clearly unsuitable to an end-user, and would never be incorporated as a permanent part of a live system. The editor provides no help, no control, and no validation. For this reason, data entry under UniVerse is almost always done under the control of UniVerse Basic programs, which can offer users meaningful prompts, help messages, type and data validation, security control, and so forth. Sometimes such programs are coded by hand. Others consist of unique UniVerse Basic programs generated by 'screen generators' or 'fourth generation languages' (4GL's) working from screen specifications created by analysts or even end users.

A variation on this theme is the 'screen interpreter'. This is a UniVerse Basic program designed to handle all the common functions required for data entry and modification. Instead of taking a screen specification and generating a UniVerse Basic program from it, it uses it to control the prompts it displays, and validation it applies, at run time, and actually does the data entry itself.

The pros and cons of these various methods are really outside the scope of this course. I mention them because UniVerse provides its own, rather basic, screen interpreter. It is called REVISE, and it uses the dictonary of a file as a screen specification: because the dictionary contains much of the information it requires: the names of the fields, user friendy labels for them (column headings), display widths and so on.

Truth be told, though, REVISE is not great. It's interface is extremely clunky, and it is still too awkward for most users, while offering few advantages to the developer over the naked editor.

Having said that, it is sometimes a convenient way of creating a quick and dirtry makeshift data entry screen. It is also used to edit menu records, which contain many multivalued fields and are therefore rather tiresome to handle using ED. Once you've tried it, you'll need to decide on its suitability for any particular purpose, but almost any tool is sometimes useful.

To illustrate the REVISE command, we shall need a data file. If you wish to follow the examples which follow, create a dynamic file called CUSTOMERS with the dictionary below (if you are unsure how to do this, consult the earlier sections of this guide on Universe Files, Dictionaries and The Editor: ED before continuing).

Name

|

@ID

|

NAME

|

CONTACTS

Type/Desc

|

D Customer Code

|

D Customer Name

|

D Contact Names

Field

|

0

|

1

|

2

Conversion

|

(none)

|

(none)

|

(none)

Heading

|

Cus. Code

|

Cus. Name

|

Contacts

Formats

|

10L

|

30T

|

30T

Single/Multivalued

|

S

|

S

|

M

A sample REVISE session

The simplest way to invoke REVISE is simply to type REVISE filename. Try it:

>REVISE CUSTOMERS

CUSTOMERS REVISE.1 Mon Aug 16 13:44:29 1999

Cus. Code=

The prompt here, Cus. Code, is taken from the 'column heading' (line 4) of your @ID dictionary record. REVISE is asking for the key of the record you wish to edit or create. If the key you entered existed, the corresponding record would be displayed on the screen for you to edit: you will see what this display looks like a little later. For now, the file is empty, so any key is going to be new. When you enter a new key, REVISE prompts you field by field for the information it needs to create the record.

Cus. Code= GSL
New Record
Cus. Name=

Again, this prompt is taken from line 4 of a dictionary record: this time line 4 of the NAME field definition. Simply enter a value and hit ENTER:

Cus. Name= Grommet Subframes Limited
CUSTOMERS -Screen 2-CONTACTS Mon Aug 16 13:48:46 1999

@ID==> GSL
No. CONTACTS......................
1
Contacts=

You may recall that the CONTACTS field was defined as multivalued, to allow more than one contact name to be recorded against each company. REVISE handles multivalued fields by clearing the screen and then prompting you for values one by one. When you do not wish to enter any more values, you just press ENTER:

Contacts= Hugo Grommet (MD)
Contacts= Ashleigh Plumbstone (FD)
Contacts= (Press RETURN)

CUSTOMERS -Screen 2-CONTACTS Mon Aug 16 13:56:26 1999

@ID==> GSL
No. CONTACTS......................
1 Hugo Grommet (MD)
2 Ashleigh Plumbstone (FD)
3

Change which line item=

Once you have entered as many values as you wish, REVISE lists them for you to check, and to modify if necessary. Let us assume that you need to modify the second contact, as his name is actually spelt 'Ashley'. Enter 2:

Change which line item= 2

CUSTOMERS -Screen 2-CONTACTS Mon Aug 16 13:58:05 1999

@ID==>>GSL Line==>> 2
3 CONTACTS Ashleigh Plumbstone (FD)
Contacts= Ashley Plumbstone (FD)
CUSTOMERS -Screen 2-CONTACTS Mon Aug 16 13:59:50 1999

@ID==> GSL
No. CONTACTS......................
1 Hugo Grommet (MD)
2 Ashley Plumbstone (FD)
3

Change which line item=

As you can see, the new contact name is now in the list of values: but only because you retyped it in its entirety. Is there a quicker way to correct small mistakes? Say, this time, you must correct the second contact because there should be no 'b' in his surname. Once again, you begin by selecting the second line to edit.

Change which line item= 2
CUSTOMERS -Screen 2-CONTACTS Mon Aug 16 14:02:46 1999

@ID==>>GSL Line==>> 2
3 CONTACTS Ashley Plumbstone (FD)
Contacts=

At this point, you could retype the entire name, ommitting the 'b' from the surname by way of correction. However, there is an easier way. REVISE allows you to use the C or 'change' command from its cousin ED. To remove the 'b', you therefore need only enter:

Contacts= C/b//

CUSTOMERS -Screen 2-CONTACTS Mon Aug 16 14:03:32 1999

@ID==> GSL
No. CONTACTS......................
1 Hugo Grommet (MD)
2 Ashley Plumstone (FD)
3

Change which line item=

Once again, the corrected list of values is displayed for your approval. Let us now assume there are no further errors. Simply press ENTER to complete your entry of the CONTACTS:

Change which line item= (Press ENTER)

CUSTOMERS -Screen 1-FIRST SCREEN Mon Aug 16 14:04:15 1999

1 @ID GSL
2 NAME Grommet Subframes Limited

S1 == FIRST SCREEN
S2 == CONTACTS

CHANGE=

You have now finished enter your CUSTOMERS record, and you now have the chance to modify any of the fields you have entered. This, incidentally, is the display you would have seen if, when you first entered GSL at the Cus. Code prompt, it had been an existing record.

Notice, incidentally, how this screen is using the actual underlying field names to label the values in the display, rather than the column headings from line 4 of the dictionary records it was using earlier: such as @ID instead of Cus. Code. It is difficult to account for this rather bizzare inconsistency, and if you plan to allow you eventual users to use REVISE to enter and modify records, you should try and stick to friendly and meaningful field names (but of course, you were going to do that anyway, weren't you?). Even so, it is difficult to avoid the most arcane of them all: @ID, unless you set up a second D type dictionary record for field 0, which is something I hate doing.

At this prompt, you could enter a 2 to change the customer's name, or (interestingly enough) a 1 to change its key. Changing the key of a new record has no unusual implications: REVISE will simply file the new record under its new key, and as it never existing under its old, this is straightforward. However, if you use REVISE to modify an existing record, REVISE will quite happily let you do so. This has the effect of deleting the original record and creating a new one under your new key: logical enough, but a somewhat drastic implementation to be buried under what looks like a simple field change.

You could also enter S1 or S2. They are both labelled: and as you can see from those labels, S2 will take you back to the CONTACTS list for further additions or modifications. S1 will take you to the 'first screen'. But hang on: aren't you at the first screen? Yes. And would you see this prompt anywhere except the first screen? No. So what does S1 do? Try it.

CHANGE= S1
CHANGE=

That's it. Enter S1 and it will simply redisplay the prompt: and keep redisplaying it until you enter something other than S1. Stranger than fiction.

Anyway, by now I am assuming you have recorded more than you ever wanted to know about Grommet Subframes Limited, so simply press ENTER to indicate that you do not wish to change anything further:

CHANGE= (Press ENTER)

CUSTOMERS REVISE.1 Mon Aug 16 14:07:49 1999

Cus. Code=

You are finally returned to the very first revise screen you saw after entering the original REVISE command. Here, you can enter further keys to edit or create, or you can just press ENTER to exit.

Cus. Code= (Press ENTER)
>

?, TOP and ^

REVISE has a few special instructions you can use while you are editing. The most important are ?, TOP and ^.

? is a request for help. It displays messages of varying degrees of helpfulness and consistent terseness.

^ is supposed to resemble an 'up arrow', which is does a bit, once you know. It returns you to the previous prompt, in case you have made a mistake during entry you wish to correct immediately.

TOP returns you right to the 'top' of your record: effectively 'quitting' the record (like Q in ED). Why it couldn't have been called QUIT I am not sure. Be aware also that TOP, unlike ED's Q, does not warn you if you are about to abandon changes without filing them.

@REVISE and @ phrases

So where does revise get the list of fields to prompt for? It follows the following strategy:

1. If there is an @REVISE (or @ENTRO) phrase on the dictionary, it will derive its list of fields to edit from that. This is a link back to the good old days when REVISE was called ENTRO: UniVerse seems to have gone to some lengths to provide versions of all command names with a 'V' in them (or should I have said 'Versions'?). Try ENTRO, it still works.

2. Failing an @REVISE/@ENTRO, it will take use an @ entry (see Phrases).

3. Failing both of these, it will automatically create an @ENTRO phrase by listing all the D types in the dictionary. If more than one D type refers to the same field number, it will choose the first one it finds (not by alphabetical order: effectively at random). This is another good reason for only having one D type per physical field. You could, of course, edit the @ENTRO phrase to correct the choice of field names if you would prefer others, but why set up situations like this which increase your workload?

By editing the @ENTRO phrase, you can persuade REVISE to edit only a subset of the fields. You can also add keywords (like VERIFY and VERIFIELD) which add some useful internal and external validation: but this level of detail is outside the scope of this course. As ever, if your appetite is wetted, consult the UniVerse documentation for more information.

In summary, REVISE is a sometimes useful but rather clunky and at times rather odd program. Personally, I would never stick it in front of a user, though I find it occassionally useful as a developer's utility. It's a nice idea, but I can't help feeling it could have been written better. At the end of the day, it's your call.

Computers: Universe: Universe Files

It is probably worth recapping on a few points made when discussing UniVerse's general structure (see The UniVerse Paradigm above):

Recapping UniVerse Files

1. A UniVerse account is a collection of files, and a Universe file is a collection of records.

2. Each record in a UniVerse file is simply a string of ASCII characters, divided into fields, values, and subvalues by field marks (character 254), value marks (character 253) and subvalue marks (character 252) respectively.

3. Each record has a unique 'key', a string of characters which is associated with the record, and can be used to access it directly without reading through every record in the file.

4. Everything in UniVerse is stored in files: each command in the command lanuage is a record in the special VOC file, and each Universe Basic program is a record in a programs file (often called BP for 'Basic Programs').

5. Most files give specific meanings to each field number in their records: for instance, a CUSTOMERS file may use the first field of each record to store the company name, the second field of each record to store the company phone number, and so on. However, not all files work like this; program files, for instance, simply have one line of UniVerse Basic code on each field: not only don't such records give no positional meaning to their fields, they probably wont even have the same number of fields in each record.

File types

So much, then, is common to all UniVerse files: and for most purposes, UniVerse commands and UniVerse Basic statements can operate in the same way on any file, regardless of its contents.

However, UniVerse files can be further divided into three types. This differenciation is chiefly for performance reasons: the different physical implementations of the three file types makes them suitable to do different jobs efficiently.

The three types are 'directory' files, 'static' files, and 'dynamic' files.

The command to create a file is:

CREATE.FILE filename filetype otherparameters

Convention suggests that the filename should be uppercase, and words divided using dots, as in CUSTOMER.INVOICES.

The filetype is a number, and for historical reasons the range of possible numbers is a little odd. 1 and 19 produce the two slightly different forms of directory file, 2 through 18 exclusively produce the 17 possible types of static file, and 30 produces a dynamic file.

The otherparameters depend on the filetype selected, and are examined in more detail below.

Computers: Universe: Directory Files

To create a directory file, the command is:

CREATE.FILE filename 1 or
CREATE.FILE filename 19

Directory files gain their name from the fact that they are implemented as directories under UNIX: each record in the directory file being a simple ASCII file under UNIX.

The different between type 1 and type 19 directory files is subtle. Type 1 files break up long record keys into sections not longer than 14 characters, and created a set of nested directories to store the entire name. This is a little difficult to explain except by example:

If you save a record called THISISAVERYLONGNAME in a type 1 file called TYPE1, the path to the UNIX file created will run .../TYPE1/THISISAVERYLON/GNAME. Thus the file will be called GNAME, and it will be the only file in a directory called THISISAVERYLON. This mechanism is a historical throwback to operating systems such as MSDOS which cannot handle long file and directory names.

In addition, keys to records in type 1 files are limited to 41 characters in length. A key of 123456789-123456789-123456789-123456789-12 would be automatically truncated to 123456789-123456789-123456789-123456789-1, and saved as ...TYPE1/123456789-1234/56789-12345678/9-123456789-1.

Unless, therefore, you have some reason to make your file structure, when viewed from UNIX, easily transportable to MSDOS, use type 19 files, which operate far more straightforwardly. The same record in a type 19 file is saved with a UNIX pathname of ...TYPE19/THISISAVERYLONGFILENAME.

Do not be confused by this into thinking that the key of a record in a type 1 file changes from the point of view in UniVerse: type 1 and type 19 files are indistinguishable from UniVerses point of view, and any UniVerse command or program would read the key THISISALONGFILENAME from either a type 1 or a type 19 file. It is only when you look at the storage under UNIX that the difference becomes apparent.

Directory files have a number of uses:

1. Only type 1 and type 19 files make their records and individually readable to UNIX. They are therefore sometimes used to communicate with UNIX programs.

2. The UniVerse Basic compiler will only compile records in a type 1 or type 19 file. All source code, therefore, has to be stored in such files.

3. There are a few other UniVerse commands which will work only with type 1 or type 19 files, but these are much less important than the basic compiler.

4. UniVerse Basic provides a group of statements for 'sequential file I/O', in which the fields of records are read or written in sequence. These only work on records in type 1 or type 19 files.

As can be seen, the uses of directory files are very specific, and unless you have a specific reason to use a directory file, do not create one. Above all, do not use them to contain randomly accessed application data (such as customer or invoice records), as they are extremely inefficient in this role.

Computers: Universe: Dynamic Files

To create a directory file, the command is:

CREATE.FILE filename 30 or
CREATE.FILE filename DYNAMIC

(Both these commands have the same effect: the creation of a dynamic file.)

If the last section on static files convinced you that they were likely to prove a pain to set up and maintain well, then you are not alone. For many years, static hashed files were the only kind available with PICK systems, but in the late eighties Prime added a new file type called 'dynamic' files to Prime INFORMATION. VMark adopted these into UniVerse.

Dynamic files are intended to perform the same tasks as static files. Like static files, they are divided into groups, and like static files, they 'hash' records into these groups according to their keys. The vital difference is that as you add data to dynamic files, they increase their own modulo automatically: and as you remove it, they reduce it. Hence 'dynamic'.

They have a wide range of parameters (wider than static files) which you can specify at creation time, or modify after creation, and which allow you to fine tune their performance: but unlike static files (which must be configured well in order to perform), dynamic files perform reasonably well with all of these parameters set to their defaults. When you become involved in the intricate performance tuning of a system which uses dynamic files, you can find the information you'll need in the UniVerse documentation, but it is not necessary to provide it in an introductory course like this one.

If this is all true, why are static files still in use at all?

1. At many sites, they aren't.
2. Dynamic files have a slightly higher write overhead: the processing which normally takes place during a static file RESIZE is divided amongst thousands on individuals record writes to dynamic files.
3. A well sized static file will slightly outperform a dynamic file. If your file is extremely stable (and therefore can be well-sized once and left like that), or your resizing process extremely efficient, you may benefit from this.
4. Basic on some very old anecdotes, some users seem to fear that dynamic files are prone to corruption. While files do sometimes corrupt, I have found dynamic files no more likely to do so that static ones.

My own advice, in short, is that unless you have a good reason not to, use dynamic files.

Computers: Universe: Static Files

The command to create a static file is:

CREATE.FILE filename type modulo separation

The type must be between 2 and 18 if the file is to be a static file. Which of these you choose, and what the modulo and separation parameters do takes a little explanation.

How static files work

A static file is designed to hold application records: like customer records in a CUSTOMERS file. It's aims are to ensure that (a) the file structure is not so complicated that each record takes a long time to add to the file, but (b) the file structure allows records to be found quickly when they must be read. These aims are somewhat conflicting: the more clever your record indexing system (to make records easy to find), the longer it takes to add a record and update the indexing.

Static files are a reasonable compromise between these conflicting aims. They can be most easily explained by an analogy.

Imagine a post room. Every day they receive letters: each letter received is like a record being added to a file. There job is to somehow store them in such a way as to make them easy to find, so the postroom is like the file itself.

Most postrooms solve the problem by screwing 'pigeon holes' to the wall: a series of wooden boxes with a label on each one.

UniVerse files do the same. Instead of 'pigeon holes' they have 'groups'. The modulo is simply the number of groups they have. The separation is the number of 512 byte 'disk frames' are allocated to each group: so for instance, if you create a file with a separation of 4, each group can hold 2K.

Returning to our postroom: as each letter arrives, it is put in the pigeon hole corresponding to the address it is being sent to. Gradually, the 'Wynberg' pigeon hole fills up with letters to various addresses in Wynberg, the 'Constantia' pigeon hole fills up with letters to Constantia, and so on.

So far, so good. If you know the address a letter was sent to, you don't need to search through every letter in the post room to find it: you can just search through the letters in the appropriate pigeon hole.

Again, this is exactly how UniVerse accesses static files. It Knows the 'key' (equivalent to the address) of the record it is looking for, and it knows which group that key should be in. It then looks through all the records in that group until it finds the one it wants. Note that this means that there is no index giving the precise location of each individual record, so there is no index to be updated every time a record is written.

Again back in the post room: a problem arises when you have received so many letters for 'Wynberg' that no more will fit in that particular pigeon hole. You put a bucket on the floor, stick a 'Wynberg' label on it, and start putting new letters to Wynberg in the bucket. This works, but by the time you've got three or four 'Wynberg' buckets, it's going to take a long time whenever you want to find a letter to Wynberg.

The same thing happens as you add records to a static file. After a while, some of the groups accumulate more records than they can hold. As explained above, the capacity of each group is determined by the separation, measured in 512 byte 'disk frames'. A static file with a separation of 4 can therefore store 2K in each group, and 2K of disk space is reserved for each group when the file is created. If more than 2K of records were added to a group, the group would 'overflow', grabbing an extra disk frame to store the excess. Disk frames used in this way are called 'overflow frames', and groups can gradually build up long chains of overflow frames. The more a group overflows, the longer it takes to find individual records in the group.

The man running the postroom could try and solve his problem in one of three ways:

1. He could make each pigeon hole bigger. This might help a bit, because it gets the letters out of the buckets scattered around the floor and up into the pigeon holes, where they are all in the same place and quicker to get at.

The equivalent under UniVerse would be to increase the file's separation, thus making the groups bigger. This removes many of the overflow frames, which may be scattered around the disk and thus particularly slow to search.

The problem with this solution is that it doesn't actually reduce the number of letters in each pigeon hole. There many still be so many letters in the "Wynberg" pigeon hole that it takes a long time to find one.

2. He could make more pigeon holes: perhaps dividing each current pigeon hole into two by having pigeon holes for "North Wynberg" and "South Wynberg", "North Edgemead" and "South Edgement" and so on. The basic system of deciding which pigeon hole each letter goes in hasn't changed: it's still based on suburb, but because there are more pigeon holes, the average number of letters in each pigeon hole will go down, and the amount of overflow will probably fall.

The equivalent under UniVerse would be to incrase the file's modulo, thus making more groups available. This reduces the average number of records in each group, and thus, probably, the overflow.

This is usually pretty effective, and increasing file modulos is the most common solution to overflow. However, it doesn't always solve the problem. Imagine that almost all of the letters in the old "Wynberg" pigeon hole ended up in the new North Wynberg pigeon hole. The new North Wynberg pigeon hole would then still be overflowed, and the new South Wynberg pigeon hole would be nearly empty. The problem here is that the letters are not being evenly distributed between the pigeon holes, so increasing the number of pigeon holes doesn't help.

3. If faced with a bad distribution of letters, he could decide to replace the labels on the pigeon holes. For instance, instead of having 17 pigeon holes each with the name of a suburb, he might decide to label the pigeon holes with the numbers 1 to 17. All letters to house number 1, as in '1 High Street', would go into pigeon hole 1, all those to 2, as in '2 Villa Crescent', would go into pigeon hole 2, and so on. Letters to house number 18 would go into pigeon hole 1. In this way, he can completely change the distribution of the letters between the pigeon holes, and this new scheme will probably spread them more evenly.

The equivalent under UniVerse is to try another type. As explained above, types 2 through 18 are all static files. The difference is that they each use a different system for deciding which group each record should go in. If the records in a static file are unevenly spread between the groups, try changing the type of the file.

Choosing a good separation

The UniVerse technical documentation makes two recommendations: (a) that your separation should be a power of 2, so that the boundaries of each group are more likely to coincide with the boundaries UNIX uses to organise its disk, which also tend to be in powers of 2 multiplied by 512 bytes, and (b) that your separation should not be over 16, as the performance of big groups tends to degrade.

This gives a range of possible values of 2, 4, 8 or 16. The consultants Fitzgerald and Long, who specialise in PICK file maintenance, recommend 4 as being optimum for almost all files, and I tend to agree with them. A separation of 2 gives you group capacities of only 1K, and your records would have to be very small and evenly spread not to overflow such small groups. A separation of 8 or 16 allows 4K or 8K into each group respectively: and it will clearly take longer to read 4K or 8K to find a record than 2K.

Choosing a good modulus

To decide on your modulus, you must calculate how much data the file is likely to store. If the file is completely new, this may be difficult, and you'll just need to make the best estimate you can. If it is already in use, you can count the number of records it contains and their average size, and multiply the two figures together.

If you stick generally to a separation of 4, as I recommend above, then in principle each group can store 2K without overflowing. You could, therefore, divide the total amount of data you plan to store by 2K in order to find the number of groups, ie. the modulo, you need.

The problem with this is that it assumes that the records will be spread exactly evenly: because if the average amount of data in each group is 2K, then if some groups store less than 2K, others must store more and must therefore be overflowed. Also, it makes no allowance for growth: and many files either fluctuate in size or get gradually bigger. For both these reasons, it's better to use a higher number than this formula would suggest.

Experience suggests that a reasonable rule of thumb is to choose a modulo twice as big as you need in theory. So instead of dividing the amount of data by 2K to get the modulus, divide by 1K.

One last point is that your modulo should be a prime number. This is because of the way in which the records are distributed between the groups. The key of each record is turned into a usually huge arbitrary number by a UniVerse 'hashing algorithm'. There are 17 different hashing algorithms, corresponding to types 2 to 18 discussed below. This 'hashing number' is then divided by the modulo, and the remainder determines which group the record should be stored in. The groups are numbered from 0. Thus if I add customer IBM to my modulo 7 CUSTOMERS file, UniVerse might come up with a hashing number of 74. The remainder when this is divided by the modulo is 4, which means the record goes into group 4. If the modulo is not a prime number, this system tends to favour certain groups at the expense of others because of a mathematical effect known as 'factorising' which it is thankfully not necessary to understand. Just stick to prime numbers. The UniVerse command PRIME n will display the nearest prime numbers above and below n, so you don't need to work them out.

Choosing a good type

The 17 possible types, numbered from 2 to 18, each relate to a different mathematical formula known as a hashing algorithm. This algorithm takes your record key and turns it into a hashing number. The hashing number is then divided by the modulo, and the remainder determines which group the record will go into.

What you are looking for, therefore, is a type which will give you the widest possible range of hashing numbers for the keys in your particular file. The more variation there is in the hashing numbers produced, the more evenly your records will be distributed between the groups.

How do you choose it? Well, if you just type CREATE.FILE TEST without entering a type, you will be prompted to enter a type. If you enter a question mark, you will get the following advice:

...
  2      Hashed.  Keys end with numbers.
  3      Hashed.  Keys end mainly with numbers.
  4      Hashed.  Keys end with letters.
  5      Hashed.  Keys end with full range of ASCII characters.
  6      Hashed.  Keys begin with numbers.
  7      Hashed.  Keys begin mainly with numbers.
  8      Hashed.  Keys begin with letters.
  9      Hashed.  Keys begin with full range of ASCII characters.
 10      Hashed.  Keys are numbers.
 11      Hashed.  Keys are mainly numbers.
 12      Hashed.  Keys are letters.
 13      Hashed.  Keys are full range of ASCII characters.
 14      Hashed.  Entire keys are numbers.
 15      Hashed.  Entire keys are mainly numbers.
 16      Hashed.  Entire keys are letters.
 17      Hashed.  Entire keys are full range of ASCII characters.
 18      Hashed.  Entire keys are of arbitrary form.
...

So it should be simple, shouldn't it? If your keys begin with letters, use type 8. There is even a UniVerse command called HASH.HELP which does this work for you. Enter HASH.HELP VOC and it will examine the VOC records and analyse them cleverly according to the rules above. It will then display something like:

File VOC  Type= 3  Modulo= 347  Sep= 4      02:29:23pm  28 Jun 1999  PAGE    1

Of the 8826 total keys in this file:

      0  keys were wholly numeric (digits 0 thru 9)
         (Use File Type 2, 6, 10 or 14 for wholly numeric keys)

      9  keys were numeric with separators (as reproduced below)
         0123456789#$%&*+-./:;_
         (Use File Type 3, 7, 11 or 15 for numeric keys with separators)

   8789  keys were from the 64-character ASCII set reproduced below
         !"#$%&'()*+,-./0123456789:;<=>?@ABCDEFGHIJKLMNOPQRSTUVWXYZ[\]^_`
         (Use File Type 4, 8, 12 or 16 for 64-character ASCII keys)

     28  keys were from the 256-character ASCII set
         (Use File Type 5, 9, 13 or 17 for 256-character ASCII keys)

The keys in this file are more unique in their entirety.
The smallest modulo you should consider for this file is 4441.
The smallest separation you should consider for this file is 4.
The best type to choose for this file is probably type 18.

The only tiny problem with all this is that it is baloney. Type 18, for example, is most definitely not the best type for the VOC file analysed above, and HASH.HELP has an uncanny knack of finding not only the wrong type, but more often than chance would predict, the worst type for your files.

The truth is that there is no formula, rule of thumb, gift of experience, or system of demonic divination which will tell you the best type. The only way to find the best type for a static file is to try all 17 and see which one gives you the most even spread of records. If you've only just created your file, you wont be able to analyse the best type for it until its got some records in it. Just give it type 18 till then: there's one chance in 17 it's the best, and it's quicker than the 1 in 17 chance you get from trying to base your decision on how many letters there are in the key.

Maintaining your file

Universe provides a number of commands to allow you to analyse and maintain your file once you've created it.:

RESIZE filename newtype newmodulo newseparation

RESIZE allows you to change the type, modulo, or separation of your static file. If there are any of these parameters you wish to leave unaltered, you can use a * in their place. For instance, RESIZE MYFILE * 107 * changes the modulo of MYFILE to 107 while leaving the type and separation unchanged.

You may occassionally wish to run a RESIZE using the parameters * * * (ie. leaving the type, modulo and separation as they are). Though this seems odd at first sight, it can be useful as during a resize the UniVerse file is 'compacted', and pockets of unused space left in groups by the addition and deletion of records are reclaimed, releasing disk space and reducing overflow.

In fact, I don't recommend the use of RESIZE. The chief problem is that if a RESIZE is interrupted for any reason (such as, say, a power failiure), it corrupts the file it is working on. The following commands achieve the same affect (including the reclaimation of deleted space) but without this risk:

CREATE.FILE NEWFILE 3 107 4
(where 3, 107 and 4 are the new parameters required)
COPY FROM MYFILE TO NEWFILE ALL
(which copies all the records from MYFILE to NEWFILE
DELETE.FILE MYFILE
(which deletes the original MYFILE)
CNAME NEWFILE TO MYFILE
(changes the name of NEWFILE to MYFILE

HASH.AID filename testtype testmodulo testseparation

HASH.AID reports on the various statistics a file would have if it were given the testtype, testmodulo, and testseparation. To test the existing value of any of these parameters, use * in their place. It follows from this that you can examine a file's current statistics using a command like HASH.AID VOC * * *. This produces a display like this:

File name                               = VOC
File type, modulo, and separation       = 3, 347, 4
Number of records                       = 8826
Number of physical bytes                = 9461760
Number of data bytes                    = 9116736

Average number of records per group     = 25.4352
Minimum number of bytes per group       = 888
Maximum number of bytes per group       = 7897956
Average number of bytes per group       = 26273.0144
Minimum number of records in a group    = 7
Maximum number of records in a group    = 83

Average number of bytes per record      = 1032.9409
Minimum number of bytes in a record     = 20
Maximum number of bytes in a record     = 3958336

Average number of fields per record     = 27.3937
Minimum number of fields per record     = 1
Maximum number of fields per record     = 89454

Groups  25%    50%    75%   100%   125%   150%   175%   200% full
          0      2     37    106     93     58     24     27

In fact, UniVerse provides a bewildering array of other commands for analysing static files, including ACCOUNT.FILE.STATS, FILE.STAT, GROUP.STAT, GROUP.STAT.DETAIL, HASH.TEST, HASH.TEST.DETAIL. Once you feel you have an understanding of types, modulos, and separations, consult the UniVerse documentation about these. In this documentation, you will also find advice on HASH.HELP and HASH.HELP.DETAIL: Ignore it.

Computers: Universe: The Command Prompt

If you have not yet created a Universe account, do: see Universe and UNIX above.

If you have, cd to the directory housing the account, and start Universe.

The command to start Universe account is uv. The UniVerse bin directory contains this executable: if it is not on your path, you will have to enter the full path: it will be something like /universe/bin/uv.

This will bring you to the Universe prompt:

>

At this prompt, you can enter commands. The following commands are worth learning first:

QUIT

Before you learn anything else, learn how to get back to UNIX from UniVerse: simply enter QUIT. Some people find themselves logged off their server on entering QUIT, but this is not because the command itself logs you off. It only happens where a friendly system administrator has devised a command file which first invokes UniVerse and then logs out. It means that while you are in UniVerse, the UNIX command file is still running: and as soon as you return to UNIX it completes by logging you off.

LO

Unless you are using a system which logs you out when you type QUIT (see above), QUIT will only return you to UNIX. If you plan to log off the system entirely, you can do so directly from UniVerse by entering LO.

SH

This command has already been mentioned (see UniVerse and Unix above). It merely suspends UniVerse and opens a UNIX shell. It is bad practise to log out of this shell, as it doesn't give UniVerse a chance to 'shut down' tidily (releasing locks, clearing file I/O buffers and so on): always exit back to UniVerse first. Within the shell, you can carry out most UNIX functions, though you should not recursively start UniVerse again, and you should bear in mind that even if you use cd to move to a different directory, on leaving the shell you will be returned to your original UNIX directory and your original UniVerse account.

LOGTO

LOGTO takes the place of UNIX's cd command in that it moves you from one UniVerse account to another, in much the way that cd moves you from one UNIX directory to another.

However, it works slightly differently in that it doesn't accept pathnames to indicate your destination: the syntax is simply LOGTO accountname. This is because, as was explained during the description of UniVerse's heirarchical structure (see The UniVerse Paradigm above), UniVerse accounts are not recursive: that is to say, as far as UniVerse is concerned, no account contains another account. UniVerse keeps a single central list of all the accounts on a system, and when you specify the account name you wish to go to, it finds the UNIX path from this list. Even if one UniVerse account has been created in a subdirectory of another (note: not good practice), UniVerse does not recognise any relationship between them, merely two accounts at different paths.

Here lies one of the examples of something I mentioned earlier: the risks of applying UNIX commands to UniVerse structures (see UniVerse and UNIX above). If you move a directory containing a UniVerse account using the UNIX mv command, all may seem well. If you cd to the new pathname and invoke UniVerse, it will work. However, if you try to LOGTO the account you moved from UniVerse, the command will fail. This is because UNIX is not aware of UniVerse's internal controls, and will not update it's internal list of account locations. This, you must do yourself using the UNIX Administrator's menu, which is unfortunately outside the scope of this document. Refer to the UniVerse documentation for more information on this point.

SET.TERM.TYPE

Each different kind of dumb terminal has it's own instruction set for doing things like displaying text at particular screen locations, or displaying text in bold, and so on. In order to cope with these, UniVerse must know which kind of terminal you are using. If, as is now increasingly likely, you are using a PC based terminal emulator, it must know which kind of terminal it is emulating.

To set the terminal type, you can enter SET.TERM.TYPE, and enter a ? when asked for your terminal type. UniVerse will then display a list of those it supports. Select your terminal from this list.

It would be a good idea to do this before trying any of the examples in the remainder of this course: they all assume that your terminal type has been set up correctly. This terminal type definition lasts until you leave UniVerse: when you return to UniVerse you will have to use this command again, though there are ways to automate 'start up' commands of this kind, as you will learn later.

HELP

UniVerse boasts an extremely comprehensive on-line help system, similar to the UNIX man facility. To get information about a command, enter HELP commandname. For instance, you could enter HELP LOGTO to read about the LOGTO command, or even the rather desperate sounding HELP HELP to learn about the help system itself. This on-line manual also covers the statements in the UniVerse Basic programming language: a point we shall return to when the language is discussed later.

DISPLAY

To display something on the screen, enter the command DISPLAY string, as in DISPLAY Hello Mum!. This a useful enough command, but not tremendously important: I explain it because I will be asking you to enter it later as part of some worked examples on other subjects.

Computers: Universe: The Command Stack

UniVerse keeps a 'history' of all the commands you have entered at the UniVerse command prompt. To demonstrate it, it is helpful to first enter a few commands. Try the following:

DISPLAY This is my first command
DISPLAY This is my second command
DISPLAY This is my third command

(The DISPLAY command is explained above: see The Command Prompt above.)

To see you command history, enter .L, which will display a list something like this:

03 DISPLAY This is my first command
02 DISPLAY This is my second command
01 DISPLAY This is my third command

This is called your 'command stack', and all the commands to manipulate it, like the ,L command above, begin with a dot.

You can repeat your last command by entering .X, or indeed any command by entering .Xn, where n is the commands position in the stack, the most recent command always being 1. For instance, to repeat the command DISPLAY This is my second command, enter .X2. Try it.

If you now enter .L again, you will see:

04 DISPLAY This is my first command
03 DISPLAY This is my second command
02 DISPLAY This is my third command
01 DISPLAY This is my second command

Notice that when you repeated the second command, it became the most recent command, and so appeared once more at position 1 in the stack. This is how the stack generally behaves: as you enter new commands, the older commands are each gradually shuffled down the command stack. Only when you enter .X does it not generate a new entry in the command stack, because you are merely repeating the last command, so UniVerse decides to ignore it.

Take care. After a while you will find yourself 'remembering' where the commands will be and able to enter .X3 to reexecute the command you issued three commands ago, but to begin with always enter .L to list the commands before reexecuting any but your last command: many an overconfident developer has deleted the source of the program he is working on, or cleared a file of carefully loaded data, by guessing the position of the command he wanted in the stack incorrectly.

You can delete the most recent entry in the stack by entering .D, or indeed delete any entry by entering ,Dn where n is the entry's number. Try entering .D3 to delete entry three, and then .L to redisplay the stack:

03 DISPLAY This is my first command
02 DISPLAY This is my third command
01 DISPLAY This is my second command

To 'recall' an older command to the head of the stack, enter .Rn, where n is again the number of the stack entry to recall. Try recalling entry 2 with .R2, and relisting the stack with .L:

03 DISPLAY This is my first command
02 DISPLAY This is my third command
01 DISPLAY This is my second command
02 DISPLAY This is my third command

Like .X, .R brings an old command to the top of the stack: but it doesn't run it again. You would most often do this because you wished to change the command before running it again. To change the most recent command in the stack, enter .C/oldstring/newstring. For instance, you could change the word 'third' to '3rd' by entering .C/third/3rd. Try it, and redisplay the stack with .L:

03 DISPLAY This is my first command
02 DISPLAY This is my third command
01 DISPLAY This is my second command
02 DISPLAY This is my 3rd command

In principle, you could change any entry by using .Cn in place of .C to indicate it's number, but in practice its safer to use .Rn first to recall the entry, and then .C.

If the command you wish to change contains the '/' character, then you can use a different delimiter in your change command: the command .C!third!3rd would have had exactly the same effect as the one you used above. In fact, you can use any of the following characters: !@#$%&*/\:=+-?(){}[]`'.,|, so you can generally find one which doesn't appear in your command.

If the same string appears more than once in your command, and you wish to change all the occurences in one go, append /G: the 'G' standing for 'global'. For instance, type .C/m/!/g and then .L:

03 DISPLAY This is my first command
02 DISPLAY This is my third command
01 DISPLAY This is my second command
02 DISPLAY This is !y 3rd co!!and

To add something to the end of a command, you can use .A extrabit (or .An extrabit to add something to command n in the stack); and finally, for UNIX programmers having trouble remembering to enter commands and filenames in upper case, you can use .U (or .Un) to convert an entire command to upper case.

The number of commands kept in the stack is depends on the way your copy of UniVerse has been configured, but is usually about 100. Entering .L will show you up to 20: to see more, enter .Ln where n is the number of commands you wish to see.

Computers: Universe: The Editor - ED

Enough theory: let's type. UniVerse has its own command line editor which allows you to view and change records. As everything in UniVerse takes the form of records in files (programs, commands and keywords from the UniVerse command language, field descriptions in dictionaries, and, of course, traditional data records), the editor has very wide application, allowing you to do everything from changing data to writing programs.

ED: Editing a record

To invoke the editor, the command is:

ED filename recordkey

(This, incidentally, is the form taken by many UniVerse commands, as most of them operate in various ways on records in files.)

As mentioned above (see Universe and UNIX), each UniVerse command takes the form of a record in the VOC file. As we earlier entered the command SH to invoke a Unix shell, it follows that there must be a record corresponding to this command in the VOC. To find out, enter:

ED VOC SH

You should see the following message:

4 lines long.

And the UniVerse editor's prompt:

----:

P: Displaying pages

Now enter the command P to display a 'pageful' of the record,:

0001: V
0002: /bin/sh
0003: U
0004: TICRG
----:

This record only has four fields, so no more can be displayed. However, if the record had many fields, P would only display as many as would fit on your display. By repeatedly enter P therefore, you can read your record a page at a time.

Notice the message 4 lines long which appeared when you edited this record. While the editor thinks in terms of 'lines', each line is actually a field. That is to say, the editor shows one field on each line. What you are looking at here is, in a sense, 'raw' data. Using a SQL based database like Oracle, your only access to data in columns in via the SQL language, and you cannot change the values in columns in ways which are inconsistent with the column definitions. UniVerse, on the other hand, allows you to look at and even change the raw data, not constrained by the field definitions, or, indeed, anything.

Q: Quitting a record

Depending on the nature of the change, changing this record would probably have the effective of disabling the SH command, and so we shan't do it. Instead, enter the Q command to exit the record. If you had changed the record before exiting, you would see the prompt:

***** Record changed. OK to quit (Y) ?

You would then have to enter a Y before you were returned to the UniVerse prompt.

Creating a new record

When back at the UniVerse prompt, enter the command:

>ED VOC FLUFFY

You will be amazed to discover that there is no UniVerse FLUFFY command or keyword, so there is no record on the VOC file corresponding to this key. Instead you will see:

New Record.

----:

I: Inserting Lines

The command to put the editor into 'insert mode' is I. Enter it and you will see:

0001=

This prompt is telling you that whatever you type in will become line 1 (and thus field 1) of the new record 'FLUFFY'. In the case of VOC records, every record represents a command or other keyword in the UniVerse command language, and field 1 of each record determines whether the keyword in question is a command, a filename, a command parameter, or has some other meaning. We shall set up a 'paragraph' (a little like a Unix command script) to be run whenever someone enters the command 'FLUFFY', so enter PA. Your record will now look like this:

0001= PA
0002=

You are now being invited to enter a value for the second field of the record FLUFFY. Each line after the first in a UniVerse paragraph is a command, so try the following:

0001= PA
0002= DISPLAY You have just entered the command 'FLUFFY'.
0003= DISPLAY This is not a terribly useful command.
0004= DISPLAY All it does is display this message.
0005=

(Do not be concerned if you have made any mistakes in entering these lines: we shall be looking at the commands you'll need to change things, and so correct any mistakes, below.)

To indicate that you do not wish to enter any more fields, simply hit ENTER instead of entering another field. You will be returned from the = 'input' prompt to the : 'command' prompt:

0005= (press ENTER)
----:

n, +n, -n, T and B: Moving between lines

At any given time your record will have a 'current line'. This is the line which will be changed by any commands you might enter. You can make any line current just by typing in its number. Enter 2 to make line 2 active:

----: 2
0002: DISPLAY You have just entered the command 'FLUFFY'.
----:

You can also move a certain number of lines relative to your current line by entering +n or -n where n is the number of lines you want to move. For instance:

----: +1
0003: DISPLAY This is not a terribly useful command.
----: -2
0001: PA
----:

Just hitting ENTER on its own is the equivalent of entering +1 to move to the next line:

----: (press ENTER)
0002: DISPLAY You have just entered the command 'FLUFFY'.
----:

You can jump straight to the 'top' of your record with the command T, or straight to the bottom with B, like this:

----: T
Top.
----: B
0004: DISPLAY All it does is display this message.
Bottom at line 4.
----:

A subtlety here is that the top of the record is not line 1, but line 0. This is because (a) new records and completely empty records (which UniVerse allows) don't have a line 1, and (b) by going to line 0 and using the I command, you can insert lines before line 1 of your current record.

C: Changing lines

Let us now assume that you wanted to replace the word entered with the word typed. To do this, you would use the C or 'change' command thus:

----: 2
0002: DISPLAY You have just entered the command 'FLUFFY'.
----: C/entered/typed
0002: DISPLAY You have just typed the command 'FLUFFY'.
----:

(In fact, the character you used to separate entered and typed need not be /: it could be any of the following: !"#$%&()*+,-.:=@[\]_`{|} or '. This is useful when the thing you want to change, or the thing you want to change it to, actually contains a /.)

You can also use the C command to change every occurence of one string to another by adding a /G parameter. The G stands for 'global'. For instance, to change every space to an asterisk on this line, try:

----: C/ /*/G
0002: DISPLAY*You*have*just*typed*the*command*'FLUFFY'.
----:

Our command now looks a little odd. To change it back:

----: C/*/ /G
0002: DISPLAY You have just typed the command 'FLUFFY'.
----:

To apply the same change to more than one line, simply add the number of lines you wish to change to the end of the command. For instance, to change the word DISPLAY to IGNORE on the current line and the one after it (two lines altogether), add /2:

----: C/DISPLAY/IGNORE/2
0002: IGNORE You have just typed the command 'FLUFFY'.
0003: IGNORE This is not a terribly useful command.
At line 3
----:

The editor will display any lines which are actually changed. Note the At line 3 message at the end of the change. If you change more than one line in this way, the editor will make the last line examined the current line: even if the string you wanted to change did not appear in it and the line was therefore not changed. For instance, if you had entered the command C/typed/used/2, then lines 2 and 3 would have been searched for the string typed. Only line 2 contains it, so only line 2 would have been changed, but line 3 was the last line examined, and so line 3 becomes your current line. The message is just a reminder of this.

You can even apply a 'global' change across more than one line, by adding /Gn to you command where n is the number of lines you wish to change. One of the most common used of C is to do a complete search and replace by first entering the command 1 to move to the first line, and then entering the command C/something/something else/G99999. C doesn't get upset if you try to change more lines than there are in the file: it'll just change as many lines as it can find, and leave the last line as the current line.

OOPS: Undoing changes

Changing DISPLAY to IGNORE has left our paragraph looking a little odd. To reverse (or in Windows parlance 'undo') a change, you can use the quaint command OOPS:

----: OOPS
Record restored to condition prior to command "C/DISPLAY/IGNORE/2".
0002: DISPLAY You have just typed the command 'FLUFFY'.
----:

Note that note only have the lines been put back the way they were before the C command, but even your current line has been set back to 2: where you were before you made your change.

OOPS only reverses commands which change the content of the record. For instance, if you enter C/A/B to change an 'A' to a 'B', you can reverse the change with OOPS, however: if you enter the command +2 to move your current line 2 lines down, OOPS will ignore this. Neither can OOPS reverse any changes before the last.

A: Adding to a line

While you can make almost any change to a line using C, some changes are so common that they have commands of their own. For instance, to add or 'append' something to a line, enter the command A newbit, where newbit is the bit you want to add. For instance:

0002: DISPLAY You have just typed the command 'FLUFFY'.
----: A That's silly.
0002: DISPLAY You have just typed the command 'FLUFFY'.That's silly.

Note that there is no space between the full stop at the end of the original line and the word 'That'. To append a space, you must remember to leave two spaces between the A and the newbit.

If you've made this change, OOPS it back.

B: Breaking a line

You can break a line into two using the command B endofline1, where endofline1 is the sequence of characters you want at the end of the first line. Everything after these characters is broken into a new line underneath. This sounds worse than it is: and an example is clearer:

0002: DISPLAY You have just typed the command 'FLUFFY'.
----: B typed
0002: DISPLAY You have just typed
----: +1
0003: the command 'FLUFFY'
----:

Note that while B broke the line in two, it didn't change the current line. You had to type +1 (or you could just have pressed ENTER) to move the current line down one and see the new line created.

If you haven't made this change, do, because it's handy to demonstrate the next editor command, which is:

CAT: Concatentating two lines

To join your current line to the one below it, enter the command CAT. To repair the break you inserted above, therefore:

----: 2
0002: DISPLAY You have just typed
----: CAT
0002: DISPLAY You have just typed the command 'FLUFFY'.
----:

D: Deleting lines

To delete a line, enter the command D. To delete n lines, enter the command Dn. This is simply enough: the only bewildering thing is that unlike most commands, D does not redisplay the (new) current line once it has finished. For instance, if you are only line 2 and enter the command D, line 2 disappears, and line 3 becomes the new line 2, (and line 4 the new line 3, and so on). However, the editor does not display the new line 2 to let you know where you are. To get round this, a trick is to enter the command +0, which moves your current line zero lines down (ie. not at all) and forces the redisplay of your current line:

----: 2
0002: DISPLAY You have just typed the command 'FLUFFY'.
----: D
----: +0
0002: DISPLAY This is not a terribly useful command.
----:

Try this, but then OOPS the deleted line back.

DUP: Duplicating a line

To duplicate the current line, use DUP:

----: 2
0002: DISPLAY You have just typed the command 'FLUFFY'.
----: DUP
0003: DISPLAY This is not a terribly useful command.
----:

Note that a copy of line 2 now appears on line 3, and line 3 is now the current line. Enter OOPS to reverse this.

L and F: Locating and Finding

To locate or search for something, enter L something:

----: T
Top.
----: L sef
0003: DISPLAY This is not a terribly useful command
----:

Though it may not be immediately obvious, the string sef appears in the word useful. As you see, L will find your string wherever it appears, and whether it appears as a separate word or within a string.

The F or 'find' command is slightly different. F something will only find lines which begin with something. This is in fact a particular case of a more general form of the command: where Fn something will find the first line in which something appears in column position n. The plan F something command is therefore equivalent to F1 something. This is, as it seems, a very specific command, and perhaps not as well used as L: but when it is useful, it is very useful. Any kind of positionally formatted text, such as the fixed width columns in a report saved to disk, or even the indented statements of a UniVerse Basic program, are easier to manage using this command.

The commands L and F on their own (ie. without a something to search for) will simply repeat the last locate or the last find respectively.

<, >, MOVE, COPY, DROP and BLOCK: Block Editing

To define a block, first go to the first line of the block and enter the command <, then go to the last line and enter >:

----: 2
0002: DISPLAY You have just typed the command 'FLUFFY'.
----: <
Block FROM set to line 4.
----: 3
0003: DISPLAY This is not a terribly useful command.
----: >
Block THROUGH set to line 4.

If you want to define just one line as a block, you can enter the command <>

Having defined your block, you can COPY it, MOVE it, or DROP (delete) it. To copy or move it, simply go it the location you would like the block to be inserted, and enter the appropriate command:

----: T
Top.
----: COPY
BLOCK from 4 through 4. OK (Y) Y
0001: DISPLAY You have just typed the command 'FLUFFY'.
----:

COPY will make a copy of the lines in the new location (leaving the original lines alone). MOVE will delete the original lines. DROP will simply delete the original lines.

Note that before the COPY was allowed, a 'confirmation' message appeared, and you had to enter a 'Y' to proceed. You can toggle these confirmation messages on and off using the BLOCK command:

----: BLOCK
BLOCK operation verification = disabled.
----: BLOCK
BLOCK operation verification = enabled.

You can go to the beginning of your block using the command G<, and then end with G>, and you can 'clear' your block (which is to say remove the block definition, without deleting any lines) by using the <, > or <> commands on line 0. Use the T (top) command to get to line 0.

A number of the commands already explained above can be combined with blocks. For instance:

C/oldstring/newstring/B applies the change command to every line in the block,

C/oldstring/newstring/GB applies the change command globally to every line in the block,

PB displays the contents of the block a page at a time.

XEQ: Execute an operating system command

You may enter a UniVerse command without leaving the editor by using the PERFORM command:

----: XEQ DISPLAY Do something!
Do something!

----------------- Returned to the EDITOR from the XEQ command.

This command can be tremendously useful, as it allows you to consult UniVerse for information without leaving the record you are editing. For instance, if you are editing a UniVerse Basic program and you need to consult one of your earlier programs to see how you achieved a particular end, you can use XEQ to invoke the editor from within the editor and look at your other program. The record you were editing originally is not saved, but not lost, merely 'suspended' until you return to it.

FILE and SAVE: Writing your edited record back into its file

The commands FILE and SAVE will both write your record back to its file, complete with any changes you have made to it. The only difference between them is that SAVE will allow you to carry on editing (and so is most useful for making periodic 'safe copies' of your work - a very good idea incidentally), while FILE leaves the editor and returns you to the UniVerse prompt (and so you would generally used once you had finished editing your record: for the time being at least),

You can optionally specify a new record key, or even a new filename and record key, by entering SAVE/FILE newkey or SAVE/FILE filename newkey. In this way, you can edit a record, and then leave it unchanged while creating or overwriting another record - possibly in another file.

Bear in mind that UniVerse is a multiuser system and operates a system of 'record locks' to prevent two or more users simultaneously modifying a record and thus nullifying each others work. While you are editing a record, your editor will apply a lock to it, and noone else will be able to access it: through the editor or through any application. If you enter the command RELEASE, you can release this lock and continue editing the record: though naturally you risk either overwriting someone elses work, or allowing them to overwrite your work, by doing so.

.L, .X, etc

The UniVerse editor supports a command history and command stack almost identical to that available from the UniVerse command prompt. .L can be used to list commands, .X to reexecute them, and so on. Rather than describe these stack commands in full here, I would refer the reader back to The Command Stack above.

HELP: On-line documentation

The commands I have listed above are only a subset of those available within the UniVerse editor, and even some of those I have listed are capable of greater refinement than I've described here. While the information on this page should be sufficient to get you started, as you become more fluent you will doubtless wish to learn more about the editor's command set. UniVerse's own manual is very thorough, but perhaps the best source of information is the editor's own HELP command:

----: HELP
You may type one character, a keyword, or just <RETURN> for more information.

If you press ENTER, you will be shown a list of all the editor commands. By entering a single letter, you can reduce this list to those commands which begin with your chosen letter. For instance, if you enter B you will see:

B            - Set the current line pointer to the BOTTOM line.
B any        - BREAK the current line after 'any' into two lines.
BLOCK        - Toggle BLOCK operation verification between ON and OFF.

If you enter a 'keyword', which can be any word or phrase longer than a single letter, you will see a list of all the editor commands which mention that keyword in their help listing. For instance, entering the keyword BLOCK shows you all the editor commands which are somehow block related:

BLOCK        - Toggle BLOCK operation verification between ON and OFF.
C///         - CHANGE one or more lines.  formats permitted are:
                C/from/to     C/from/to/#
                C/from/to/G   C/from/to/#G   C/from/to/G#
                C/from/to/B   C/from/to/BG   C/from/to/GB
   where      / - is any delimiter character.
           from - is the character string to be replaced.
             to - is the character string to substitute.
              # - is the number of lines to CHANGE.  (The default is one)
              G - is the  letter 'G' (global)  CHANGE  all instances  in  line.
              B - is the letter 'B',  CHANGE  all lines in the  defined  BLOCK.
COPY         - COPY a BLOCK (see '<' and '>' ), source block is unchanged.
DROP         - DROP (DELETE) all lines in the defined BLOCK (see '<' and '>' ).
G<           - GO TO line defined by the beginning of the current BLOCK.
G>           - GO TO line defined by the end of the current BLOCK.
MOVE         - MOVE a BLOCK (see '<' and '>' ); source block is deleted.
PB           - PRINT on CRT all lines in the defined  BLOCK (see '<' and '>' ).
SEQ///       - Generate SEQUENTIAL numbers. Formats permitted are:
                SEQ/from/start/#   SEQ/from/start/#/inc
   where      / - is any delimiter character.
           from - is the optional character string to replace.
          start - is the starting sequential number.

ED and UV.VI

ED is the standard editor for PICK derived systems. It would be familiar to a user of Prime INFORMATION, COSMOS Revelation, or VMark UniVerse.

The other editor supported by UniVerse is UV.VI, which is simply a link to the famous UNIX editor vi. This is unique to UniVerse, simply because UniVerse is the only PICK derived system to run over UNIX.

If you are familiar with vi, it is possible to go through life without ever learning ED: and if you are coming to UniVerse from UNIX you may be tempted to do this.

The choice of editor is, in many ways, somewhat personal, and people are often quite partisan in singing the praises of their favourite editor. A direct comparison of ED and vi would therefore be contentious and unlikely to be useful. To a greater extent than perhaps we realise, we all tend to rationalise a defence of that which we are used to: and to believe that an editor feels natural because of the intuitiveness of its design, when in fact it feels natural through long habit and acclimatisation.

I would, however, recommend that any UniVerse developer becomes familiar with ED, even if it is not his first choice for his day to day work. The reasons follow:

1. ED is available on all PICK derived platforms. Many UniVerse systems must be ported from or communicate with other PICK systems on other platforms: these all provide ED but not vi.

2. Most UniVerse records attach particular meanings to particular field numbers: ED numbers the lines it is editing in recognition of this. The UV.VI interface to vi switches vi's line numbering on, but it is clumsier than ED's, and most vi programmers are not used to it, as vi is primarily a code and script editor, not a data editor.

3. ED provides ready access to the UniVerse command language through the XEQ command.

4. The command stack in ED is similar to that available from the main UniVerse command prompt: its use promotes consistency and fluency. Furthermore, the 'stack commands' used to manipulate commands both in ED and from the UniVerse command prompt are based on the commands used to change text in the editor itself.

5. As explained earlier in this course, UNIX does not understand UniVerse file internals. In order for UV.VI to work, therefore, a special linking program must first make a copy of a record's contents as a UNIX temporary file for vi to work on, and copy this back to the UniVerse file once vi has finished. This is clearly less efficient and elegant than ED, which is written in UniVerse Basic and can thus access the records directly. Furthermore, the name of the temporary file created to allow vi to work is unrelated to the name and location of the original record, and can thus be misleading.

6. ED understands UniVerse Basic, which will be covered later in this course. It can therefore automatically indent it to show it's structure: and this is a tremendously useful facility.

In short, ED was designed for use with UniVerse, and vi wasn't. I doubt I will have reached the die-hard vi enthusiast, but I hope I will have encouraged others to at least become familiar with UniVerse's own editor.

Computers: Universe: Editor Macros

In our discussion of the editor, we drew certain parallels between the editor command language and the UniVerse command system. Both had a HELP command you could use to consult an on-line user manual. Both allowed you to enter .L to list a history of previously used commands, and various other commands like .X, .R and .C to manipulate and re-execute them. One feature of the UniVerse command language wasn't compared: the way in which you could add commands to the UniVerse command language by adding records to the VOC file. Can you add commands to the editor's command language?

Well, sort of. Every command in the UniVerse command language is defined by a record in the VOC file: change those records, and you change the language. The commands in the editor command language are all 'hard-coded' into the editor: you can't change them. Neither can you just add a new command called (say) DOSOMETHING.

However, you can do something similar. Begin by starting the editor:

ED VOC FLUFFY
4 lines long.

----:

The number of lines reported will depend on the state in which you left the FLUFFY record at the end of the last section: but its not important. However long the record is, display it using the P command:

----: P
0001: PA
0002: DISPLAY You have just typed the command 'FLUFFY'.
0003: DISPLAY This command is not terribly useful.
0004: DISPLAY It just displays this message.
Bottom at line 4.
----:

Now enter the .L command to list your command stack:

----: .L

01 P

0004: DISPLAY It just displays this message.
Bottom at line 4.
----:

From this you can see that you have a single command in you command stack: the P command.

You can save this command, giving it a name of your own choosing so that you can use it again. To do this, use the .S command:

----: .S1 MYCOMMAND
Creating file "&ED&" as Type 1.
Creating file "D_&ED&" as Type 3, Modulo 1, Separation 2.
Added "@ID", the default record for RetrieVe, to "D_&ED&".
Saved "MYCOMMAND" in "&ED&".

(If someone has used the .S command from the editor before in your directory, the &ED& file will already exist and you will not see the messages describing its creation.)

The &ED& file is the closest equivalent the editor command language has to a VOC file. Each record in &ED& creates not a new command in the editor command language, but rather what is termed a macro. The idea, though, is similar.

To execute your new macro, use the .X command: but instead of specifying a line number from the command stack to reexecute, specify the name of your macro:

----: .X MYCOMMAND
0001: PA
0002: DISPLAY You have just typed the command 'FLUFFY'.
0003: DISPLAY This command is not terribly useful.
0004: DISPLAY It just displays this message.
Bottom at line 4.

***** End of prestored command execution.
0004: DISPLAY It just displays this message.
Bottom at line 4.
----:

So far, all I have demonstrated is a handy way to take a one letter command (P) and abbreviate it to 12 letters (.X MYCOMMAND): less than breathtaking. However, the principle applies, of course, to macros of any length: you can string together as many of these commands as you wish, and execute them with a single command. For instance, if your development team uses a standard header at the beginning of each UniVerse Basic program, you can create a macro to insert the template lines and call it TEMPLATE or somesuch.

Ok, ok, I can tell you're still not impressed. To get a bit more impressive, create the following macro. Create the following record in the &ED& file with the editor:

ED &ED& BASIC.RUN
New record.

----: I
0001= E
0002= SAVE
0003= XEQ BASIC @FILE @ID
0004= XEQ RUN @FILE @ID
0005= (Press ENTER)
Bottom at line 5.
----: FILE

What's happening here? Well, the first line of each macro, like the first line of each VOC record, indicates the type of record it is: fairly pointless in practice, as all editor macros have an E on this line.

The second line is the ordinary SAVE command: so when the macro executes, it will save the record currently being edited.

The third line is the clever bit. It uses XEQ to invoke the UniVerse BASIC command. This is the command which compiles programs. It takes two parameters, the filename containing the program to be compiled, and the key of the program record.

In these places, the macro passes @FILE and @ID. These are special values that are specially designed for use with XEQ commands from the editor. @FILE is automatically replaced with the name of the file which ED is currently editing, and @ID with the key of the record. So if you are editing MYPROGRAM in BP, the command actually executed by XEQ here is BASIC BP MYPROGRAM - the program you have just SAVEd. Clever, huh? The next line then runs the program for you in the same way.

When the macro finishes, you are returned to the editor, where you can continue working on your program. In this way, you can edit, compile, run, edit, compile, run... all without ever leaving the editor!

The UniVerse documentation on editor macros is a little odd, for two reasons:

1. All their examples show macro commands being created using .S - as I showed in my first example: but for most macros, it's much each just to edit &ED&, and I'm not sure why the manual doesn't explain this.

2. They explain two 'special' editor commands, LOOP and PAUSE, which they clearly feel are particularly useful in editor macros. They are both weird in syntax and implementation, and I don't fancy explaining either here. Their names sort of suggest their purposes, so if you're keen to look, go for it.

Computers: Universe: Retrieve

During out discussion of file dictionaries above (see Dictionaries above) you will have seen a number of examples of RetrieVe at work, providing simple listings of records.

We have, however, barely scratched the surface of RetrieVe's abilities. It is one of those rare tools which manages to combine simplicity in everyday use with the muscle to produce extensive and highly complex reports when they are required: and to handle the entire continuum between these extremes.

In this section, we shall take a closer look at the language, learning sufficient to produce perhaps 80% of the reports required by real clients within real systems.

Be aware, though, that RetrieVe has the power to handle most of the other 20% too: when you get to the point where you need to accomplish something which these notes do not describe, do not assume that it cannot be achieved with Retrieve: consult UniVerse's documentation first for the fine detail that you may require.

Bear in mind also that RetrieVe is closely integrated into the rest of UniVerse. Sometimes, the effect you require may depend on combining RetrieVe with other UniVerse tools: such as the creation of a new I-descriptor which in turn calls a UniVerse Basic subroutine to return the vital piece of information you need to complete your report.

It is true that during your career you will occassionally encounter reports which require hand coding using UniVerse Basic, but if you find yourself reaching for the compiler to prepare reports frequently, discipline yourself to ask first, for each report, 'could I do this using RetrieVe?'.

UniVerse Basic, for all its strengths, is a general purpose language. If you turn to it to write reports, you will not only have to write the tricksy bits which you felt were beyond RetrieVe, you'll have to write code to number pages, handle page breaks, automatically adjust to different screen and paper widths, total, average, sort... all the things you get with RetrieVe 'for free'.

Computers: Universe: Listing Records

An example file

To illustrate the query language, we need a file to enquire about. The examples in this section will use COPY.OF.VOC, which we created to illustrate the use of indexes (see Indexing Fields).

If you did not follow the examples in that section, you can create this file as follows:

>CREATE.FILE COPY.OF.VOC DYNAMIC
Creating file "COPY.OF.VOC" as Type 30.
Creating file "D_COPY.OF.VOC" as Type 3, Modulo 1, Separation 2.
Added "@ID", the default record for RetrieVe, to "D_COPY.OF.VOC".
>COPY FROM VOC TO COPY.OF.VOC ALL

825 records copied.
>COPY FROM DICT VOC TO DICT COPY.OF.VOC ALL OVERWRITING

19 records copied.
>

You also learnt earlier (see Phrases) that the @ phrase is used as to provide 'default' parameters to LIST instructions if they are entered without parameters. In this section, though, this would complicate the examples. We must remove the @ phrase from the dictionary of COPY.OF.VOC to avoid this. The DELETE command used below is straightforward, and explained fully later during our discussion of the TCL command language. For now, enter:

>DELETE DICT COPY.OF.VOC @

1 records DELETEd.
>

Your file is now ready to enquire on.

A basic list

As you have already discovered, to list the records in a file you need only enter the command LIST followed by a file name. For instance:

>LIST COPY.OF.VOC

LIST COPY.OF.VOC 10:05:46  08-19-99  PAGE 1
VOC.........

F9
PRINT.ADMIN
TEST.PARAGRA
PH
COMO
NOHEAD
LT
BREAK.VERB
SUBO
ALL.MATCH
INQUIRING
LIST.ME
IN
MAP.VERB
CONSYS.REPOR
TS
MAKE.DEMO.FI
LES
STATS
PTIME
Press any key to continue...

There are 800 or so records in this file, so LIST will pause at the bottom of every page. You may see the next page by pressing ENTER, or abandon the enquiry by pressing Q. If you want the enquiry to run to its last page (perhaps in order to see totals) without pausing after every page, press N. For now, press Q.

Listing fields

This listing displays only record keys. To display other fields, simply add their names to the command:

>LIST COPY.OF.VOC TYPE DESC SIZE

LIST COPY.OF.VOC TYPE DESC SIZE 10:32:37  08-19-99  PAGE 1
VOC.........    TYPE    DESC..........................    Length...

F9              D       Data descriptor for Field 9 of           11
                        any file
PRINT.ADMIN     PA      Paragraph                                25
TEST.PARAGRA    PA      PA                                       64
PH
COMO            V       Verb - Control copying of                31
                        command output to files
NOHEAD          K       Keyword - Do not print a                  5
                        banner page
LT              K       Keyword - "Less Than" operator            3
BREAK.VERB      V       Verb - Enable or disable INTR,           12
                        STOP, SUSP, and BRK keys.
SUBO            V       Verb - Subtract OCTAL numbers            17
ALL.MATCH       K       Keyword - Specify that ALL                5
                        strings should match for
                        SEARCH/ESEARCH statement
INQUIRING       K       Keyword - Prompt for record               4
                        name
LIST.ME         S       Sentence - Return status of              11
                        all users with your login name
Press any key to continue...

Sorting

The order in which these records appear is not, strictly speaking, random, as it is reflects the order in which the records are found in the physical groups, which in turn depends on the hashing of the file (see UniVerse Files). It is not though, as some believe, the order in which the records were added: in fact it has no logical meaning.

To sort your records by fieldname, add the words BY fieldname to the end of your enquiry. To sort first by fieldname1 and within that by fieldname2, add the words BY fieldname1 BY fieldname 2. You can in fact chain as many sorts in this way as you wish. This example sorts first by type, and then by key:

>LIST COPY.OF.VOC TYPE DESC SIZE BY TYPE

LIST COPY.OF.VOC TYPE SIZE DESC BY TYPE BY @ID 10:42:31  08-19-99  PAGE 1
VOC.........    TYPE    Length...    DESC..........................

F1              D              11    Data descriptor for Field 1 of
                                     any file
F10             D              12    Data descriptor for Field 10
                                     of any file
F2              D              11    Data descriptor for Field 2 of
                                     any file
F3              D              11    Data descriptor for Field 3 of
                                     any file
F4              D              11    Data descriptor for Field 4 of
                                     any file
F5              D              11    Data descriptor for Field 5 of
                                     any file
F6              D              11    Data descriptor for Field 6 of
                                     any file
F7              D              11    Data descriptor for Field 7 of
                                     any file
F8              D              11    Data descriptor for Field 8 of
                                     any file
F9              D              11    Data descriptor for Field 9 of
                                     any file
Press any key to continue...

You can sort your records 'backwards' by using BY.DSND ('by descending') in place of BY.

An interesting footnote is that UniVerse provides a SORT command which is identical to LIST in every respect save one: it acts as if BY @ID had been added to the end of the list of BY clauses. There is, perhaps, little harm in it, but I generally recommend that people do not use it, but use instead LIST and add the required BY @ID. This is simply because the latter is more descriptive and less easily misunderstood. For instance, if you saw the command...

SORT COPY.OF.VOC BY TYPE

...would it be obvious to you that the file was being sorted by both TYPE and @ID? The functionally identical...

LIST COPY.OF.VOC BY TYPE BY @ID

...makes this inescapable.

Sampling

It is sometimes useful to enquire on a sample of the records in your file. Just use the SAMPLE n keyword to list a sample of n records. The records are the first n encountered in the physical order they are stored in the file. As explained above, this is not strictly random, but usually might as well be. Be aware, though, that repeated SAMPLE enquiries on the same file will not yield different sets of records each time.

>LIST COPY.OF.VOC TYPE DESC SIZE SAMPLE 3

LIST COPY.OF.VOC TYPE DESC SIZE SAMPLE 3 11:57:30  08-19-99  PAGE 1
VOC.........    TYPE    DESC..........................    Length...

F9              D       Data descriptor for Field 9 of           11
                        any file
PRINT.ADMIN     PA      Paragraph                                25
TEST.PARAGRA    PA      PA                                       64
PH

Sample of 3 records listed.
>

Listing selectively

If you wish to enquire on only a subset of the records in your file, you can use the keyword WITH followed by your criteria. For instance, if you were interested only in seeing M types, you would enter the command:

>LIST COPY.OF.VOC TYPE DESC SIZE WITH TYPE = 'M'

LIST COPY.OF.VOC TYPE DESC SIZE WITH TYPE = "M" 12:00:46  08-19-99  PAGE 1
VOC.........    TYPE    DESC..........................    Length...

CONV.ACCT.ME    M       Menu - UniVerse Account                  34
NU                      Importation
PRINT.ADMIN.    M       Menu - UniVerse Spooler                  35
MENU                    Administration
BASIC.CONT      M       Menu                                     31
SP.JOB          M       Menu                                     27
CONSYS.MENU     M       M                                        26
SP.MOD          M       Menu                                     27
ACCT.CONV       M       Menu                                     30
SP.STATUS       M       Menu                                     30
MENUS           M       MENU selector - Invoke the               31
                        MENU maintenance menu

9 records listed.
>

The equal sign = is probably the most commonly used, but still only one of many comparison operators you can use in your criteria. Here is a list of the most popular, with examples:

Operator

|

Example and Meaning

|

Synonyms

=

|

TYPE = 'M'
Type equal to 'M'

|

EQ

#

|

TYPE # 'M'
Type not equal to 'M'

|

<>, >;<, NE

>

|

SIZE > 10
Size greater than 10

|

GT, AFTER

<

|

SIZE < 10
Size less than 10

|

LT, BEFORE

>=

|

SIZE >= 10
Size greater than or equal to 10

|

=>, GE

<=

|

SIZE <= 10
Size less than or equal to 10

|

=<, LE

LIKE

|

DESC LIKE ...PRINTER...
Description with the word 'PRINTER' in it. Note that the '...' strings act as wildcards

|

MATCHES MATCHING

UNLIKE

|

DESC UNLIKE ...PRINTER...
Description without the word 'PRINTER' in it. Note that the '...' strings act as wildcards

|

NOT.MATCHING

SPOKEN

|

DESC SPOKEN 'SMITH'
Description pronounced 'Smith'. Does phonetic matching, especially useful with name searches, but less so here...

|

SAID, ~

You can reverse any of these criteria using NOT: but you don't normally need to, as most of the operators have opposites in any case. For instance, NOT TYPE = 'M' means the same as TYPE # 'M',

More usefully, you can combine these criteria using the keywords AND and OR. Joining two conditions with AND means that they must both be true for the record to be selected. Joining them with OR means that at least one of them must be true.

UniVerse always evaluates AND links before OR links: you need to be careful when combining conditions to ensure that they mean to UniVerse what they mean to you. For instance, consider the following criteria:

...WITH SIZE GT 100 AND TYPE = 'PA' OR TYPE = 'S'

What this criteria will do is select all the paragraphs more than 100 bytes in length, and all the sentences regardless of their lengths. Is this rather odd result what the developer wanted? Probably not: it would seem more likely he was looking for long sentences and paragraphs: ie. any sentence or paragraph more than 100 bytes long. He could have resolved the ambiguity with brackets:

...WITH SIZE GT 100 AND (TYPE = 'PA' OR TYPE = 'S')

The meaning of this is obvious to both developer and UniVerse.

Even if the original developer had intended, for some reason, to choose long paragraphs and all sentences, he still wrote poor code as it is difficult for maintenance programmers to tell whether that was the intended result, or whether the condition contains a bug. He would have been better to include the brackets for clarity, even though they are redundant:

...WITH (SIZE GT 100 AND TYPE = 'PA') OR TYPE = 'S'

No question here what is intended.

Totalling

To total a numeric column, add the word TOTAL before the appropriate field.

>LIST COPY.OF.VOC TYPE DESC TOTAL SIZE

LIST COPY.OF.VOC TYPE DESC TOTAL SIZE 10:46:25  08-19-99  PAGE 1
VOC.........    TYPE    DESC..........................    Length...

F9              D       Data descriptor for Field 9 of           11
                        any file
PRINT.ADMIN     PA      Paragraph                                25
TEST.PARAGRA    PA      PA                                       64
PH
COMO            V       Verb - Control copying of                31
                        command output to files
NOHEAD          K       Keyword - Do not print a                  5
                        banner page
LT              K       Keyword - "Less Than" operator            3
BREAK.VERB      V       Verb - Enable or disable INTR,           12
                        STOP, SUSP, and BRK keys.
SUBO            V       Verb - Subtract OCTAL numbers            17
ALL.MATCH       K       Keyword - Specify that ALL                5
                        strings should match for
                        SEARCH/ESEARCH statement
INQUIRING       K       Keyword - Prompt for record               4
                        name
LIST.ME         S       Sentence - Return status of              11
                        all users with your login name
Press any key to continue...

...to see your total, you'll need to get to the end of the enquiry. Press N at the 'end of page' prompt to skip all further pauses. The enquiry will flash all the pages past your screen until it gets to...

LIST COPY.OF.VOC TYPE DESC TOTAL SIZE 10:46:25  08-19-99  PAGE 88
VOC.........    TYPE    DESC..........................    Length...

                        LORRY for packing and
                        unpacking Universe files into
                        ASCII 'lorry' files
P.DET           V       Verb - UNASSIGN a physical               27
                        PRINTER from your task
LIST.ITEM       V       Verb - List complete records             37
                        in specified file
INFORM          K       Keyword - Display the spooler             5
                        job number of newly queued
                        jobs
BREAK.ON        K       Keyword - Specify BREAK                   4
                        conditions in a report
LISTPA          R       Remote - LIST the PARAGRAPHS             24
                        stored in the VOCABULARY file
CUSTOMERS       F       F                                        24
                                                          =========
                                                             21,211


824 records listed.
>

Setting breakpoints

To break the report into sections, add the word BREAK.ON before the appropriate field. This will force a break whenever the field in question changes. Note that this will produce meaningless results unless the records are sorted by the field being broken on, so a sort BY the appropriate field almost always accompanies a BREAK.ON. Note also that totalled numeric fields automatically show subtotals at breakpoints:

>LIST COPY.OF.VOC BREAK.ON TYPE DESC TOTAL SIZE BY TYPE

LIST COPY.OF.VOC BREAK.ON TYPE DESC TOTAL SIZE BY TYPE 10:55:11  08-19-99  PAGE1
VOC.........    TYPE    DESC..........................    Length...

F9              D       Data descriptor for Field 9 of           11
                        any file
F7              D       Data descriptor for Field 7 of           11
                        any file
F1              D       Data descriptor for Field 1 of           11
                        any file
F2              D       Data descriptor for Field 2 of           11
                        any file
F4              D       Data descriptor for Field 4 of           11
                        any file
F5              D       Data descriptor for Field 5 of           11
                        any file
F6              D       Data descriptor for Field 6 of           11
                        any file
F10             D       Data descriptor for Field 10             12
                        of any file
F8              D       Data descriptor for Field 8 of           11
                        any file
F3              D       Data descriptor for Field 3 of           11
                        any file
                **                                        ---------
                D                                               111

MANNY.BP.O      F       F                                        26
DICT.DICT       F       File - The DICTIONARY for all            51
                        uniVerse dictionaries in the
                        system
TEST1           F       F                                        16
CUSTOMER.INV    F       F                                        30
OICES
DICT.PICK       F       File - The DICTIONARY for all            51
                        Pick style uniVerse
                        dictionaries in the system
CONSYS.RESIZ    F       F                                        72
E.FILES
THISISALONGN    F       F                                        30
AME
INTEOD.UFD      F       F                                        28
Press any key to continue...

(I've cheated here, for clarity omitting the page end prompt between the first and second pages of the report. Depending on the exact contents of your VOC, and thus your COPY.OF.VOC, the first breakpoint will probably occur somewhere after the first page.)

As you can see, RetrieVe puts a line of stars at the end of each section. If you'd like some other visual marker used instead, specify it in double quotes after your BREAK.ON:

>LIST COPY.OF.VOC BREAK.ON "::::" TYPE DESC TOTAL SIZE BY TYPE

LIST COPY.OF.VOC BREAK.ON "::::" TYPE DESC TOTAL SIZE BY TYPE 11:20:57  08-19-99
  PAGE 1
VOC.........    TYPE    DESC..........................    Length...

F9              D       Data descriptor for Field 9 of           11
                        any file
F7              D       Data descriptor for Field 7 of           11
                        any file
F1              D       Data descriptor for Field 1 of           11
                        any file
F2              D       Data descriptor for Field 2 of           11
                        any file
F4              D       Data descriptor for Field 4 of           11
                        any file
F5              D       Data descriptor for Field 5 of           11
                        any file
F6              D       Data descriptor for Field 6 of           11
                        any file
F10             D       Data descriptor for Field 10             12
                        of any file
F8              D       Data descriptor for Field 8 of           11
                        any file
F3              D       Data descriptor for Field 3 of           11
                        any file
                ::::                                      ---------
                D                                               111

MANNY.BP.O      F       F                                        26
DICT.DICT       F       File - The DICTIONARY for all            51
                        uniVerse dictionaries in the
                        system
TEST1           F       F                                        16
CUSTOMER.INV    F       F                                        30
OICES
DICT.PICK       F       File - The DICTIONARY for all            51
                        Pick style uniVerse
                        dictionaries in the system
CONSYS.RESIZ    F       F                                        72
E.FILES
THISISALONGN    F       F                                        30
AME
INTEOD.UFD      F       F                                        28
Press any key to continue...

By including certain special codes in your marker string, you can further control how your breakpoints work. For instance, the 'N' token resets the page number to one after each breakpoint. All the codes take this same form: a single letter in single quotes. To use it, you'd enter the command LIST COPY.OF.VOC BREAK.ON "::::'N'" TYPE TOTAL SIZE BY TYPE.

Other tokens include 'D', which suppresses the breakpoint line if there's only one corresponding record (because who needs to total one record?), and 'P' begins a new page for each breakpoint value. Check out BREAK.ON in the UniVerse documentation for a complete list: but these are the ones I tend to use most often.

Summarising your report

If you are only interested in the break points themselves, and not the individual records, you can summarise your report by adding the word DET.SUP (short for 'detail suppress'). Note that this has the effect of hiding the @ID column as this is clearing particular to individual records, and not breakpointed groups. The DESC field would be equally meaningless in a report of this kind and I have omitted it:

>LIST COPY.OF.VOC BREAK.ON TYPE TOTAL SIZE BY TYPE DET.SUP

LIST COPY.OF.VOC BREAK.ON TYPE TOTAL SIZE BY TYPE DET.SUP 11:11:09  08-19-99  PA
GE 1
TYPE    Length...

D             111
F           4,351
K           1,783
M             271
PA          4,032
PH            393
PQ            226
Q             117
R             688
S             569
V           8,607
X              63
        =========
           21,211

824 records listed.
>

Providing headers and footers

So far, the text of the LIST command itself has appeared as the heading of your enquiries. To apply your own heading, add HEADING "heading text":

>LIST COPY.OF.VOC TYPE DESC SIZE HEADING "My COPY.OF.VOC report"

My COPY.OF.VOC Report
VOC.........    TYPE    DESC..........................    Length...

F9              D       Data descriptor for Field 9 of           11
                        any file
PRINT.ADMIN     PA      Paragraph                                25
TEST.PARAGRA    PA      PA                                       64
PH
COMO            V       Verb - Control copying of                31
                        command output to files
NOHEAD          K       Keyword - Do not print a                  5
                        banner page
LT              K       Keyword - "Less Than" operator            3
BREAK.VERB      V       Verb - Enable or disable INTR,           12
                        STOP, SUSP, and BRK keys.
SUBO            V       Verb - Subtract OCTAL numbers            17
ALL.MATCH       K       Keyword - Specify that ALL                5
                        strings should match for
                        SEARCH/ESEARCH statement
INQUIRING       K       Keyword - Prompt for record               4
                        name
LIST.ME         S       Sentence - Return status of              11
                        all users with your login name
Press any key to continue...

You can add footers similarly by adding FOOTING "footer text".

There are a number of special 'tokens' you can include in headers and footers. They all appear between single quotes:

'P' will include a page number.
'D' will include the date.
'L' will include a line break.
'G' will expand to a string of spaces as long as any other 'G' on the same line, and sufficient to make the complete line cover the width of the page. This ludicrous explanation is entirely correct and completely impossible to understand: the net effect is to 'spread out' elements of a heading, so HEADING "'D''G'My Heading'G''P'" will put the date on the extreme left, the page number on the extreme right, and the words My Heading equidistant between them.

>LIST COPY.OF.VOC TYPE DESC SIZE HEADING "'D''G'COPY.OF.VOC Report'G''P'"

08-19-99                         COPY.OF.VOC Report                         1
VOC.........    TYPE    DESC..........................    Length...

F9              D       Data descriptor for Field 9 of           11
                        any file
PRINT.ADMIN     PA      Paragraph                                25
TEST.PARAGRA    PA      PA                                       64
PH
COMO            V       Verb - Control copying of                31
                        command output to files
NOHEAD          K       Keyword - Do not print a                  5
                        banner page
LT              K       Keyword - "Less Than" operator            3
BREAK.VERB      V       Verb - Enable or disable INTR,           12
                        STOP, SUSP, and BRK keys.
SUBO            V       Verb - Subtract OCTAL numbers            17
ALL.MATCH       K       Keyword - Specify that ALL                5
                        strings should match for
                        SEARCH/ESEARCH statement
INQUIRING       K       Keyword - Prompt for record               4
                        name
LIST.ME         S       Sentence - Return status of              11
                        all users with your login name
Press any key to continue...

You can also link your heading to your breakpoints, such that each breakpoint value starts on a new page, and the breakpoint value itself appears in the heading for that page. To do this, you need to use one of BREAK.ON's special codes (see above) which I've not yet mentioned: 'B'. This causes the breakpoint value to appear in the heading. You also need to put a 'B' token into your heading, telling LIST where to put the value.

This is one of those things that is harder to describe than to do. Check over the BREAK.ON notes again, try the following example, and you should get it:

LIST COPY.OF.VOC BREAK.ON "'B'" TYPE DESC TOTAL SIZE BY TYPE HEADING "Type 'B' records"

Type D records
VOC.........    TYPE    DESC..........................    Length...

F9              D       Data descriptor for Field 9 of           11
                        any file
F7              D       Data descriptor for Field 7 of           11
                        any file
F1              D       Data descriptor for Field 1 of           11
                        any file
F2              D       Data descriptor for Field 2 of           11
                        any file
F4              D       Data descriptor for Field 4 of           11
                        any file
F5              D       Data descriptor for Field 5 of           11
                        any file
F6              D       Data descriptor for Field 6 of           11
                        any file
F10             D       Data descriptor for Field 10             12
                        of any file
F8              D       Data descriptor for Field 8 of           11
                        any file
F3              D       Data descriptor for Field 3 of           11
                        any file
Press any key to continue...

It's redundant, of course, to show the 'D' type in the heading and then again on ever row. To avoid it, use BREAK.SUP (break on suppressing column) instead of BREAK.ON:

LIST COPY.OF.VOC BREAK.ON "'B'" TYPE DESC TOTAL SIZE BY TYPE HEADING "Type 'B' records"

Type D records
VOC.........    DESC..........................    Length...

F9              Data descriptor for Field 9 of           11
                any file
F7              Data descriptor for Field 7 of           11
                any file
F1              Data descriptor for Field 1 of           11
                any file
F2              Data descriptor for Field 2 of           11
                any file
F4              Data descriptor for Field 4 of           11
                any file
F5              Data descriptor for Field 5 of           11
                any file
F6              Data descriptor for Field 6 of           11
                any file
F10             Data descriptor for Field 10             12
                of any file
F8              Data descriptor for Field 8 of           11
                any file
F3              Data descriptor for Field 3 of           11
                any file
Press any key to continue...

Printing your enquiry

To send your enquiry results to the printer instead of the screen, add LPTR ('line printer') to your command, as in LIST COPY.OF.VOC TYPE SIZE DESC LPTR. This will print to your 'default printer': which printer is your default printer will depend on how your system adminstrator has configured your system. Go and hassle him if you're in doubt.

If your system has many printers, you administrator may have set up more than one UniVerse 'print channel'. Different channels can route output to different printers or even to files on your disk. They are created with the SETPTR, which we will encounter later in these notes, and each one is numbered. If you need to print to a channel other than the default (channel 0), add the channel number to the end of your LPTR command, as in LIST COPY.OF.VOC TYPE SIZE DESC LPTR 2.

Computers: Universe: Overriding Dictionaries

RetrieVe and Dictionaries

You may have noticed during the last section (see Listing Records) that you have not had to specify any display specifications for the columns in your enquiries so far. For instance, when you listed the TYPE column, you did not need to specify that you wanted a four character wide field justified to the left and with a heading of 'TYPE': all this information was derived from the dictionary of the COPY.OF.VOC file.

This is, of course, one of the strengths of UniVerse. The way in which a field is displayed depends above all on its contents: and of course its contents do not vary from enquiry to enquiry. It is therefore more efficient to define these details once in the dictionary of the file, and allow enquiries using the dictionary in question to 'inherit' the display details. This has the further advantage that if at some point in the future the contents and thus the display requirements of the field change, simply by changing the corresponding dictionary record all the enquiries using the record are updated.

Sometimes, though, enquiries will vary in the way in which they present fields. Very commonly, one enquiry which lists only keys and descriptions will wish to allow a wider column width to the description than another which shows many columns from the same file, and cannot afford the column space.

This problem, and one solution, have already been discussed (see Dictionaries). The most common solution is to define a 'synonym' dictionary record, evaluating the same data but giving it different display characteristics: such as a different column width.

Overriding existing dictionary definitions

There is another technique, though, which can prove useful where you are confident that the change you wish to make to the display characteristics of a field is unique to the enquiry you are working on. For instance, if you are running a 'once off', 'ad hoc' enquiry, you may not wish to go to the trouble of creating a new dictionary record simply in order to give one column greater width. More importantly, you may wish to avoid cluttering up the dictionary file with records never likely to be used again.

You can specify parameters which override specific dictionary parameters within your retrieve statement. This is perhaps easiest to illustrate by example. You may have noticed that in the sample enquiries run in the previous section, the DESC (description) frequently wrapped onto two or more lines within a fairly narrow column. You could avoid this by overriding the dictionary display width for the column like this:

>LIST COPY.OF.VOC DESC FMT "65T"

LIST COPY.OF.VOC DESC FMT "65T" 13:04:39  08-19-99  PAGE 1
VOC.........   DESC.............................................................

F9             Data descriptor for Field 9 of any file
PRINT.ADMIN    Paragraph
TEST.PARAGRA   PA
PH
COMO           Verb - Control copying of command output to files
NOHEAD         Keyword - Do not print a banner page
LT             Keyword - "Less Than" operator
BREAK.VERB     Verb - Enable or disable INTR, STOP, SUSP, and BRK keys.
SUBO           Verb - Subtract OCTAL numbers
ALL.MATCH      Keyword - Specify that ALL strings should match for
               SEARCH/ESEARCH statement
INQUIRING      Keyword - Prompt for record name
LIST.ME        Sentence - Return status of all users with your login name
IN             Keyword - The word "IN"; ignored by RetrieVe
MAP.VERB       Verb - Display a MAP of the contents of the system CATALOG
CONSYS.REPOR   F
TS
MAKE.DEMO.FI   Verb - Create demo files (8.3.3)
LES
STATS          Keyword - Synonym for STATISTICS
Press any key to continue...

The FMT keyword following the DESC fieldname controls the format in which that field is displayed. It overrides the fifth line of the DESC dictionary record, which shows a format of 30T.

You can override most of the dictionary fields in this way:

CONV overrides the third dictionary record field: the conversion.
COL.HDG overrides the fourth dictionary record field: the column heading.
FMT, as we have seen, overrides the fifth dictionary record field: the format.
SINGLE.VALUE and MULTI.VALUE overwride the S or M in the sixth field of the dictionary record.

Columns without dictionary records

You can even list columns not connected to any dictionary record using the EVAL keyword. You can use the expression EVAL "formula" almost anywhere you can use a field name in a RetrieVe command. The formula works in precisely the same way as the formula found on the second line of an I-descriptor (see Imaginary Fields), and effectively means you can avoid creating an I-descriptor if you are confident that you will not be using your formula anywhere except in the current enquiry. EVAL is particularly good for 'ad-hoc' enquiries.

To take an example, imagine that you wished to include a column showing the length of the keys for all the COPY.OF.VOC records. You could create an I-descriptor to do this easily enough, but you've come to the conclusion that this information will never be needed again, so its best not to clog up the dictionary with the extra record. (Incidentally - I think you'd be right about this. It's difficult to think of a plausible reason why anyone should want such a bizarre statistic: but cut me some slack, it's not always easy writing training courses).

Using EVAL, your enquiry would run:

>LIST COPY.OF.VOC EVAL "LEN(@ID)"

LIST COPY.OF.VOC EVAL "LEN(@ID)" 13:22:58  08-19-99  PAGE 1
VOC.........    LEN(@ID)..

F9              2
PRINT.ADMIN     11
TEST.PARAGRA    14
PH
COMO            4
NOHEAD          6
LT              2
BREAK.VERB      10
SUBO            4
ALL.MATCH       9
INQUIRING       9
LIST.ME         7
IN              2
MAP.VERB        8
CONSYS.REPOR    14
TS
MAKE.DEMO.FI    15
LES
STATS           5
PTIME           5
Press any key to continue...

Ok, so it works, but its pretty untidy. The numbers are left justified, and the column title simply a restatement of the formula. This is because without a dictionary record, you RetieVe doesn't know how to format the information. But you can use any of the keywords listed earlier in this section, like FMT, to solve this problem:

>LIST COPY.OF.VOC EVAL "LEN(@ID)" COL.HDG 'Key length' FMT '10R'

LIST COPY.OF.VOC EVAL "LEN(@ID)" COL.HDG "Key length" FMT "10R" 13:27:07  08-19-
99  PAGE 1
VOC.........    Key length

F9                       2
PRINT.ADMIN             11
TEST.PARAGRA            14
PH
COMO                     4
NOHEAD                   6
LT                       2
BREAK.VERB              10
SUBO                     4
ALL.MATCH                9
INQUIRING                9
LIST.ME                  7
IN                       2
MAP.VERB                 8
CONSYS.REPOR            14
TS
MAKE.DEMO.FI            15
LES
STATS                    5
Press any key to continue...

Isn't that better?

What if you now wanted to sort the enquiry by the length of the key? (This example is getting weirder and weirder, but stick with it.) If you were sorting by a fieldname, you'd have to specify the fieldname twice: once in the list of fields, and again in a BY clause. Does this mean you have to type the EVAL... with all its accompanying nonsense twice? Well, you could, but there is a better way. You can use the keyword AS to give a 'name' to your EVAL column, and then use the name in the BY clause. It's done like this:

>LIST COPY.OF.VOC EVAL "LEN(@ID)" COL.HDG 'Key length' FMT '10R' AS LEN.KEY BY LEN.KEY

LIST COPY.OF.VOC EVAL "LEN(@ID)" COL.HDG "Key length" FMT "10R" AS LEN.KEY BY LE
N.KEY 13:42:12  08-19-99  PAGE 1
VOC.........    Key length

|                        1
<                        1
+                        1
=                        1
-                        1
A                        1
%                        1
P                        1
)                        1
;                        1
~                        1
?                        1
&                        1
*                        1
Q                        1
/                        1
(                        1
>                        1
,                        1
Press any key to continue...

In fact, you can even use AS to provide a 'synonym' to an ordinary field too. Let's say someone took your formula and created a dictionary record called THE.LENGTH.OF.THE.KEY. Even to me (and I have always preferred long, descriptive and unabbreviated names for computer entities) this seems over the top. To avoid having to type it more than once, you could say:

>LIST COPY.OF.VOC THE.LENGTH.OF.THE.KEY AS LEN.KEY BY LEN.KEY

Computers: Universe: Select Lists

NOTE!

RetrieVe and SQL both use a command called SELECT. They are not related. UniVerse can tell whether you are executing a RetrieVe or a SQL SELECT by analysing the syntax of the overall command: they are formed quite differently, and do different things, All the examples below are RetrieVe SELECT commands.

The SELECT command

The SELECT command creates a list of keys 'in memory' which is then used by the next command you execute. Much of its syntax is the same as that for the LIST command (see Listing Records). It supports the same WITH, BY and SAMPLE keyswords. For instance:

>SELECT COPY.OF.VOC SAMPLE 3

3 record(s) selected to SELECT list #0.
>>

So what has happened here? Well, three keys from the COPY.OF.VOC file are now stored in a select list. Note the prompt is now >> instead of the usual >: this is a reminder that the command you are about to type in will be using a select list.

To see what effect this has, try the following command:

>>LIST COPY.OF.VOC

LIST COPY.OF.VOC 14:00:33  08-19-99  PAGE 1
VOC.........

F9
PRINT.ADMIN
TEST.PARAGRA
PH

3 records listed.
>

This LIST command would normally have displayed all the records in the file: but because there was (in UniVerse jargon) an 'active select list' of three keys, it displayed only those three records.

So what is the point of this? You could have achieved the same thing more easily by typing LIST COPY.OF.VOC SAMPLE 3.

Firstly, LIST is not the only command which responds to select lists. For instance, if you wished to edit a number of records, you could first create a select list containing their keys, and then use ED like this:

>SELECT COPY.OF.VOC SAMPLE 3

3 record(s) selected to SELECT list #0.
>>ED COPY.OF.VOC

SELECTed record name = "F9".
6 lines long.

----:

What has happened here? Well, ED has spotted the select list, and so has begun by using the first key from that list to open a record. As soon as you abandon or file the current record, the editor will open the next record in the select list, and so on until it runs out of keys and prompts you to enter the next. Try it:

----: Q

SELECTed record name = "PRINT.ADMIN".
2 lines long.

----:

Two new commands become available within ED when you are using it with a select list in this way. The first, N, simply moves to the next record in the list without saving the current one (much as Q does, so I'm not entirely sure of the point to this command), while X leaves the editor altogether, regardless of the number of keys left in the select list. Use this to exit this example.

Most commands which operate on individual records will respond to select lists. The compiler BASIC will compile all the records (programs) in a select list, DELETE will delete them all, COPY will copy them all, and so on. You'll learn about these commands during our discussion of the TCL command language later.

Also, the UniVerse Basic programming language contains statements to read the keys from select lists, and so it is possible to write programs which are designed to be run once a select list is in memory, and thus can be applied to any group of records the user requires.

Intersecting select lists

One of the commands which will automatically work from an active select list is the SELECT command itself. This effectively means that by issuing a series of SELECT commands, the various lists produced can be intersected. For instance, to create a select list of three sampled M type COPY.OF.VOC records, try:

>SELECT COPY.OF.VOC WITH TYPE = 'M'

9 record(s) selected to SELECT list #0.
>>SELECT COPY.OF.VOC SAMPLE 3

3 record(s) selected to SELECT list #0.
>>LIST COPY.OF.VOC TYPE

LIST COPY.OF.VOC TYPE 14:52:46 08-19-99 PAGE 1
VOC......... TYPE

CONV.ACCT.ME M
NU
PRINT.ADMIN. M
MENU
BASIC.CONT M

3 records listed.
>

Of course, the same select list could have been built in one step by using the clause WITH TYPE = 'M' SAMPLE 3, but such simplification is not always easy, or even possible. Where it isn't, this intersecting behaviour is useful.

Numbered select lists

The examples above showed the use of the 'default' select list. In fact, UniVerse allows each user to store up to ten select lists, numbered 0 to 9. The default is number 0, and if the select command is specified without a select list number, the results are loaded into 0. To load a different numbered select list, use the TO keyword, as here:

>SELECT COPY.OF.VOC SAMPLE 3 TO 1

3 record(s) selected to SELECT list #1.
>>

Note that this time, the command prompt has not become >> as it did before. This is because only the default select list, list 0, will automatically be picked up by the following commands. The numbered select lists can be accessed by UniVerse Basic statements, and a few other commands which take select list number parameters, and are therefore used less often.

Saving, getting, and clearing lists

If you wish to, you can save your select list for use in the future. One advantage of this is that you can then use it more than once without the overhead of reselecting the records which make it up. To save a select list, use the command SAVE.LIST:

>SELECT COPY.OF.VOC SAMPLE 3

3 record(s) selected to SELECT list #0.
>>SAVE.LIST MYLIST

3 record(s) SAVEd to SELECT list "MYLIST".
>

The keys are actually written to a record called MYLIST in the file &SAVEDLISTS&: you may remember that this was one of the three UniVerse files created automatically when you first created your UniVerse account, along with VOC and VOCLIB. You can even look at the record with the editor:

ED &SAVEDLISTS& MYLIST
3 lines long.

----: P
0001: F9
0002: PRINT.ADMIN
0003: TEST.PARAGRAPH
Bottom at line 3.
----: Q
>

As you can see, it is a simple list, with each field bearing a key. In fact, you can create your own 'saved lists' using ED without ever issuing a SELECT command just by creating a record in &SAVEDLISTS&.

To activate your saved list, use the command GET.LIST:

>GET.LIST MYLIST

3 record(s) selected to SELECT list #0. >>

Finally, you can clear a list you don't plan to use with the CLEARSELECT command:

>CLEARSELECT
SELECT list number 0 cleared.

Any of these commands can be used with numbered select lists too, by using the forms:

SAVE.LIST listname FROM listnumber
GET.LIST listname TO listnumber
CLEARSELECT listnumber

Computers: Universe: A Note on SQL

With a few tweaks and reservations, UniVerse supports the Structured Query Language or SQL, which might be seen as an alternative to RetrieVe, particularly to those familiar with SQL after experience with database such as Oracle and Ingres.

From a technical point of view, this support is both impressive and worthwhile. Impressive, because SQL was not designed to deal with typeless, 'post-relational' (which means basically 'non-relational') databases like PICK. Worthwhile, because anything that smooths the conversion of a computer system from an existing base and preserves code is worthwhile.

However, I do not recommend the use of SQL for the development of new enquiries and reports, much less its use as the primary reporting engine in an entire system. If it's SQL you want, you really are better off using a product like Oracle, which was designed to work with it, and which extends it (via languages like 'PL/SQL' or 'Procedural SQL') into the primary development lanuage too: giving you a far more consistent development platform.

Successfull systems were being developed using PICK systems, and the forerunners of RetrieVe, well before SQL was supported. The SQL support does not fill any functional gap, but rather adds a handy piece of support when porting systems.

The issue is similar to that between vi and ED. Whatever objective comparisons might be made between the tools, they assume a level playing field which does not exist. ED and RetrieVe start with the enormouse advantage of having been specifically designed for the environment within which they work.

For these reasons, this course does not cover SQL, even though it is supported. If you already know it, you don't need my help with it. If you don't, don't learn it to use with UniVerse, spend the time learning RetrieVe.

Computers: Universe: The TCL Command Language

The UniVerse command language, called TCL under a number of PICK systems and PERFORM under Prime INFORMATION, was introduced very near the beginning of this course (see The Command Prompt).

Strictly speaking, TCL incorporates all the UniVerse commands shipped with UniVerse (as opposed to you add to the VOC file). Many of these have already been described fully in earlier sections: for instance, seeUniverse Files for CREATE.FILE, Listing Records for LIST, and The Editor - ED for, well, ED. This section introduces what I believe to be the best of the rest: the most common and useful commands not already mentioned. It makes no attempt to be comprehensive. For more specialised commands, and technically complete descriptions of each command, refer to the UniVerse documentation. This selection, though, will get you up and running confidently much more quickly than the sometimes ponderous reference guides.

Many commands have a number of different syntaxes, which allow them to do a number of different things: I haven't tried to show them all, again I focus on the most common and useful ones. Some of the uses are far from intuitive and are easy to tie yourself into knots with. For instance, here is an example COPY command:

COPY FROM INVOICES TO OLD.INVOICES 0001 0002

Now, even before reading the documentation, it'll be pretty clear that this copies records 0001 and 0002 from the INVOICES file to the OLD.INVOICES file. Now look at:

COPY FROM INVOICES TO OLD.INVOICES 0003,0004

Would you have guessed that this copies only one record, and then changes its key? And if both commands were in the same paragraph can you be sure that you, and future maintenance programmers, would notice the vital comma in the second command?

More computer time and utility is lost through bugs and maintenance work than is recovered by tiny performance improvements. Rather than use the 'copy and rename' version of COPY, recast the second command as follows:

COPY FROM INVOICES TO OLD.INVOICES 0003
CNAME OLD.INVOICES 0003,0004

It's difficult to imagine anyone misunderstanding this.

Computers: Universe: Menus of Commands

You can build menus for your applications without coding by using UniVerse's own 'menu procressor'. Just define your menu as a record in a menu definition file, entering lists of option names and associated commands. UniVerse then uses this information to display your menu, process the replies, and execute the commands.

First create a file to store your menus:

>CREATE.FILE MY.MENUS DYNAMIC
Creating file "MY.MENUS" as Type 30.
>

The UniVerse menu editor itself begins with a UniVerse menu. To bring it up onto your screen, enter the command:

>MENUS

UniVerse Menu Maintenance

 1. Enter/Modify       a menu
 2. Enter/Modify       a formatted menu
 3. Display            a summary of all menus on a menu file
 4. Display            the contents of a menu
 5. Enter/Modify       a VOC menu selector item
 6. Enter/Modify       a VOC stored sentence item
 7. Display            all menu selector items on the VOC file
 8. Display            all stored sentence items on the VOC file
 9. Display            the dictionary of a file
10. Print              a summary of all menus on a menu file
11. Print              the contents of a menu
12. Print              a virtual image of a menu on the printer
13. Print              the contents of a formatted menu
14. Print              the dictionary of a file
15. Print              detail of a menu, including VOC records referenced

Which would you like? ( 1 - 15 )  ?

Select option 1 to enter your new menu:

Which would you like? ( 1 - 15 ) ?1
Name of MENU file=

Your menu file is called MY.MENUS, so:

Name of MENU file=MY.MENUS

 MENU PROCESS DEFINITIONS  REVISE.1  Fri Aug 20 14:43:39 1999


MENU.NAME= 

You may find this sparse screen layout familiar. In fact, you've seen something like it before, because UniVerse uses REVISE to provide a menu maintenance screen (see The REVISE Command). For this example, we'll call your menu EXAMPLE.MENU:

MENU.NAME= EXAMPLE.MENU
New record.
TITLE= My example menu

MENU PROCESS DEFINITIONS -Screen 2-MENU SELECTION ITEMS Fri Aug 20 14:48:41 1999 MENU.NAME==> EXAMPLE.MENU No. DESC............................... ACTION......... EXP................. 1 DESCRIPTION=

Having entered a key for your menu record, and a title to display at the top of the menu, you are now prompted for the description of your first menu option. In fact, for each menu item you wish to create, you will be prompted for three pieces of information: a description (to display on the screen), an command to display on the screen if the menu option is selected by the user, and an optional 'explanation' to display if the user asks for help concerning the option.

The first command will display a simple VOC listing, so try the following values:

DESCRIPTION= List the VOC
ACTION= LIST VOC BY @ID
EXPLANATION= Display a sorted list of all the records in the VOC file

As soon as you have pressed return at the end of this explanation, you will be prompted for another menu item. Try this one:

DESCRIPTION= Say hello
ACTION= BLOCK.TERM HELLO
EXPLANATION= A warm greeting

Once you have finished entering options, simply press ENTER at the DESCRIPTION= prompt:

DESCRIPTION= (Press ENTER)

As usual, REVISE will redisplay the list of multivalues to allow you to change them. Press ENTER again:

MENU PROCESS DEFINITIONS -Screen 2-MENU SELECTION ITEMS Fri Aug 20 15:01:38 1999

MENU.NAME==> EXAMPLE.MENU
No. DESC............................... ACTION......... EXP.................
1 List the VOC LIST VOC BY @ID Display a sorted lis
2 Say hello BLOCK.TERM HELL A warm greeting
3

Change which line item= (Press ENTER)

Then press ENTER again to file the menu record:

MENU PROCESS DEFINITIONS -Screen 1-MENU NAME AND TITLE Fri Aug 20 15:03:21 1999

1 MENU.NAME EXAMPLE.MENU
2 TITLE My example menu

S1 == MENU NAME AND TITLE
S2 == MENU SELECTION ITEMS

CHANGE= (Press ENTER)

And (unusually for REVISE) enter QUIT when asked if you'd like to edit another menu record:

MENU PROCESS DEFINITIONS REVISE.1 Fri Aug 20 15:04:37 1999

MENU.NAME= QUIT

All of which will bring you back to the original menu:

UniVerse Menu Maintenance

 1. Enter/Modify       a menu
 2. Enter/Modify       a formatted menu
 3. Display            a summary of all menus on a menu file
 4. Display            the contents of a menu
 5. Enter/Modify       a VOC menu selector item
 6. Enter/Modify       a VOC stored sentence item
 7. Display            all menu selector items on the VOC file
 8. Display            all stored sentence items on the VOC file
 9. Display            the dictionary of a file
10. Print              a summary of all menus on a menu file
11. Print              the contents of a menu
12. Print              a virtual image of a menu on the printer
13. Print              the contents of a formatted menu
14. Print              the dictionary of a file
15. Print              detail of a menu, including VOC records referenced

Which would you like? ( 1 - 15 )  ?

Where you can finally press ENTER to return to the UniVerse prompt.

You need now to create a menu pointer in your VOC file before you can invoke your menu. The first line (like all VOC records) carries the type of the record, an M, followed by an optional description. The second line contains the name of the menu file, and the third the key to the menu record. Create one like this:

>ED VOC EXAMPLE.MENU
New record.

----: I
0001= M Example menu created during training
0002= MY.MENUS
0003= EXAMPLE.MENU
0004= (Press ENTER)
Bottom at line 3.
----: FI
"EXAMPLE.MENU" filed in file "MY.MENUS".
>

Finally invoke your menu via this menu pointer by typing:

>EXAMPLE.MENU

My example menu

 1. List the VOC
 2. Say hello

Which would you like? ( 1 - 2 )  ?

Trying option 1 displays:

LIST VOC BY @ID 15:16:11  20-08-99  PAGE 1
NAME..........    TYPE    DESC..........................

#                 K       Keyword - "Not Equal"
%                 K       Keyword - Calculate
                          percentages
&                 K       Keyword - The Boolean
                          conjunction "AND"
&COMO&            F       F 1,1 used for COMO listings
&DEVICE&          F       File - Contains all logical
                          device names
&ED&              F       F 0 0
&HOLD&            F       F
&MAP&             F       File - Used by MAKE.MAP.FILE
&PARTFILES&       F       File - Contains all parts of
                          Distributed Files
&PH&              F       F
&SAVEDLISTS&      F       F
&UFD&             F       File - Used by uniVerse to
                          access the current directory.
(                 K       Keyword - "Open Parenthesis"
)                 K       Keyword - "Close Parenthesis"
*                 K       Keyword - SQL multiplication
Press any key to continue...

Press Q to escape the listing and then press ENTER to return to the menu. Option 2 displays:

    HHHH    HHHH   EEEEEEEEEEEE   LLLL           LLLL            OOOOOOOOOO
    HHHH    HHHH   EEEEEEEEEEEE   LLLL           LLLL           OOOOOOOOOOOO
    HHHH    HHHH   EEEE           LLLL           LLLL           OOOO    OOOO
    HHHHHHHHHHHH   EEEEEEEEEE     LLLL           LLLL           OOOO    OOOO
    HHHHHHHHHHHH   EEEEEEEEEE     LLLL           LLLL           OOOO    OOOO
    HHHH    HHHH   EEEE           LLLL           LLLL           OOOO    OOOO
    HHHH    HHHH   EEEE           LLLL           LLLL           OOOO    OOOO
    HHHH    HHHH   EEEEEEEEEEEE   LLLLLLLLLLLL   LLLLLLLLLLLL   OOOOOOOOOOOO
    HHHH    HHHH   EEEEEEEEEEEE   LLLLLLLLLLLL   LLLLLLLLLLLL    OOOOOOOOOO













Press any key to return to the menu... 

Again, pressing ENTER will return you to the menu.

To display the help you entered for the options, enter an option number followed by a question mark:

Which would you like? ( 1 - 2 ) ?2?
A warm greeting

To access the general help on menus, which explains all this, simply enter a question mark:

Which would you like? ( 1 - 2 ) ??

                                   MENU
                                   ----





       Typing in the number preceding the description of the selection
             that you wish to run will start the desired process.


                 To exit from this menu, just type <RETURN>.


        If you wish further information about any selection, just type
          in the selection number followed by a question mark ("?").

   For example:
          "1?" will give further information on selection number one.




Press any key to return to the menu... 

Don't forget that each menu pointer in the VOC file is itself a valid command, and so can be invoked as the action of an option on another menu. Using this technique, you can develop nested menu structures.

The menu processor also allows you to create menus in which the exact coordinates at which option is displayed can be defined, as can the string the user must type in to escape the menu: but the principle behind them and the creation is much the same: as usual, refer to UniVerse documentation for the tricksy stuff.

Computers: Universe: Printer Commands

SETPTR

Syntax: SETPTR channel,width,length,top,bottom,mode,options

UniVerse uses numbered 'printer channels' to route information to printers. When you use an LPTR keyword to send your enquiry to a printer (see Listing Records) or a CP command to print a single record (see Record Commands), your output goes to the default channel: channel 0. Some commands and keywords, though (like LPTR) can be followed by a channel number, allowing you to print to any printer attached to a channel.

To link a printer to a channel, use the SETPTR command. In turn, the parameters are:

channel: a channel number between 0 and 255. 0 is the default channel.
width: the width of the paper on the printer (in characters)
length: the length of the paper on the printer (in lines)
top,bottom: the margins to allow at the top and bottom of the page (in lines)
mode: 1=output to printer, 3=output to record in &HOLD&file, (2=output to 'assigned device', see UniVerse documentation)
options: most important being AT unixprinterdevice (in mode 1) and AS filename (in mode 3), others can be found in the UniVerse documentation.

An example may help. The command...

SETPTR 0,80,66,3,2,1,AT laser001

...sets the default print channel to route output to the unix printer device laser001, formatted for pages of 66 lines of 80 characters each, and leaving 3 lines at the top and 2 at the bottom blank.

To 'print to disk' try something like:

SETPTR 0,80,66,3,2,3,AS MYOUTPUT

This formats the output the same way, but directs it into a record called MYOUTPUT in &HOLD& instead of to the printer.

SPOOL

Syntax: SPOOL -LIST or SPOOL -CANCEL jobnumber

To see the jobs currently waiting in the spool queue, enter the command SPOOL -LIST. To remove one from the queue, use SPOOL -LIST to find its job number, and then enter SPOOL -CANCEL jobnumber.

Computers: Universe: Record Commands

COUNT

Syntax: COUNT filename

Counts the records in filename.

CT

Syntax: CT filename recordkey

Displays a record on the screen (stands for 'Copy to Terminal'). If you don't want to actually change a record, saves you loading up the editor just to see what's in it: and eliminates the risk that you'll accidentally change it.

CP

Syntax: CP filename recordkey

As CT, but sends the output to the default printer.

COPY

Syntax: COPY FROM filename1 TO filename2 recordkey1 recordkey2...
or COPY FROM filename1 TO filename2 ALL

The first syntax shown here copies recordkey1 and recordkey2 from filename1 to filename2: unless, that is, records by these keys already exist on filename2, in which case they are not overwritten. The second command works the same way, but copies all of filename1's records.

To copy the records even if it means overwriting, add the word OVERWRITING to your command. To remove the records which get copied from filename1 (effectively moving the records) add DELETING. Finally, copying a lot of records can take a while, and watching a flashing cursor for a minute or more makes me nervous. To get feedback of the record keys as they're copied, add SQUAWK.

CNAME

Syntax: CNAME oldfilename TO newfilename
or CNAME filename oldrecordkey, newrecordkey

The first syntax changes the name of a file: changes both the key of the file pointer record in the VOC and the name of the corresponding UNIX files.

The second syntax changes the key of a record in the file.

EXCHANGE

Syntax: EXCHANGE filename recordkey1 recordkey2

OK, so this is not a command you will use every day, but I like it. This record swaps the contents of two records.

DELETE

Syntax: DELETE filename recordkey1 recordkey2...

Deletes records from a file. Will also work with a select list: just build your list and type DELETE filename.

CLEAR.FILE

Syntax: CLEAR.FILE filename

Removes all the records from a file. Better than deleting them all as it reinitialises the file, collecting all wasted space and so on. The command works from a select list: this is not a recommendation but a warning, for if you do a CLEAR.FILE with an active select list it will look for files with names like those in your list and clear them if it finds them.

Computers: Universe: Terminal Commands

SET.TERM.TYPE

Syntax: SET.TERM.TYPE terminalname

In order to properly control your display, UniVerse must know what kind of terminal you are using. Each terminal must be sent different sets of 'instruction strings' to do things like clear the screen, position the cursor, and so on. If you were using a DEC VT100 terminal you'd enter the command SET.TERM.TYPE VT100. You'd enter the same command, of course, if you were using a terminal which emulated a VT100, or a PC based 'terminal emulator' in VT100 mode.

To see the list of terminal types supported by your UniVerse installation, enter the SET.TERM.TYPE command without a terminal name. When you are prompted for one, enter a ?, and the names will be listed.

Some terminals, and most terminal emulators, can display a range of screen sizes other than the ubiquitous 80 columns by 24 rows. To persuade UniVerse to make use of the extra space in displaying enquiry results and so forth, enter the command SET.TERM.TYPE WIDTH numberofcols LENGTH numberofrows. You can also add the WIDTH and LENGTH keywords after the terminal name and thus set the terminal type, and its dimensions, in a single command.

The SET.TERM.TYPE command is often included in LOGIN paragraphs (see LOGIN, ON.EXIT and ON.ABORT): complete with a terminal name if the developer knows the kind of terminal his users will be using, and without if he does not (so that they will be prompted to choose one).

GET.TERM.TYPE

Syntax: GET.TERM.TYPE

Sister command to SET.TERM.TYPE, displays the current terminal type, width and length settings.

PTERM

Syntax: PTERM settingname setting

Use PTERM to define your terminal settings. To get a complete list of possible settingname values, simply type PTERM, and they will all be displayed along with their current values. By far the most import is PTERM ERASE (press erase key), which will define the key use wish to use to 'backspace' over mistyped characters. If you try PTERM ERASE..., and see the message PTERM: Option 'ERASE' requires an argument, it means that whatever key you pressed is already defined as the erase key, and effectively erased the space after the ERASE rather than being passed to PTERM as a parameter: in other words, you needn't worry.

CS

Syntax: CS

Clears the screen.

Computers: Universe: The VOC File

The VOC file lies at the heart of each UniVerse account. 'VOC' is short for 'vocabulary', the idea being that every word in the UniVerse command language is stored in this file.

By changing the VOC file, therefore, you can change the UniVerse command language itself within an account. This is an extremely useful but potentially risky process, and should be treated with some care.

One interesting and simple feature of the VOC file, which demonstrates its role in defining the command language, is that by editing any VOC record and saving it under another key, you effectively create a synonym for the original key. For instance, by editing the VOC record DISPLAY, and saving it as SHOW, you have can use SHOW wherever you previously might have used DISPLAY. This applies to any VOC record: whether it is a command name, a keyword or parameter, or a file name. Indeed, if you delete the original keyword, your new synonym becomes the only way of accessing the command: but of course doing this will break any routine which used the command under its old name and is therefore not recommended.

The previous sections describing the editor should have acclimatised you to editing VOC records. It described the process of creating a new VOC record, looking something like this:

ED VOC FLUFFY
New record.

----: I
0001= PA Rather silly example of a paragraph
0002= DISPLAY You have just entered the command 'FLUFFY'.
0003= DISPLAY This is not a terribly useful command.
0004= DISPLAY All it does is display this message.
0005= (Hit ENTER)
----: FILE
"FLUFFY" filed in file "VOC".

At the time, the main purpose was to explain the editor, so the notes merely touched on the meaning of these lines. In this section, they will be examined far more closely.

The first line is particularly important. It determines what the 'type' or purpose of each VOC record. In this case, the type is PA, short for 'paragraph'. Here, it is followed by a description or comment on the purpose of the VOC record. This too is common to the structure of all VOC records: after the type specifier on the first line, a comment or description may appear to document the VOC record for those who edit it in the future.

The meaning of the lines beyond the first depends on the type of record specified by the characters at the beginning of the first. These types are now discussed in turn.

Computers: Universe: File Pointers

Earlier in this course (see Universe and UNIX) we explored the relationship between what unix calls 'files' and what universe calls 'files'. to briefly recap: the terms are related, but not synonymous. depending on the type of the universe file (see Universe Files), what UniVerse calls a file may be implemented using any of a number of different combinations of UNIX directories and files.

Each file has a file pointer in the VOC of its parent environment: created by the CREATE.FILE command along with the UNIX portions of the file itself. The name of the VOC record defines the name of the file as it is known to UniVerse. The contents of the record tells UniVerse where to find the file within the UNIX filing structure.

To examine these file pointers, and the things they point to, we shall create three files: one directory file, one static file, and one dynamic file. Begin by creating the directory file with the command:

>CREATE.FILE DIRECTORY.FILE 19
WARNING: An operating system file will be created with a truncated name.
Creating file "DIRECTORY000" as Type 19.
Creating file "D_DIRECTORY000" as Type 3, Modulo 1, Separation 2.
Added "@ID", the default record for RetrieVe, to "D_DIRECTORY000".

This rather unfriendly and misleading series of messages is trying to tell us a number of things:

1. A UNIX directory called DIRECTORY000 has been created as the physical form of the UniVerse DIRECTORY.FILE file.

2. A UNIX file called D_DIRECTORY000 has been created as the physical form of the UniVerse DIRECTORY.FILE file. The purpose of dictionaries is covered later in the course. For now, it is worth noting simply that a file dictionary is, itself, an independent file, and that every 'data' file has a companion 'dictionary' file which describes its contents to utilities such as the RetrieVe query language. Whatever type you select for your file, UniVerse creates your dictionary files as type 3 (ie. static), modulo 1, separation 2.

A record with the key @ID has been added to this dictionary.

The UNIX file names chosen are interesting. CREATE.FILE creates two files, a main or 'data' file with the name 'X', and a 'dictionary' file with the name 'D_X'. UniVerse attempts to keep the names of the UNIX files it creates to 14 characters or less, and so applies the following naming scheme:

1. If the requested UniVerse file name is 12 characters or less in length, like TWELVE.CHARS, the name of the directory file created is the same, ie. TWELVE.CHARS, and the name of the UniVerse dictionary file is preceded by a D_ thus: D_TWELVE.CHARS.

2. If the requested UniVerse file name is more than twelve.characters in length, like OVER.TWELVE.CHARS, the name of the directory file created consists of the first nine characters of this name followed by a three digit suffix, in this case OVER.TWEL000. The dictionary file is prefixed in the usual way, giving D_OVER.TWEL000. The three digits are chosen so as to ensure the UNIX file name is unique. If UNIX file OVER.TWEL000 already exists, the file is called OVER.TWEL001, and so on.

Returning to the file DIRECTORY.FILE we created earlier, its file pointer looks like this:

ED VOC DIRECTORY.FILE
3 lines long.

----: P
0001: F
0002: DIRECTORY000
0003: D_DIRECTORY000
----:

As do all VOC records, file points store their type and an optional description in field 1.

Field 2 contains the name of the UNIX directory used to physically implement the main DIRECTORY.FILE file.

Field 3 contains the name of the UNIX file used to physically implement DIRECTORY.FILE's dictionary.

To create our example static file, enter the command:

>CREATE.FILE STATIC.FILE 2 1 4
Creating file "STATIC.FILE" as Type 2, Modulo 1, Separation 4.
Creating file "D_STATIC.FILE" as Type 3, Modulo 1, Separation 2.
Added "@ID", the default record for RetrieVe, to "D_STATIC.FILE".

The message which follows is very similar to the one we saw when creating DIRECTORY.FILE above. In this case, the UniVerse file name is less than 13 characters long, and so the corresponding UNIX file names are not abbreviated: but exactly the same naming conventions apply to the creation of static files as do to the creation of directory files.

In fact, the only difference here is that the 'data' file is implemented as a UNIX file (rather than a UNIX directory) because it is a UniVerse static file rather than a UniVerse directory file.

The file pointer to STATIC.FILE is much as you would expect.

ED VOC STATIC.FILE
3 lines long.

----: P
0001: F
0002: STATIC.FILE
0003: D_STATIC.FILE
----:

Finally, to create a dynamic file, enter the command:

>CREATE.FILE DYNAMIC.FILE DYNAMIC
Creating file "DYNAMIC.FILE" as Type 30.
Creating file "D_DYNAMIC.FILE" as Type 3, Modulo 1, Separation 2.
Added "@ID", the default record for RetrieVe, to "D_DYNAMIC.FILE".

As do directory and static files, dynamic files are created with static dictionaries, type 3, modulo 1, separation 2. Also, the same UNIX file naming conventions apply: as the UniVerse file name DYNAMIC.FILE is exactly 12 characters long, it is not truncated: but if it had been longer, it would have been.

The UNIX entity DYNAMIC.FILE is actually a directory. This is because the 'data' part of a dynamic file is implemented using exactly two UNIX files, alwats called DATA.30 and OVER.30, and these are stored in this directory: the former stores the 'ordinary' data, and the latter any data which has overflowed its groups. The names of these files therefore do not appear in the file's pointer, as they never vary: only the name of the directory containing them varies, and this appears in the pointer, which looks like this:

ED VOC DYNAMIC.FILE
3 lines long.

----: P
0001: F
0002: DYNAMIC.FILE
0003: D_DYNAMIC.FILE
----:

As all the files and directories named on fields 2 and 3 of file pointers are UNIX objects, UNIX can be used to move them from place to place. Furthermore, while we have only seen simple UNIX names in these file pointers, they are in fact relative paths which simply happen to point to the current directory: ie. the directory housing the current UniVerse account. It follows from this that it is possible to play lots of games with UniVerse file pointers and the UNIX objects they point to. For instance:

1. By editing a file pointer and saving it under a different name, you have now created a synonym by which the same file can be referred to: neither of which has any claim to being the 'real' name, and thus either of which might be used by different developers in their work, creating confusion and ambiguity.

2. By editing a file pointer, saving it under a different name, and deleting the original, you have effectively changed the name of the UniVerse file: and in the process broken any programs which refer to the file under the original name.

3. By moving the UNIX entities making up the file, and editing the file pointer to reflect the new paths on fields 2 and 3, you have effectively created a file with is nominally part of the account, but is not actually stored within the account directory. Therefore, if at some point someone backs up the directory (on the assumption that they are backing up the account), they will unknowingly omit this file and thus undermine the validity of the backup.

From my description of these activities, you will have gathered that I don't generally encourage them. There are few good reasons for imposing an artificial structure in place of UniVerse's own, and it is a common cause of error and corruption. The sole legitimate aim recorded above, that of creating synonyms, is better achieved using Q pointers: see the next topic Q Pointers.

Computers: Universe: Keywords

Keywords are generally parameters or modifiers applied to verbs. We came across one when we examined the CREATE.FILE filename DYNAMIC command, as DYNAMIC is a keyword.

Editing a keyword reveals the following:

ED VOC DYNAMIC
2 lines long.

----: P
0001: K
0002: 241
----:

The number in the second field is provided to whichever verb is being run, which understands it and modifies its behaviour accordingly. As keywords work by numbers in this way, they are not terribly interesting to edit.

One peculiarity, though, is that some words which are usually used as keywords may also be used as verbs in their own right. An example is the DISPLAY command we have used in many examples to date. The VOC record for DISPLAY looks like this:

ED VOC DISPLAY
3 lines long.

----: P
0001: K
0002: 258
0003: DISPLAY.VERB
----:

This indicates that the word DISPLAY has two entirely separate uses. If used as a keyword following some other verb, it is keyword 258: and it is up to the verb in question what to do if this keyword is specified. On the other hand, if used as a command in its own right, as in DISPLAY Hello mum!, the UniVerse command on the third line is executed instead. Editing this in turn reveals an ordinary verb.

ED VOC DISPLAY.VERB
4 lines long.

----: P
0001: V
0002: DISPLAY
0003: I
0004: GHNK
----:

Computers: Universe: Other VOC Records

In addition to the types of VOC record we have discussed, you will come across a number of others, which I will list briefly here chiefly for the sake of completeness.

Menu pointers: M

VOC records with M as the first character of their first fields are menu pointers, used to invoke UniVerse menus. To see them explained, turn to Menus of Commands.

'Global' dictionary records: D, I, PH, etc.

As has been briefly mentioned, records in the dictionary of a UniVerse file are used to describe the contents or layout of the main or data records. Their main use is to name and describe the fields available via the Retrieve query language. For instance, the record CUSTOMER.NUMBER in the dictionary of an INVOICES file allows the term CUSTOMER.NUMBER to appear in Retrieve enquiries based on that file. Some dictionary records, though, could apply to many files: for instance, a dictionary item called RECORD.LENGTH reporting the length of a record in bytes could be useful, and no matter what fields are stored in a record, every record has a particular length. To avoid having to set up dictionary items such as RECORD.LENGTH in every dictionary, you can save them instead in the VOC file, where Retrieve will be able to use them regardless of the file you are enquiring about. For more information about dictionary records, turn to Dictionaries.

'Data' records: 'X'

A few VOC records exist simply to store information or configuration details, rather than to support the UniVerse command language. These have an X at their beginning of their first field. One example, which you will find in every UniVerse account, is:

>ED VOC RELLEVEL
4 lines long.

----: P
0001: X
0002: 9.4.1.1
0003: INFORMATION
0004: INFORMATION.FORMAT
Bottom at line 4.
----: Q
>

Field 2 stores the release of UniVerse, and fields 3 and 4 define the 'flavour' of the UniVerse account (see UniVerse and PICK above),

X type VOC records should be used sparingly, or (preferably) not at all. The VOC file is central to the function and performance of the UniVerse account. Every additional X type makes the file larger and possibly slower to access, and removes a 'word' which would otherwise have been available to the UniVerse command language. If you find yourself planning many X type records, consider setting up a separate UniVerse file to store them, rather than littering the VOC with them.

Computers: Universe: Paragraphs

We have already encountered paragraphs during our discussion of the UniVerse editor. The FLUFFY record was a paragraph, if not a very useful one.

A paragraph is UniVerse's equivalent to an MS-DOS 'batch file' or UNIX 'script'. MS-DOS batch files are rarely more than lists of commands to be executed in a certain order. UNIX scripts, on the other hand, are often intelligent routines, containing their own variables, decision making and looping structures. UniVerse paragraphs lie somewhere between the two, but are rather nearer the MS-DOS end of the spectrum than the UNIX end. Complex processing is almost exclusively done in UniVerse Basic.

In-line prompts... <<...>>

At its simplest, then, a UniVerse paragraph is simply a list of UniVerse commands, written exactly as they would be typed at the UniVerse command prompt, such as FLUFFY. However, there are a few ways in which they can be made more flexible and useful. For example:

ED VOC RECLAIM
2 lines long.

----: P
0001: PA
0002: RESIZE <<I2,Enter filename to RECLAIM>> * * * CONCURRENT
Bottom at line 2.
----: Q

This paragraph illustrates a device called an in-line prompt. In-line prompts make paragraphs more useful by allowing you to prompt for details of the commands be executed at run time. In the example above, the standard UniVerse command RECLAIM simply uses RESIZE to resize a file without changing its type, modulo or separation: hence the * * * parameters (for details of the RESIZE command, see Static Files above). As was mentioned during the discussion of the RESIZE command, this has the effect of reorganising the file internally and reclaiming pockets of unused space created during the addition and deletion of records into groups.

The interesting thing here, of course, is that the creator of the paragraph could not know in advance which file the user would wish to reclaim. Instead of specifying a file name, therefore, he used the <<...>> syntax to create an in-line prompt.

The I2 before the comma in the inland prompt stands for Input word 2. It means that if the user enters the command RECLAIM CUSTOMERS, the second word (CUSTOMERS) will be substituted into the command, making the overall command RESIZE CUSTOMERS * * * CONCURRENT. On the other hand, if the user simply enters RECLAIM, the paragraph will display the following prompt:

RECLAIM
Enter file name to RECLAIM=

At this prompt, the user could enter CUSTOMERS to reclaim the customers file.

Try it: make up a fictional file name if you don't want to sit and wait for RESIZE to do its stuff. You'll get an error message reporting that your file name is invalid, but this will illustrate the principle just as well.

There are many different flavours of in-line prompt. The simplest form is just <<promptstring>>. This ignores any parameters which may have been typed in on the command line and simply displays the prompt promptstring to request a value from the user. Note that if more than one in-line prompt with the prompt promptstring appears in your paragraph, the prompt promptstring will only be displayed once, and the value entered will be used for them all.

This is usually helpful, but if you want to force a fresh prompt even if you are using the same prompt string, you can use the A, prefix thus: <<A,promptstring>>.

A variation on the In prefix used by RECLAIM (which you'll recall used the nth word from the command line if it was there, but prompted for it if it wasn't) is the Cn prefix. This also uses the nth word from the command line, but evaluates to nothing (ie. an empty string) if it isn't. Sn is subtely different again, using parameters not taken from the command line used to run the paragraph, but rather from the command line originally entered by the user. These are different when, say, the user enters the command PARA1 A B C, and one of the lines in PARA1 is PARA2 X Y Z. In this case, C3 evaluates to Y, but S3 to B.

If you need to substitute more than one value into your command, use R,. This will prompt repeatedly until the user enters an empty value by hitting return. The list of values entered is then inserted into the command separated by spaces. This sounds worse than it is: an example should make it clear:

ED VOC ENTER.WORDS
New record.

----: I
0001= PA
0002= DISPLAY You entered "<<R,Enter words>>"
0003= Press RETURN
Bottom at line 3.
----: FI
"ENTER.WORDS" filed in file "VOC".

The paragraph runs like this:

ENTER.WORDS
Enter words=AREN'T
Enter words=IN-LINE PROMPTS
Enter words=WONDERFUL
Enter words= Press Return
You entered "AREN'T IN-LINE PROMPTS WONDERFUL"

If you wish to separate the words entered using an R type in-line prompt with something other than a space, specify R(c) where c is the character you like to see between each entry. For instance, the result the paragraph above would have given if written with an R(*) in place of the R would have been:

You entered "AREN'T*IN-LINE PROMPTS*WONDERFUL"

Note that the space between the words IN-LINE and PROMPTS remains: this is because it was actually entered as part of the string, and not automatically added by the in-line prompt in response to RETURN.

You can jazz up your prompts using @(CLR) to clear the screen before the prompt appears, @(BELL) to sound the terminal bell when the prompt is displays, and @(col,row) to position the prompt at column col, row row. You can use these in combination with each other, or the options above. For instance, try just typing in the following at the UniVerse command prompt:

DISPLAY You entered "<<@(CLR),@(BELL),R(*),Enter words>>"

This will clear the screen and beep, before repeatedly prompting Enter words= until you press RETURN to enter an empty string, and finally display the words you entered separated by asterisks.

This last example illustrates an interesting point: in-line prompts are not restricted to use in paragraphs, but are actually features of the command language itself, and you can, in principle, use them in any command. It is unusual to use them in a directly entered command, but not unheard of. For instance, if you had to compile a large number of different records in the BP file, you might enter the command:

BASIC BP <<Enter BP record key>>
Enter BP record key=PROGRAM1
Compiling: Source = 'BP/PROGRAM1', Object = 'BP.O/PROGRAM1'
*****************

Compilation Complete.

Why? Well, when you come to compile the next program, you can just...

.X
Enter BP record key=PROGRAM2
Compiling: Source = 'BP/PROGRAM1', Object = 'BP.O/PROGRAM1'
**********************************

Compilation Complete.

So in this case, the in-line prompts are stored as part of the stack, and when the command is re-executed, the in-line prompt is again used to find out which program you wish to compile. Neat, huh?

By typing in HELP and using the cursor to select the <<...>> topic, you can see the on-line documentation describing the use of in-line prompts, and learn a few other tricks not described here: but these are the most commonly used features.

Logic and flow control in paragraphs... IF/THEN, GO, LOOP and REPEAT

You can add conditional logic to your paragraph using the IF command. For instance:

ED VOC TEST.PARAGRAPH
New record.

----: I
0001= PA
0002= IF <<Display something?>> = 'Y' THEN DISPLAY Ok, "something".
0003= Press RETURN
Bottom at line 2.
----: FI
"TEST.PARAGRAPH" filed in file "VOC".

Try running this command twice, entering a Y the first time...

TEST.PARAGRAPH
Display something?=Y
Ok, "something".

...and N the second time...

TEST.PARAGRAPH
Display something?=N

While you can make a single line conditional in this way, IF is more commonly used in conjunction with another command, GO, which can cause the flow of execution to jump to another line of your paragraph.

The following example is typical:

ED VOC TEST.PARAGRAPH.2
New record.

----: I
0001= PA
0002= IF <<(E)nglish or/o e(S)pañol?>> = 'E' THEN GO ENGLISH.MESSAGE
0003= IF <<(E)nglish or/o e(S)pañol?>> = 'S' THEN GO SPANISH.MESSAGE
0004= DISPLAY E or S only please/E o S solomente por favor
0005= GO END
0006= ENGLISH.MESSAGE:
0007= DISPLAY Hello!
0008= DISPLAY How are you?
0009= GO END
0010= SPANISH.MESSAGE:
0011= DISPLAY ¡Ola!
0012= DISPLAY ¿Como esta usted?
0013= END:

This paragraph prompts the user with a choice of language, and displays messages an appropriate message. It works well enough: but the problem is that if the user enters something other than an 'E' or an 'S', he is given no chance to correct his mistake: the paragraph displays an error message and terminates.

In attempting to solve this problem, you might be tempted to edit the paragraph until it looked like this:

0001: PA
0002: GET.LANGUAGE:
0003: IF <<A,(E)nglish or/o e(S)pañol?>> = 'E' THEN GO ENGLISH.MESSAGE
0004: IF <<(E)nglish or/o e(S)pañol?>> = 'S' THEN GO SPANISH.MESSAGE
0005: DISPLAY E or S only please/E o S solomente por favor
0006: GO GET.LANGUAGE
0007: ENGLISH.MESSAGE:
0008: DISPLAY Hello!
0009= DISPLAY How are you?
0010= GO END
0011= SPANISH.MESSAGE:
0012= DISPLAY ¡Ola!
0013= DISPLAY ¿Como esta usted?
0014= END:

Note the highlighted changes. First, a new prompt has been inserted above the language prompt. Secondly, an A, has been added to the first in-line prompt, so that if it must be used again, the paragraph will force it to be displayed even though it has an existing value. Lastly, a GO has been added to return the user to the prompt should the value he enters be invalid.

It all looks good. You can enter it and try it... or you can save yourself the trouble and read on, because it won't work. The problem is that GO statements cause the UniVerse command processor to search down the paragraph for the appropriate label: if the label is above the GO, it will not be found.

To allow you to repeat a section of a paragraph in the way being attempted here, you must use the LOOP and REPEAT commands: the former marking the beginning of the section you wish to repeat, and the latter marking the end. Rewriting the paragraph above using these new commands gives you:

0001: PA
0002: LOOP
0003: IF <<A,(E)nglish or/o e(S)pañol?>> = 'E' THEN GO ENGLISH.MESSAGE
0004: IF <<(E)nglish or/o e(S)pañol?>> = 'S' THEN GO SPANISH.MESSAGE
0005: DISPLAY E or S only please/E o S solomente por favor
0006: REPEAT
0007: ENGLISH.MESSAGE:
0008: DISPLAY Hello!
0009= DISPLAY How are you?
0010= GO END
0011= SPANISH.MESSAGE:
0012= DISPLAY ¡Ola!
0013= DISPLAY ¿Como esta usted?
0014= END:

The label and GO which were used to try and create a loop in the previous paragraph are here replaced by LOOP and REPEAT. This paragraph will now work as expected.

Most languages which provide statements like LOOP and REPEAT also provide some kind of WHILE or UNTIL condition which tells the program when to exit the loop: UniVerse Basic, for instance, does. However, the UniVerse command language does not: LOOP/REPEAT loops will loop forever, or until you GO to a label outside the loop: so be warned.

Computers: Universe: Q Pointers

In our discussion of file pointers (see File Pointers above), we discussed the danger of creating multiple file pointers simply in order to provide synonyms by which a file could be accessed. As the file pointer is the only thing which defines a file name under UniVerse, having more than one file pointer effectively gives the same file two names: and provides no clue to users that the two files are in fact the same, unless they take the trouble to edit the pointer records themselves.

To illustrate the risks, try the following:

>CREATE.FILE DIRECTORY.FILE 19
WARNING: An operating system file will be created with a truncated name.
Creating file "DIRECTORY000" as Type 19.
Creating file "D_DIRECTORY000" as Type 3, Modulo 1, Separation 2.
Added "@ID", the default record for RetrieVe, to "D_DIRECTORY000".
>

The next stage in our illustration involves creating a 'synonym' file pointer to this file. In the last section, we did this by creating a new VOC record with the editor: and this is commonly the way it is done. UniVerse does, however, provide a command which achieves the same thing: so for the sake of learning this command, we shall use it instead:

>SETFILE

Enter DATA file pathname = DIRECTORY000

What do you want to call it in your VOC file = DIRECTORY.FILE.POINTER

Establishing file pointer:
Pathname "DIRECTORY000"
VOC Name "DIRECTORY.FILE.POINTER"
OK to establish pointer (Y/N) ? Y

Pointer "DIRECTORY.FILE.POINTER" established in VOC file.
>

This creates a VOC record in exactly the same way as you could with the editor, as you can check:

>ED VOC DIRECTORY.FILE.POINTER
3 lines long.

----: P
0001: F
0002: DIRECTORY000
0003: D_DIRECTORY000
Bottom at line 3.
----: Q
>

Now enter the command:

>DELETE.FILE DIRECTORY.FILE.POINTER
DELETEd "DIRECTORY000", Type 19.
DELETEd file "D_DIRECTORY000", Type 3, Modulo 1.
DELETEd file definition record "DIRECTORY.FILE.POINTER" in the VOC file.
>

You have been allowed to delete the file using the file pointer you only created as a synonym. While the VOC record DIRECTORY.FILE.POINTER has been deleted, DIRECTORY.FILE is still there, and now points to a non-existant path. You can demonstrate this to yourself by entering a command to count the number of records in DIRECTORY.FILE:

>COUNT DIRECTORY.FILE
Unable to open "DIRECTORY.FILE" file.
>

A good principle to maintain, therefore, is that you should only have one file pointer to each file: which uniquely defines the file's 'real' name.

There are legitimate reasons, though, why you might wish to create a synonym to a file name. You might, for instance, be working at a site where two or more languages are in common use: say English and Afrikaans in South Africa, or English and Spanish in the United States. Having created your files using names consistently selected from one language, you might wish to create synonyms for each filename in the second language.

But perhaps the most common reason to create file synonyms is to allow a file which was created within one UniVerse account to be accessed from another. It was explained earlier in the course (see The UniVerse Paradigm above) that UniVerse observed a strict and simple hierarchy: accounts contained files, files contained records, and so on. It was also explained that each account was an entirely independent entity, with it's own VOC file defining its own command environment. However, by using file synonyms, it is possible to access a file in one account from another.

Both of these aims can best be achieved using a Q pointer. For the sake of our examples, we will create another new file:

>CREATE.FILE CUSTOMER.FILE DYNAMIC
WARNING: An operating system file will be created with a truncated name.
Creating file "CUSTOMER.000" as Type 30.
Creating file "D_CUSTOMER.000" as Type 3, Modulo 1, Separation 2.
Added "@ID", the default record for RetrieVe, to "D_CUSTOMER.000". >

To create a synonym in a second language is extremely simple. The example here is in Afrikaans:

>ED VOC KLANT.FILE
New record.

----: I
0001= Q
0002= (Put in a space)
0003= CUSTOMERS.FILE
0004= (Press RETURN)
Bottom at line 3.
----: FI
"KLANT.FILE" filed in file "VOC".
>

The first line of this VOC record, like the first line of all VOC records, indicates the type of the record. Q pointers carry, unsurprisingly (and for no particular reason) a Q. The second line contains the name of the UniVerse account in which the file lives. If it is left blank (as here), then the file is assumed to be in the same account as the Q pointer itself. The third line contains the name of the file: note that this is the UniVerse name, not the UNIX name. You can now use the name KLANT.FILE to refer to the file CUSTOMER.FILE. Try it:

>COUNT KLANT.FILE

0 records counted.
>

You can set up a Q pointer to a file in another account just as easily, though any example of this would depend on the names of the accounts as installed on your system. Suffice to say that an account name entered on line 2 of the Q pointer will refer the pointer to that account when seeking the file on line 3.

Note that Q pointers contain no UNIX paths. The account name on line 2 is a UniVerse account name, and the file name on line 3 is a UniVerse file name. When you use the pointer, UniVerse consults it's internal list of account names to resolve the location of the account, and then looks in the VOC file of the account it finds to resolve the location of the file. This is a great strength. If a UniVerse account is moved, provided the UniVerse administrator updates the list of accounts within the UniVerse system administration menu, and external Q pointers pointing to a file in the moved account will continue to work: foreign file pointers, though, dependent on a particular UNIX path to access the file, will be broken. Equally, consider the situation if someone were to delete and then recreate the CUSTOMER.FILE file. The UNIX name of the file might well change (you'll remember that the three digits at the end of this name are essentially arbitary), but as long as the UniVerse file name is the same, any Q pointer will still work. A F type synonym, which relies on an absolute UNIX path, though, will break.

But the real pay-off is that UniVerse 'knows' that a Q pointer is just a synonym, and not the real file name. Try the command:

>DELETE.FILE KLANT.FILE
"KLANT.FILE" is already in your VOC file as a type "Q" record.
File name =(just press RETURN)
>

The word 'already' in the error message is ridiculously misleading: the reason the file cannot be deleted is not because the VOC pointer is 'already' there, but because it is a Q pointer. However, the point is that the file cannot be deleted. By and large, you can access your file via a Q pointer exactly as you could via an F, but certain important functions are reserved for the 'real' F pointer.

One final absurdity: in the same way that there is a SETFILE command to create F type pointers, there is a command to create Q pointers: it is called SET.FILE. That's right, the only difference between the two is the dot between SET and FILE. The reasons are historical: the SETFILE command came first, and preceded the invention of Q pointers. When Q pointers came along, it was realised that these provided a better way of creating synonyms, but to change the SETFILE command to create Q pointers might break existing applications. Therefore, a new command was commissioned, called SET.FILE. Go figure. I tend to avoid them both, as it's just as easy (and less prone to error) to set up such pointers by hand. For the sake of completeness, though, here is an example of SET.FILE being used to set up another Q pointer to the CUSTOMER.FILE:

SET.FILE
Q name: CLIENT.FILE
Account: (press RETURN)
File: CUSTOMER.FILE
Q-pointer written to VOC file.
>

Today's main message is, though: leave your default F type pointers as they are on file creation, and use only Q pointers to refer provide synonyms and access from other Universe accounts.

Computers: Universe: Remote Commands

A remote command is a pointer in the VOC file to a command record stored in another file. Typing in the name of the remote command record causes the command pointed to to execute.

The first line of a remote command carries its type (as do all VOC records): in this case, an R.

The second line contains the name of the file which contains the command record to be executed.

The third line contains the key to the command record to be executed.

An example follows:

>ED VOC DO.SOMETHING
New record.

----: I
0001= R
0002= VOCLIB
0003= SOMETHING
0004= (Press RETURN)
Bottom at line 3.
----: FI
"DO.SOMETHING" filed in file "VOC".
>

The command record pointed to by this record might run as follows:

>ED VOCLIB SOMETHING
New record.

----: I
0001= PA
0002= DISPLAY What would you like me to do? Go away.
0003= (Press RETURN)
Bottom at line 2.
----: FI
"SOMETHING" filed in file "VOCLIB".
>

Testing this example of a remote command produces the result:

>DO.SOMETHING
What would you like me to do? Go away.

Remote commands have two main uses:

1. Some commands, particularly long paragraphs, can be extremely large records. Large records can damage the performance of static files by causing overflow (see above, Static Files): and the voc is a static file. as every command, every parameter and every filename referenced by a universe application must be read from the voc before it can be interpreted, an overflowed voc file can cause an entire application to perform badly. by using a remote control, large voc records can be moved into another file, and replaced with small remote control records which point to them. in principle and file can be used to store the command, but he file voclib (short for 'voc library') is provided specifically for this purpose, and rather than allowing commands to be stored in many different files, it is probably better to keep them solely to the VOC and VOCLIB files. Note that in the example above I called the remote command DO.SOMETHING and the command itself SOMETHING, to minimise the danger that they would be confused. However, most commonly remote commands point to commands with the same name in the VOCLIB file: and this is good practice to follow.

2. Remote commands can carry an extra, fourth field, which is the name of a globally cataloged UniVerse Basic subroutine. Unless you have previous knowledge of UniVerse, this phrase will not mean much to you yet: but by the end of the section on UniVerse Basic you will know how to create these. They are simply a particular kind of program. If the name of such a program is included on the fourth line of a remote control, the program is run before the command is executed. If the program returns a '0' value in its final parameter, the command is not executed, and a security violation message is displayed. In this way, it is possible to apply security control to individual commands in the UniVerse command language: and this is the main purpose of this feature. However, it can also be used to log activity, provide help, or indeed anything that can be achieved using UniVerse Basic.

The program named on the fourth line of a remote control record accepts and returns certain parameters, another term which may be familiar to you from other programming languages, but will be covered in depth later. For now, it is worth recording the names of these parameters, so that you can return to this section once you're writing such programs:

REMOTE.COMMAND

|

The remote command VOC record itself

COMMAND

|

The command the user typed in, complete with parameters

LEVEL

|

0=Command typed in at UniVerse prompt, 1=Command invoked by another command, or 2=Command invoked by a command invoked by a command (or even more layered)

PORT

|

User's port number

ACCOUNT

|

The name of the account the user is in

USER

|

The user's login name

FLAG

|

Value returned by the program, 1 allowing the command to execute, 0 preventing it

Computers: Universe: Sentences

A sentence is basically just a paragraph (see Paragraphs above) with only one command.

Compare...

>ED VOC TEST.PA
New Record.

----: I
0001= PA
0002= DISPLAY Hello mum!
0003=
Bottom at line 2.
----: FI
"TEST.PA" filed in file "VOC".
>TEST.PA
Hello mum!

...with...

>ED VOC TEST.S
New Record.

----: I
0001= S
0002= DISPLAY Hello mum!
0003=
Bottom at line 2.
----: FI
"TEST.S" filed in file "VOC".
>TEST.S
Hello mum!

The results are identical. In fact, there are only two differences between sentences and paragraphs:

1. Any parameters entered after the sentence name on the UniVerse command line are automatically added to the end of the command in the sentence before it is executed.

Using the paragraph and sentence created above, compare the command...

TEST.PA ...and dad!
Hello mum!

...with...

TEST.S ...and dad!
Hello mum! ...and dad!

The sentence automatically appended the parameters ...and dad! to its DISPLAY command before executing. To read the command parameters in the paragraph, you would have had to use in-line prompts (see Paragraphs above).

2. Sentences simply ignore all commands after the first.

Compare...

>ED VOC TEST.PA.2
New Record.

----: I
0001= PA
0002= DISPLAY Hello mum!
0003= DISPLAY Hello dad!
0004=
Bottom at line 3.
----: FI
"TEST.PA.2" filed in file "VOC".
>TEST.PA.2
Hello mum!
Hello dad!

...with...

>ED VOC TEST.S.2
New Record.

----: I
0001= S
0002= DISPLAY Hello mum!
0003= DISPLAY Hello dad!
0004=
Bottom at line 3.
----: FI
"TEST.S.2" filed in file "VOC&quot.
>TEST.S.2
Hello mum!

Note that while the paragraph displayed both messages, the sentence only displayed the first.

Computers: Universe: Verbs

Verbsare all command words. Enter a verb at the UniVerse prompt, and something will happen: even if it is only the display of a message telling you that the verb requires more parameters than you have supplied.

Several of the commands you have used in previous sections are verbs. They include:

SH: The UNIX shell command.

HELP The on-line manual command.

ED: The editor command itself.

Let's examine the SH command in more depth:

ED VOC SH
4 lines long.

----: P
0001: V
0002: /bin/sh
0003: U
0004: TICRG
Bottom at line 4.
----:

The V on the first line indicates that this is a verb. Like any VOC item, a verb can store a description after the word V.

Verbs work by running programs, and the name of the program they run appears on the second line. Here, it is the UNIX shell program /bin/sh.

The third line of the verb indicates what kind of program is being run. It can take any of the following values:

Letter

|

Program Language

B

|

UniVerse Basic

C

|

C shell script

D

|

DOS batch file

E

|

'External'

I

|

'Internal'

P

|

'Primitive'

Q

|

Query command

S

|

Bourne shell script

U

|

Operating System command

I provide the complete list for reference, but in most cases you will only need two understand two of these. B links a verb to a UniVerse Basic program. When you cover UniVerse Basic programming a little later, it is worth bearing in mind that you can create a new UniVerse verb by linking a V type VOC record to a UniVerse Basic program. U links a verb to an Operating System command. In the main, you can use verbs with a U on their third line to provide UniVerse versions of your favourite UNIX commands: but test these carefully. While most such links are well-behaved, some UNIX processes resent being invoked from inside UniVerse, and thus behave a little oddly.

Finally, the fourth line contains a series of one-letter codes which determine the kind of environment or setup required by the verb. These are all rather technical, and beyond the scope of this document. They are not always necessary, and for now you may simply leave this line clear and consult the UniVerse documentation only if your new verb behaves oddly.